<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The covenant of grace opened: wherein these particulars are handled; viz. 1. What the covenant of grace is, 2. what the seales of the covenant are, 3. who are the parties and subjects fit to receive these seales. From all which particulars infants baptisme is fully proved and vindicated. Being severall sermons preached at Hartford in New-England. / By that reverend and faithfull minister of the gospel, Mr Thomas Hooker.</title>
            <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 246 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E562_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11285</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858980</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858980</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111041</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86524)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111041)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E562[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The covenant of grace opened: wherein these particulars are handled; viz. 1. What the covenant of grace is, 2. what the seales of the covenant are, 3. who are the parties and subjects fit to receive these seales. From all which particulars infants baptisme is fully proved and vindicated. Being severall sermons preached at Hartford in New-England. / By that reverend and faithfull minister of the gospel, Mr Thomas Hooker.</title>
                  <author>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 85, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Dawson, and are to be sold at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 3d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregational churches --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Covenant theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, American --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111041:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111041:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COVENANT OF GRACE OPENED: WHEREIN Theſe particulars are handled; viz.
<list>
                  <item>1. What the Covenant of GRACE is,</item>
                  <item>2. What the Seales of the Covenant are,</item>
                  <item>3. Who are the Parties and Subjects fit to receive theſe Seales.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>From all which Particulars Infants Baptiſme is fully proved and vindicated.</p>
            <p>Being ſeverall Sermons preached at <hi>Hartford</hi> in New-England.</p>
            <p>By that Reverend and faithfull Miniſter of the Goſpel, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> THOMAS HOOKER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Dawſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Crown in <hi>Popes-head Alley.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111041:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111041:2"/>
            <head>THE Covenant of Grace opened in ſeverall Sermons.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>neſ. 17.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>Abraham</hi> took <hi>Iſhmael</hi> his ſonne, and all that were born in his houſe, and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe, and Circumciſed the fleſh of their foreskin, in the ſelf-ſame day, as God had ſaid unto him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſcope of this Chapter is to ſhew the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> by adding the ſeal of Circumciſion, and it's inſtituted by the cutting off the fore-skin of every male in his houſe; where we may ſee the obedience of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> he does it without any neglect upon all the males in his houſe: The occaſion of this is, becauſe there are a generation of Anabaptiſts that do go about ſecretly to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce perſons, and lead them into errour; and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reſie is a mark they are known by. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14. <hi>That we be no more children carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with every winde of Doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſſe whereby they lye in wait to deceive:</hi> the word is taken from Cheators, that by cunning deceive men; and therefore to clear the coaſt, and ſo prove the lawfulneſſe of the Baptizing of children againſt ſuch deceivers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctr.</hi> There is no weaknes of Faith in perſons received into the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111041:3"/>Church, nor want of years in thoſe that are born of them that ſhould hinder them from receiving the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>l of the Covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>You may ſee here <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his family circumciſed, now you may judge in your ſelves, whether in ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> had, it be not likely there were ſome weal ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſome, if not many doubting, being clouded b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſon of f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>leſſe; in which regard, they might have bin hindred: &amp; alſo it may be thought there were many children in the family, being ſo large, for he had 300. when he went to reſcue <hi>Lot,</hi> and this was ſome good ſpace of time after; and the text ſaith, All were circumciſed, none were hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred: and what was ſaid of <hi>Abraham</hi> in this truth, the ſame way be ſaid of all truths of the ſame kinde; this is the point.</p>
            <p>Now for the opening of it,
<list>
                  <item>1. what this Covenant of Grace is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the ſame that <hi>Abraham</hi> had, that we have now in the times of the Goſpel?</item>
                  <item>2. What are the ſeals of this Covenant, or are they of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture now as they were then?</item>
                  <item>3. The Parties and ſubjects fit to receive theſe ſeals; all the men and children in a family; whether they are not the ſame at this day?</item>
                  <item>4. In caſe ſome ſhould be unworthy; yet if they walk ſo, as in the judgement of charity, there do nothing appear that make them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; whether may not the Church in that caſe give them the Seals?</item>
                  <item>5. We will ſhew you the reaſons of the point.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, What is meant by the Covenant of Grace? this Covenant of Grace, ſo much as ſerves my turn at this time, it is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of God to a people, that he will chooſe ſuch, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ingages himſelf to be their God, and to make them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people.</p>
            <p>I adde that, to make them to be his people, becauſe that is it, that bears up the Covenant and confirms it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, When God gave a covenant to <hi>Adam,</hi> it was <hi>doe and live;</hi> and if he had improved that, he and his poſterity might have had life thereby: but now in the covenant of grace it is otherwiſe now, God gives himſelf freely to his, and makes them to be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo that he will be our God, and make us to be his people; this is the covenant of grace, and it may be conſidered in a double no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I finde a double covenant, an inward, and an outward.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Inward, ſtanding in a ſpirituall inſtitution of it between God and man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein God cals a people, and makes them anſwer his call, and makes himſelf really their God by Faith, and ſo they have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111041:3"/>unintereſt in God, and he performs it in them, and makes himſelf theirs by Faith; ſo that the work is his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are partakers of this covenant ſhall never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all; but this is to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is an outward covenant, and this is tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e large; the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation of this, God gives on his part to Chriſtians, and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement on their part, is ſubjection to him; and by this, God does advance a people: by outward diſpenſation he declares himſelf to be their God, and thereby takes them to be his people in a choice manner, and peculiar to himſelf. Exodus 19.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Now a handfore, if you will hear my voice indeed, and keep my covenant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you ſhall bee my chiefe treaſure above all people, though all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mine.</hi> He will diſcover himſelf to them, and impropriate them unto himſelf: hence they are called the lot of his inheritance, <hi>Deutr.</hi> 32.9. and God is ſaid to know them above all the Nations in the world; <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. He doth ingage himſelf unto them, and if they anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the outward priviledge, he will make them a choice people, and own them in that ingagement, and improve himſelf for their good; if they yeeld their Allegiance to him, he will enlarge himſelf to them in his diſpenſations to them; and doth avouch himſelf to be theirs, as they avouch the Lord to be their God; <hi>Deutr.</hi> 26.17.118. This is done by the outward covenant, and it is if they keep his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tents; hence, when they imbrace the ordinances, God is ſaid to draw neer to them, <hi>Deutr.</hi> 4.78. and they neer to him: all nations may be ſaid to be farr from God that want theſe outward covenants, and he from them; and therefore he is ſaid to dwel among them, and they to dwel with him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84.10. <hi>A day in thy Courts is better then a thouſand:</hi> God takes ſpeciall notice of them, and he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> every moment, and keeps them night and day: hence they are ſaid to come under the wing of God, that is under the ſpeciall expreſſions of his favour.</p>
            <p>The former of theſe covenants ſhould alway be between God and his people; and where it is, it never fails, if they receive the ſpirit working of it in them.</p>
            <p>But this outward is more large, the inward is more ſure; the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is larger, and may iſſue from falſe grounds, and may aym at falſe ends; ſometime yeeld in conviction, thus <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utr.</hi> 5.27. <hi>God neare and hear all that God ſhall ſay, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it unto us; and we will heare it and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. So they were convinced, for the Lord ſaith in the following verſe, <hi>they have well ſaid all that they have ſaid.</hi> When they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:111041:4"/>the mountain burning, their conſciences began to be awakned, and this made them ſpeak wall; but oh that there were ſuch a heart in them, but their heart would not hear to ſubmit: ſometimes men hear for novelties, and that prevailes. But we ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Joſhua</hi> when he was to take his leave of the world, and to draw near to his death; <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he ſaith, <hi>If it ſeem evill unto you to ſerve the Lord, chuſe you this day whom you will ſerve, &amp;c.</hi> the anſwer is, the Lord ſorbid that wee ſhould ſerve other Gods, for he brought us out of the land of Egypt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. So he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was a convicting conſcience; and ſometime God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of them, makes them ſay, <hi>we will ſerve the Lord,</hi> but yet they would not doe what they ſaid. Thus we ſee, this outward co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is more large, and may ariſe from falſe grounds, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.13. <hi>though ſhe was marryed to God, yet her heart was not with him;</hi> ſo in <hi>Deutr.</hi> 29.4. <hi>Yet the Lord hath not given an heart to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor eyes to ſee, nor ears to hear unto this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here may be a queſtion, whether the Covenant of grace be the ſame in the time of the Goſpel, with that in the time of the Law?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> In regard of the ſubſtance it is the ſame; though it may differ in ſome outward ceremonies or circumſtances, yet there is no difference in the ſubſtance of it. Now the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it; call it a carnall covenant, in regard of this that is now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but as one hath ſaid, <hi>it is a carnall conceit in them that think ſo;</hi> but this is too fulſome, and therefore the wiſeſt of them will not own it, but doe it mincingly, becauſe they would avoid the dint of it; they ſtoope becauſe they have not power to make good the ground.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the covenant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and with us, is the ſame, we may ſee the text for it is plain, if we look <hi>Galat.</hi> 38. The ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture foreſeeing that God would juſtifie the Gentiles through Faith, preached the Goſpel unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaying, <hi>in thy ſeed,</hi> &amp;c. ſo it was Goſpel he preached to <hi>Abraham:</hi> therefore it is a Goſpel cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and not a carnall covenant; God did foreſee the frailty of poor ignorant men, that would call the goſpel a new covenant; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he having declared this to be goſpel, <hi>in thy ſeed ſhalt all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth be bleſſed,</hi> the ſame that is now with the goſpel: that covenant abides for ever; Thus the ſcripture foreſeeing of their folly hath made this plain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is the main ſcope of that in the 4 of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and in the beginning, he makes good this doctrine: the Apoſtle in the three former ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers he had inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>voured to prove juſtification by Faith; here he brings in the example of <hi>Abraham,</hi> he proves it to be in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111041:4"/>ſame manner as to <hi>Abraham;</hi> he is called the father of the faithfull not by naturall generation, for ſo he was not a father to the Gentiles, but by imitation, as is ſaid of the Jews, their father was an <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,</hi> and their mother was an <hi>Hittite:</hi> ſo all the faith full may be ſaid to be juſtified as he was, all the Saints of God may ſay ſo, it is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the 11, and 12, verſes he diſputes the reaſon why he did receive it; that he might be the father of all them that believe: the queſtion was when <hi>Abraham</hi> did receive it; it was before hee was circumciſed, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17. This was the reaſon he is called the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them that believe, though they were not circumciſed; and after he received circumciſion, the ſcope and aym of God was not to hinder any, but he that was circumciſed was ſaved by Faith, and he that was uncircumciſied ſhould be ſaved by Faith; all ſhould be ſaved one way; there is one way to all in Chriſt, if we atend the 22, 23, 24. <hi>verſes,</hi> we ſhall ſee there is no hole unſtopped; it was not imputed to him alone, but for us alſo, ſo that the ſcope of God is one to all that believe; for that it is imputed to us alſo, as to him, in the ſame way; ſo that what was to him, is to me; there is the ſame way of juſtification to all; that is clear here.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the ſumme of the Goſpel be contained in the Law and the Prophets then it is the ſame to us, as it is to them: but that it is ſo, the proof is <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22. <hi>Paul</hi> did preach what Moſes and the Prophets did ſay ſhould come, that <hi>Chriſt ſhould ſuffer and riſe from the dead,</hi> &amp;c. ſo as this was the ſumme of <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching, that they had ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If there be one Mediator, then there is one covenant; he in whom the covenant is made, and he by whom the covenant is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: but ſo it is, we have one Mediator alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. <hi>Is God the God of the Jews onely, is he not the God of the Gentiles:</hi> ſo as all is of God, ſo he will ſave the Jews by Faith, and the Gentiles alſo by Faith; ſo they are all ſaved by one and the ſame manner, and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. <hi>It is aſmal thing that thou ſhouldeſt be my ſervant to raiſe up the tribes of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and raiſe up the deſolatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Iſrael:</hi> I will alſo give thee a light for the Gentiles that thou mayeſt be my ſalvation to the end of the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that we ſee, it is through him it is perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that as it is the ſame God and Chriſt, ſo there is but one cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with them: And now</p>
            <p n="5">5. The covenant of <hi>Abraham</hi> dos contain the perfection of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and ſaving grace that belongs to the Saints of God, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.32. Chriſt diſputes about the Reſurrection of the dead, he ſaith, <hi>He is the God of</hi> Abraham, he is not the God of the dead but of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111041:5"/>he diſputes from the perfection of the covenant, it includes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the reſt. This may ſuffice to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w the <hi>covenant of grace</hi> is the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Difference is in the manner of the diſpenſation, therein it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in regard of the circumſtances of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In regard of the Ordinance, it is divers from Baptiſme: in that there was cutting away, here is waſhing away; that was to the male, this is to all; that was to be done on the eighth day, this may be on any day. But theſe things doe not make another Sacrament, though the manner be divers in adminiſtration of them; that look<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at Chriſt to come; that he ſhould be incarnate, was ſealed by that: but by baptiſme is ſealed that <hi>Chriſt is come, and hath ſuffered, and is raiſed and ſet at the right hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Hence the outward diſpenſation was in many types and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, Chriſt being to come, the ordinances went before in types; and in their ordinances they had many types: nay, the very nation and their land was typicall; the nation of the <hi>Jewes</hi> was a type of Gods elect; and Gods calling and chuſing them from among other nations, was a type of his calling and chuſing his elect from out of the men of the world, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6, 7. <hi>The Lord hath choſen you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loved you, &amp;c. And therefore be you ſeparate from all other nations, though they rebell, yet be you ſeparate from them.</hi> And they might not make any marriages with them that were of the Gentiles. <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall dwel alone in ordinances, priviledges, and ſeparation. <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> 10.11, 12. <hi>Give praiſes unto the God of your Fathers, and doe his will, and ſeparate your ſelves from the people of the land, and from the ſtrange wives: And the people anſwered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We will doe according to thy words.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 10.28. it was unlawfull for a Jew to keep company with a Gentile. And therefore God prepared <hi>Peter,</hi> by letting down aſheet, to goe to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> by which he made it clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, the difference was taken away. And not onely ſo, but the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was a type of the Kingdom of Heaven, becauſe God choſe that land for them, and gave it them, as their proper right, and therefore when they ſhall be called, they may fight for it again by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right; it differs not now, for they are a peculiar people, and a choyce people, and that is a choyce and peculiar Land, and ſeparate from all other. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. The Jewes call them <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncirumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and without the covenant,</hi> in an externall manner; but look wee at the ſubſtance of the covenant, and there is no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, the Jew i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaved by faith, and the Gentile through faith; ſo as the caſe is cleare, the covenant is the ſame. If any diſpute and ſay,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111041:5"/>that is nothing here; for all is from a covenant of grace, it was the ſame with <hi>Abraham</hi> when he lived.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether the ſeales of the covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> be of the like efficacy with ours in the times of the Goſpel? The anſwer is in three things:
<list>
                  <item>1. Their Sacraments and ours are not alike in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of efficacy, but ours exceed theirs in the efficacy of them, for ours ſeale 1. more clearly,</item>
                  <item>2. more largely,</item>
                  <item>3. more lively.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In the <hi>Clearneſſe,</hi> they ſhewed Chriſt to come in the fleſh; but ours manifeſt Chriſt is come, and is dead and is riſen, and aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſits in heaven, and will not leave till he have wrought it in us; ſo as it is more cleare to us then the law could ſet it forth, and therefore they were called <hi>ſhadowes:</hi> ſo it ſhewes there is a body, but when the body is come, the ſhadowes goe away. But in the Goſpel, Chriſt repreſents things more neere, and things that are more neere are more clearly ſeen. All the Sacraments in the law are ſaid to be dark, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>We have a more ſure word, to which you do well to attend unto, as to a light that ſhineth in a dark place, untill the Day-ſtarre ariſe, &amp;c.</hi> where the Law is compared to night, and the Goſpel to the Day-ſtar. Hence <hi>Numbers</hi> 24 17. <hi>I ſhall ſee him, but not now; I ſhall behold him, but not neere, &amp;c.</hi> The Law endured till <hi>John,</hi> but now the Star-light is gone. Hence our Saviour ſaith, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that is leaſt in the Kingdome of Heaven, is greater then he,</hi> that is, in the times of the Goſpel. So as by all this it is plain, the light is more cleare now then in the time of the Law. Hence all the types of the Law led people about. <hi>John</hi> 16.23, 24. <hi>I ſay unto you, whatſoever you ſhall ask in my Name, he will give it to you. Hitherto you have asked nothing in my Name, &amp;c.</hi> Hence Interpreters ſay, he alludes to the Law, that led men about, but not directly to Chriſt: but we are led directly to Chriſt; they led not to Chriſt nextly, but in types. Some think he meanes, they have asked no great ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ters: but the minde of God is, in that day, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, when I ſhall ſee you again after my death, you ſhall ask nothing but it ſhall be given you; that is, when he was dead and riſen again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they did queſtion it before, about ſeeing him again, but they ſhall never queſtion it more after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; for then they ſhall ſee it clearly, they ſhall look at Chriſt as come into the world, and dead, and riſen again; you have asked no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the name of a Saviour that hath ſatisfied. And ſome thinke, and I think they have the truth; but after they ſhall ask in the name of a Saviour that hath ſatisfied, and fitting at the right hand of God; hence they are called <hi>better promiſes, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.6. becauſe now it is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111041:6"/>not what ſhould be done, but now he hath performed it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is better in that regard. This is the ground of the Sacraments in the Goſpel, and ſo it is more clearly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ours in the time of the Goſpel, is of a larger meaſure, more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant then in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time they were: after the great work of our redemption was accompliſhed, then was the ſeaſon for the ful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of a larger meaſure of grace to be declared. By death Chriſt did conquer, by his reſurrection he did triumph, and by his aſcending he went into his own countrey, and then was a full time for the large communication of all grace to his Church: therefore it is ſaid, the Spirit was not given, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not yet glorified. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>When he aſcended upon high, &amp;c.</hi> Hence <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Law made nothing perfect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but when Chriſt came, he perfected all things, Heb.</hi> 11.40. The Saints under the Law had imitiation, but not perfection, they heard of <hi>Chriſt to come,</hi> but if hee had not come, they had not been perfect; but we are in the time of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now in the time of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are now more lively and more vigorous then they were then, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13. <hi>In that he ſaith a New Teſtament, hee hath abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated the Old, &amp;c</hi> The Old is decayed, but now it is New and freſh. Hence we ſee the meaſure of it, <hi>I will put my law in your heart, and all ſhall know me.</hi> We need not ſay, <hi>know me,</hi> for all ſhall know me, they ſhall all know the things of God and grace. Thus ours exceed theirs in the time of the Law in the degrees of efficacy.</p>
            <p>The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> propoſition wherein the pinch lieth, the Sacraments in the old Teſtament, and ours agree, they have the like ſpirituall efficacy in the kind, though in the degree ours exceed theirs: The ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this will ſcatter the cavils of Papiſts and Anabaptiſts. What is meant by ſpirituall kind? two things: Firſt, the things of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant that were to be ſealed. Secondly, the manner of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance. 1. Chriſt, intereſt in him, and participation of the fruit and benefit of his merits and obedience: by conſequence all outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits are conſequences of the covenant of grace, life and peace. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac.</hi> 2.5. <hi>My covenant was with him of life and peace, &amp;c.</hi> The covenant of Grace being conveyed unto them; Chriſt is now the Prince of peace, the pith of all the covenant of grace: the ſame I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the poſſeſſion of Chriſt is the ſtabliſhment of the heart in it, there lies the power of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The manner of it, as theirs did in the old, ſo ours in the new, it lies in three things.
<list>
                  <item>1. It ſignifies God and grace:</item>
                  <item>2. it conveyes:</item>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:111041:6"/>
                  <item>And 3. it exhibits grace; the ſame ſpirituall efficacy in thoſe in the law and of ours, and of the like vertue. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 12 <hi>And the Father of Circumciſion, not unto them onely that were of the Circumciſion, &amp;c.</hi> it was the ſeale of the covenant of Faith, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits the meaning there in the law, and ſo theirs and ours are alike inſignifying, ſealing, &amp; exhibiting to the party an intereſt in Chriſt; as in the Law, ſo in the Goſpel. Here they are alike: in degree they differ, but for the kinde they are the ſame. This I proved to you, I will cleare it by reaſon.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>I would not have you ignorant, that all our fathers were under the Cloud, and all paſſed through the Sea, &amp;c.</hi> I wil ſhew you the ſcope of the Apoſtle; His aim is to pull a way the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall confidence which they placed in their priviledges, which they thought would preſerve them from plagues: They could ſay, we have Baptiſme and the Supper of the Lord, we eate the fleſh of Chriſt, and drink his blood, and are advanced, ſo that we ſhall be preſerved from ſuch plagues. No (ſaith the Apoſtle) theſe will not doe it; for I can ſhew you a people had theſe as well as you, which were overthrowne and deſtroyed in the wilderneſſe; they were as eminent as you, and yet they were deſtroyed, they had the Cloud and the Sea, as well as you have Baptiſme; and they had Manna, and the water out of the Rock, as well as you have bread and wine in the Supper of the Lord; yet their priviledges would not preſerve them; no more will yours preſerve you. This is the meaning of God in the words; ſo as it is a folly for us to think, if we ſin as they did, that we ſhould not be plagued as they were. They that are truly ſaid to be truly baptized in the right uſe of their Sacraments, their Sacraments are the like with ours: but ſo they are ſaid to be by the Spirit of God: <hi>Thry were baptized,</hi> are the words of the Text, and therefore if we ſhould deny it, we deny the words of the Spirit of God, which is blaſphemy to doe. The reaſon lies in the phraſe: not becauſe the ſignes are the ſame, though the ſame thing be ſignified: inſtead of Baptiſme is the Cloud and Sea; the red Sea held forth the like good to them, as ours to us, the force is the ſame; there is the like vertue in the one, as in the other: They are the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and drank the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as we do: The Manna, and the Water out of the Rock, was the ſame with our Supper of the Lord; for the good of the Suuper is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he is there, and our ſpirits feaſt; <hi>His fleſh is meat indeed, and his blood is drink indeed;</hi> the whole does ſignifie and exhibit CHRIST it is like ours, the elements are not the ſame, but there is the ſame ſpirituall food, and they ſeale up the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111041:7"/>ſame <hi>Chriſt</hi> to them as to us, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is preſented as ſpirituall refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them and us. It is a dream of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> they were not the ſame with ours; for though theirs were extraordinary: yet that hinders not the Argument; we look at it as a Sacrament, not at the extraordinarineſſe of it.</p>
            <p>The third Argument: That ſenſe that overthrowes the ſenſe of the Apoſtle, that is to be rejected: But to ſay that Iſrael did not enjoy the ſame priviledges in the kind of them, is to make the ſenſe of the Apoſtle void, and therefore it is to be rejected: The Jewes provoking God, ſhall be puniſhed, ſo ſhall you. It had been eaſie to have anſwered, they are not of that excellency that ours be; and therefore though theirs could not preſerve them, ours may. But now if yee attend the mind of God, it is cleare, theirs are the ſame with outs in the kinde of them. And this is the firſt thing that may prevent all cavils.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is from that, <hi>Rom</hi> 4 11. <hi>Abraham received the ſigne of Circumciſion, as the ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of faith, &amp;c.</hi> that is, the righteouſneſſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> received by faith, ſealed by circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that was the ſeale of the righteouſneſle of faith by Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo as they have ſpirituall efficacy with baptiſme, they have the utmoſt power a Sacrament hath, to ſignifie, ſeale, and exhibite the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good of the covenant of Grace: it is a ſeale God appointed and it doth exhibit. When a man hath ſet to his Seale, he ſtands ingaged this promiſe he doe accompliſh. Every promiſe a man makes, if he perform it not, it is becauſe he is feeble and cannot, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is unfaithfull and will not, but theſe cannot befall God: ſo there is exhibition where there is ſealing, if it be appointed for the ſame; and baptiſme can doe no more but ſignifie, ſeale, and exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit: ſo is circumciſion a covenant of Faith, ſo there is no gainſaying, but the Argument is plain in the Text. I will make ſome collections.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence it is plain, that <hi>Abraham</hi> had, was the covenant of the Goſpel and Grace: It is proved thus, That which was the Covenant of the righteouſneſſs of faith, is the covenant of the Goſpel; that this is ſo, we may ſee it by the Apoſtle, <hi>If it be of workes, it is not of faith; if it be of faith, it is not of workes,</hi> Rom. 3, But <hi>Abrahams</hi> covenant is a covenant of the righteouſneſſe of faith: That which circumciſion ſealed, was a covenant to <hi>Abraham;</hi> to ſay it was a carnall covenant, is groſſe; and to ſay it was not a covenant of Faith, is to deny the text, and dig it up by the roots. So we ſee that it was a covenant of grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sacraments in the old Teſtament require and preſume, and preſuppoſe in the right uſe of them, <hi>Faith in the receiver,</hi> as being the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111041:7"/>righteouſneſſe of God, I know not how any can deny it, it is ſo clear theirs did require faith as well as ours doe. The efficacie of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment rightly uſed, is to ſeale up our ſalvation; but abuſed, it ſealts up our condemnation. The right uſe of it is to eſtabliſh our hearts, but the abuſe of it doth haſten our condemnation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some perſons my rightly uſe a Sacrament with allowance from God, and may receive the good thereof, that have not the exerciſe of reaſon, as <hi>Infants,</hi> as we may ſee in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time: And this will give an anſwer to all them that ſhall ſay, How can infants get good by Baptiſme, when they have not the uſe of reaſon? <hi>Abrahams</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren had the good of the Sacrament ſealed up unto them, and yet they had not the uſe of reaſon; yet they had a right unto it by allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from God.</p>
            <p n="4">4 According to a right rule from God, and right Reaſon, perſons may have faith in the courſe of charity, that have not the uſe of reaſon: they in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time had grace, and that was the grace of Faith; if it ſeale up, ſome may have it; but that ſome children are thus fitted, and faith is ſealed unto them in circumciſion, if any will deny it, they muſt deny the Text, and that is impudency it ſelfe. If ſo, why not in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme as well as Circumciſion; for Circumciſion muſt have faith, ſo muſt they in Baptiſme?</p>
            <p n="5">5 There is more required of ſome perſons then there is of other in receving of the ſame ſacrament in the alowance of God, &amp; according to right Reaſon; there is more required of men, then there is of children: Take a man that is to joyn in the covenant of the people, he is bound to ſtoop to the Ordinance, <hi>Eſay</hi> 56.67. The ſtrangers that were to joyne, they muſt keep the Sabbath, and embrace the Covenant, &amp;c. This is to make a proſelyte, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.15. they are made of the ſame profeſſion. Men of yeares muſt approve of the things of God, and walk accordingly; all this is required of men of yeares, and then to offer themſelves to the ordinances, for they did never force them: but in children this is not required, if the Father had embraced the Faith. So as you may ſee theſe things are plain, wkich if they be obſerved, it will make you caſt away Anabaptiſme.</p>
            <p>The third Scripture is in <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.11, 12. if the effects of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the old Teſtament and the new, be the ſame, then they are the ſame: the effect done by the thing, ſhewes the thing: if the things wrought be the ſame, then it is alike; but the things done are the ſame. The Apoſtle in the Text ſhewes it is the ſame in Circumciſion, as in Baptiſme, both ſeale up the death of Chriſt; there was decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111041:8"/>both were for the maſtering, or leſſening and decaying of ſin, ſo doth circumciſion by cutting off the fore-skin in the ſame operation.</p>
            <p>Now there are two objections to be anſwered from ſeverall Texts, it appeares they are the ſame with ours. The firſt is that in 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, nor uncircumciſion, but the keeping of the command of God.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaking to perſons to keep in the ſame Calling God had called them, he ſaith, <hi>Circumciſion is nothing, &amp;c.</hi> The next is <hi>Galat,</hi> 6.13. they make nothing of it. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.6. <hi>For in Chriſt Circumciſion nor uncircumciſion availeth any thing, but faith that worketh by love:</hi> that is, ſay they, it is weake, and can doe nothing, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit them nothing if they be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed;</hi> and the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>Beware of Circumciſion,</hi> by way of Irony, ſo as he accounts it as nothing. All theſe places are of the ſame nature, and may receive the ſame anſwer to them all. God lookes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all theſe Sacraments to be attended according to a double time and conſideration. Firſt, in the firſt inſtitution they had an eye to, and did ſeale up Chriſt to come in the fleſh, when they were firſt ordained by God, 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. God lookes at them as having attained their end and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, which was Chriſt to come: therefore when he was come, they had an end. Therefore now they were of no uſe, being out of date; and now they could not be uſed without ſinne: he appoints now therefore to abrogate them, they were to ceaſe becauſe Chriſt was come: though they were alike at the firſt, now they were out of date, now they were not to be uſed. To this purpoſe are all theſe places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor</hi> 7.19. <hi>If thou be called being uncircumciſed, be not circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:</hi> if you were circumciſed when it was in date, then ſeek not to be uncircumciſed: if you be uncircumciſed, be not circumciſed now it is out of date. It cannot be taken the Apoſtle for bad circumciſion when it was in date; for then he had ſpoken againſt the command of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. He commanded them to be circumciſed. So <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15. <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus neither circumciſion, &amp;c. availeth any thing, but a new creature.</hi> For though they were given to the Jewes, yet now they were gone out of the world, and ſo now they availed not. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, to ſet them up now, was to ſet up that which God had deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So that now nothing availed, but faith and a new creature. And <hi>Gal,</hi> 5.4. <hi>He is fallen from Grace;</hi> but now he doth not attend the firſt inſtitution, if he doe, hee nullifies the nature of Chriſt, becauſe when Chriſt is come, it is to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh. This is a heynous thing, Chriſt ſhall doe him no good, Chriſt will not ſave
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111041:8"/>him. In the laſt place, he ſpeakes this to falſe Apoſtles, that would have men partly ſaved by Chriſt, and partly by workes; and ſo they nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Chriſt, and the work of grace: for he muſt have all or none, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not joyne works and grace together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection</hi> 2. From the witneſſe of the word, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Which were but a ſhadow of things to come, but the body is Chriſt.</hi> And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.18 they are ſaid to be weak. And <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10, 13. called <hi>a carnall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> And if it be ſo, then they are not alike with ours in the new Teſtament, they are of another nature, the ſpirituall work of the ſoule. For anſwer, the Sacraments are apprehended in a double ſenſe, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, or as ſeparate from the thing ſignified; but the Apoſtle lookes at them as carnall now, as <hi>Heb</hi> 7.18, 19. he ſaith, <hi>The Law was weake, and made nothing perfect but the bringing in of a better hope, &amp;c.</hi> that is, Chriſt he accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſheth all, and brings in a better hope of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſinnes. So 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21, 22. it is not the water, but the thing ſignified by the water. So the ſigne is weak, but the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied is ſtrong. So the caſe is cleare.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Concluſion.</hi> The ſpirituall efficacy of the Sacraments in the old and new Teſtament, proceed not from themſelves immediatly uſed in the working of any good, but as they are uſed by the holy Ghoſt. The conſideration whereof will help in the main point, to ſhew the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the working of the Sacrament, for it is a great ſecret, and the want of the knowledge hereof, is the cauſe perſons get ſo little good by the Sacrament. This propoſition hath two parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſpirituall influence the Sacraments put forth, is not from themſelves immediatly, but as they are uſed by the Spirit. For the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding of this firſt part, conſider it in ſome things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Sacrament is not a principall, but an inſtrumental cauſe in any ſpirituall work: they doe not ſet themſelves a work, but they worke under the principall agent; as a toole in the hand of a man, ſo in the work of the Sacrament, it is by the mediation of the Spirit, and the meanes of faith, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.16. <hi>Hee that beleeves and is baptized, &amp;c. But he that believeth not, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26. <hi>That he might ſanctifie it and cleanſe it by water through the word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sacraments as inſtruments, put forth a ſpirituall efficacie, when they are lawfully uſed according to God: but not when they are abuſed in an unlawfull manner, and unworthily received; then they doe not put forth any ſpirituall efficacie. Thus the Supper of the Lord puts forth ſpirituall efficacie when it is ordered in a lawfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Is is not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111041:9"/>And the <hi>Cup of bleſſing</hi> is the ſame, and yet <hi>be that receives is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, eates and drinkes his own damnation,</hi> and makes himſelfe guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt, becauſe he abuſes the ſeale. He that abuſes the Kings ſeale is puniſhed, and therefore much more theſe. The Goſpel is the power of God to ſalvation, but it muſt bee mixed with faith, and then it is the ſavour of life unto life, but without it, is the ſavour of death unto death. And ſo is the Sacrament; therfore when a thing is lawfully done, it is no ſinne, but if it be abuſed, then it is ſinfull: therefore that the Sacrament is abuſed, it is from ſinne; but the ſpirituall work of a Sacrament helps forward to ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ſpirituall efficacy a Sacrament puts forth, is not as a Phyſicall inſtrument, but as a Morall. I put it in theſe termes, that I might cleare it up in their termes which they uſe which darken the truth. Now ſee the explication, Inſtruments are of a double nature, ſome have quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties inherent, that is, ſticking in them by nature; as ſome phyſicall hearbs are of a purging nature, others comfortable, they have it in their nature put into them ſo to work, and it abides in them, but other are made ſerviceable by Art, they are made ſharp or ſweet: Or in tooles, ſome are made ſharp, fit for uſe, as a bone wil not cut our bread, but we muſt have ſomething made ſharp: ſo things are made phyſicall either by Nature or by Art. The Papiſts call it Phyſicall in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: they ſay the Sacraments work naturally, if taken, they have a quality to convey grace: the Sacrament taken, they ſay, will worke of it ſelfe; but it is a groſſe conceit to ſatisfie a carnall heart: then a drunken wretch muſt have grace, if he can but have the uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Thus the Papiſts derogate from Chriſt, by making a quality to be inherent in the Sacraments, to convey grace into any man that receives them.</p>
            <p>The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> diſtinction is, they are morally good, as ſome inſtruments that have no power of themſelves, but as they are ſtated by way of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, as he that uſes them doth appoint them: As a piece of wax is appointed to ſeale up a bargain, the Wax conveys nothing, it is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be a witneſſe to ſet forth the truth as the party is ingaged accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to agreement: as <hi>Elijahs</hi> Cloke divided the waters, it was not in the Cloke, but it was a ſigne to intimate that God would be with him. So the Braſen Serpent was appointed of God for the people that were ſtung, by looking on it they ſhould be healed: there was no ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in the braſſe to heale them: for afterwards in <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ekiahs</hi> dayes, he called it <hi>Nehuſhtan,</hi> a piece of braſſe: But by Gods inſtitution, God uſed it as a meanes to work by, but the vertue was in himſelfe; there
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111041:9"/>was no inherent vertue in the braſſe, but God appointed it for this end as a morall inſtrument.</p>
            <p n="4">4 When the Sacraments are thus taken for ſuch an end, and to ſuch a work, there is a divine vertue goes along with them for that end, the ſame power that did appoint them, will goe along with them, and will work in them for that end. There be three things in the inſtitution of them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 God appointing them out according to his will, in wiſdome and power, the bread ſignifying the body of Chriſt as meat; the water ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the blood of Chriſt waſhing a way the guilt and filth of our ſins, the wiſdome and good pleaſure of God going along with them for that end.</item>
               <item>2 They are ſeales of Gods ingagement to man, that is ſignified by theſe his Faithfulneſſe and Truth alwayes goe with it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. It is called, <hi>The Seale of the Righteouſneſſe of Faith:</hi> So as it is as ſure as that.</item>
               <item>3 There is the accompliſhment and performance thereof; here ſhall we find the good Spirit of God going along with this ordinance to ſee it done, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3 11. <hi>He ſhall baptize you with the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29. <hi>That is Circumciſion that is of the heart, &amp;c.</hi> So as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is ſtated for that uſe, it hath alway this, the good Spirit of God going along with it, &amp; carrying it to the underſtanding, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies all ſpirituall good to the underſtanding to a man <hi>that worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it:</hi> it carries it <hi>ſacramentally:</hi> So as it is plain, no man can inſtitute a Sacrament to have the good of it as the Seale; the Spirit of God muſt make good Gods engagement, ſo as <hi>the heart</hi> cannot get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the goodneſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3 The Sacrament exhibits grace, ſo the Spirit of God go along with it, and ſee it accompliſhed; thus theirs is the ſame with ours, for theirs and ours comunicate the vertue of it by the Spirit of God: And hence it followes, that it is of force as under the motion of that bleſſed <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſo that there is no more of the Bread, nor of the Wine that have this fruit, but ſo much as is uſed to this end. And as the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> was not of that uſe to heale, but at that time the Lord had ſet it apart for that uſe, and therefore afterwards it was called <hi>Nehuſhtan.</hi> Hence followes a threefold collection.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Hence this will bee a meanes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe and help you to ſee how the <hi>Spirit</hi> can work in Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>The main worker is the <hi>Spirit,</hi> all is poſſible to him, he can ſecretly doe it to a childe: he is not confin'd to our work, he can overſhadow
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111041:10"/>the heart of a Child as he did the Virgin.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In the manner of the working, in which we may ſee foure thing, for our help.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The Sacrament of Baptiſme is a ſeale of our firſt entrance; and the Supper is our nouriſhing in the family of Chriſt: And this being the ſcope of Baptiſme ſealing our firſt work into Chriſt, that whereby we are implanted into Chriſt; in which work we are meetly paſſive: but when wee are ſetled on Chriſt, the truth is this, wee have a gracious principle put into us, and ſo we work by our ſelves, and by the help of the Spirit: but at the firſt the Spirit makes us willing that we may will it. This is the confeſſion of all our orthodox Divines.</item>
               <item>2 In this firſt grace wherein we are paſſive, God works in us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, all the workes we are paſſive in.</item>
               <item>3 Hence we may ſee the Spirit may as well ſeale within us without us as well as work within us without us, without any oppoſition, there is the ſame reaſon for the one as the other; I know nothing to oppoſe, but if he doe the one; he may doe the other.</item>
               <item>4 Hence we may ſee, if this be true, that he can ſeale within us, without us, it may be conceived, that though there be no ſaving qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity comes from the Sacrament, the Spirit may worke in himſelfe, and from himſelfe, without the work of the child. This makes it eaſie to a mans apprehenſion: it is indeed ſecret firſt in God, in baptiſme this is wrought, and the Spirit can ſeale as well as work it in the ſoul.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The third Poſition: There is no quality in the Sacrament as a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but meetly an inſtrument, a miniſteriall worke; but the Spirit can work it with eaſe: that way he did work in the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the very ſame he worketh now.</p>
            <p>Now to the third Head, where the main ſtreſſe lies, and that is in the perſons that are capable of the covenant of Grace, and that we heard was no weakneſſe of faith, nor want of yeares; Who be they then that be capable ſubjects? For the opening the point,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 We will explicate the point.</item>
               <item>2 We will anſwer the objections of the adverſaries, thoſe that would deſtroy the comforts of the faithfull.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 Who be the ſubjects capable for this Covenant, and we will ſpeak of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In generall: 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, in particular. And this generall ſhall bee as a Torch ſet on the top of a paire of ſtaires, that gives light almoſt to all the roomes in the houſe for paſſage.</p>
            <p>The firſt concluſion is, That the Seales do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not give the firſt grace;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111041:10"/>but doe preſuppoſe that ſuch as doe receive them, are within the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace; which covenant hath ever in the old, and now in like manner in the new, ſealed up the covenant to them that are partakers of it: in which we muſt conſider three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The ſeales of the covenant doe not give the firſt grace: I will not look at grace as it is in God, but as it is communicated unto us; it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes a former favour that they bring in them, and being in the covenant, they receive God by it. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. <hi>I looked upon thee, and thy time was the time of love, and I ſpred my skirt over thee, and made a covenant with thee, and thou becameſt mine.</hi> Firſt, it was a time of love, and then he takes them into covenant. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.4.5. <hi>Remember me with the favour of thy people, &amp;c.</hi> And if the Sacrament give the firſt grace, then it ſhould be given to all people, the Church could hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der none, becauſe then they ſhould hinder their comming to God, and the Apoſtle affirmes the contrary by ſaying, (1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5: 12, 13.) <hi>What have I to doe to judge them that are without, &amp;c.</hi> The preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel muſt be to <hi>every creature,</hi> becauſe that is a meanes to bring men to Chriſt; but the Seals are to be given to them that are within. When any of the Heathen came to joyn with the Jewes, it was lawfull for them to become Proſelytes, they were to turn Jewes, that was, to profeſſe the ſame faith with the Jewes: And when they were joyned, then it was lawfull to circumciſe them, but elſe it was not lawfull. Firſt, they muſt have a being in the Covenant, and then they might have the ſeales.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Propoſition is, the Seale preſuppoſes all thoſe to be in the covenant of grace, that have the Seals: for the Seals doe not make the Covenant, but eſtabliſh the Covenant; it is onely given to them that be in the Covenant: there is no ſeal put to a blank; ſo a ſeale here is taken for granted they are in the covenant. Hence bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>In whom you were circumciſed, &amp;c.</hi> Hence we are ſaid <hi>to put on Chriſt, Galat.</hi> 3.27. ſo as all our inciſion and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſealed up by baptiſme, and it ſtabliſheth the heart. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. <hi>If thou believe with all thy heart thou mayeſt, &amp;c.</hi> It is not therefore a carnall covenant, it ſuppoſes how after ward they ought to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>It is the ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of Faith,</hi> ſo as by faith they receive it.</p>
            <p>They take it for granted. <hi>Abraham</hi> had faith, how could it be ſealed up! and therefore, I wonder, at the ſpeech of the Authour of a booke come lately to my hand: It is in the fifth page. I doe not finde the word <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that he did believe in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, or that it was required
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111041:11"/>he ſhould ſo doe, when the words are ſo plain, Rom. 4.11. <hi>By the word which he had, being uncircumciſed;</hi> every part of the ſentence ſhews it forth, <hi>that faith, that did make</hi> Abraham <hi>a father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and a patterne,</hi> did look to Chriſt as the Object of it; and it looks mainly there: but <hi>Abraham</hi> was a pattern, and therefore we look at Chriſt, <hi>as the bleſſed ſeed:</hi> that faith which he had, being uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by which he was a father to them that were uncircumciſed, that faith is ſuppoſed to be the faith of the ſeed; I know not how any body is able to avoid it, Philip. 3.9. <hi>That I might be found in him, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my own righteouſnes, &amp;c.</hi> that faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> did look at the bleſſed ſeed. That man ſpeaks doubtfully, which makes me feare he would have ſaid it was a carnall Covenant, but that he durſt not, ſeeing what was comming down the Hill upon him, which he was not able to avoid: but the caſe is cleare, that which is preſuppoſed to be in <hi>Abraham,</hi> before he was circumciſed, is preſuppoſed to be in all that are allowed to receive as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, he being a pattern: if circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion did preſuppoſe faith in <hi>Abraham,</hi> it doth ſo to all that are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: the reaſon is, if the ſame covenant and the ſame ſeal was to the reſt, as was to <hi>Abraham;</hi> the ſame is required that was in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the ſame thing ſeal up one and the ſame, it never differed, the ſame ſeale, it did ſeale to all alike; ſo as the ſecond part is plain in the text, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17, 10, 11.12. <hi>This ſhall bee a token of my Covenant, &amp;c.</hi> there was not one covenant for him, and another for them, but all is one and the ſame. Here it is objected, it was a ſeale to <hi>Abraham,</hi> hee had ſaith, but how was it to his family? <hi>Anſwer</hi> is, The ſcope of God in the place, is to diſcover a ſtanding rule, how ſacraments were to be, not how they were to be to unworthy perſons, but how they were to be to perſons that receive them aright, look at Gods appointing of them, in regard of the nature of the ſeals, they doe ſeal up the ſame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace to all that receive them: if ſome pretend they had grace, and yet they crept in, and had no grace, inwardly they deprived themſelves of the benefit of the Ordinance, yet in the nature of it, it aymes at this; but if the receiver hinder and ſtop the benefit, it is his fault, the ſacrament is the ſame: for Children wee muſt look at them, as God allows us, and then they were within the covenant, for none could ſay the contrary, if there be any inconveniency againſt Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in this, I ſay, if they had it according to their own deſire, to men of years, I will ſay, as much for children, as they for them; it is a ſeal of remiſſion of ſins; ſuppoſe hypocrites offer themſelves to it, as <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Magus</hi> did, how did it ſeale up him, when he was ſtill in <hi>the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111041:11"/>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le of bitterneſſe;</hi> ſo as there is the ſame inconveniency in men, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing faith; if we ſay therefore, baptiſme is not a ſeal of our inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it is blaſphemy; if we look at baptiſm as from God, it intends it the unworthines of it doth hinder, but God intends it. As the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, it is the favour of life unto life, if it be worthily received, but if it be abuſed, then it is the ſavour of death unto death: If men creep into the Church, that are unworthy, and hinder the benefit, yet it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not the ſeal. As the Charter of a City is, all that ſerve out their years, and ſue out their libertie, ſhall be made free: a man comes out of his time, and gets out this freedome; if after, the Maſter come in, and ſhew how he dealt baſely with him in his ſervice, and he forfeit all his freedome; will you ſay, ſuch a Cities Charter is broken? No, but his bare carriage was the cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo the ordinance of God is the ſame, and is not to be blamed, although the receiver be unworthy. So in the Supper of the Lord, <hi>He that receives it unworthily eates and drinks his own damnation, and is guilty of the body and blood of the Lord,</hi> and it is ſealed up to him, and yet the fault is not in the Seale.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concluſion, is this, being in the covenant of grace, is to be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to rationall charity, and accordingly it is to be diſcerned and determined, according to the rule of rationall charity; and this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty God hath deligated to the Church: for the diſpenſation of it, God gave it to the father of the family in the wilderneſſe; in the time of the New Teſtament it is given to the Miniſters: the ſeale is outward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is impoſſible for man to ſearch into the heart, and to diſcover it really: it is the Prerogative of God to ſearch the heart, Jer. 17.10. <hi>The heart is deceitfull above meaſure, who can know it? I the Lord ſearch the heart. &amp;c.</hi> God knows the heart, many a man judges highly of the things that are naught. God hath commended theſe to his Church, and it is impoſſible to ſearch the heart, to finde out a cloſe hypocrite: God allows his Church to go to rationall charity, to the rule of reaſon and love: by the bounds of love inlightned by the rule of reaſon and Religion, and according to the rule, the Church may judge men; thus <hi>John</hi> took a taſte of the men that came to him in <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> by confeſſing their ſins; thus we muſt proceed according to the bounds of love, enlightned by Religion and rationall charity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This judgement according to the rules of rationall charity, is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to miſtakes. <hi>Paul</hi> was long with <hi>Demas,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> was miſtaken by <hi>Symon Magus,</hi> and it is ſaid, they went out from us, <hi>becauſe they were not of us, for if they had been of us, &amp;c. a man may deceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111041:12"/>Galas.</hi> 6.3. If a man think he is ſomewhat, &amp;c. yet the Church is bound to go according to Religion: we muſt judge, and may p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tice without ſin when we are miſtaken, becauſe it is our ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; if ſubtiltie of heart go beyond us, it is not the Churches fault, God doth require it; if he deceive himſelf and me, in the judgement of charity and verity, charity may be out-bid, therefore covenant grace is one thing, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace is another; according to the eye of man, and the Church, ſuch a man is fit: Now federall grace is ſuch as all falſe hypocrites have, federall grace they have enough to ſhew, and may receive the ſeals; Now it is poſſible hypocrites may be in the Church, that the Church are not able to condemn; nay ſuppoſe there were a thouſand Churches in <hi>England,</hi> and they receive the beſt according to the rules of charity, in reaſon there may be many hypocrites come into the Church, for it is as a draw net, it hath bad as well as good, and it is a barn fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore that hath c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>affe, as well as Wheat, if all were admitted, there are millions of perſons, wee cannot ſay this man is one ſealed for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and here is one ſealed for perdition; no man can ſay this child or this man ſhall be damned: I cannot ſay, this or that man is a reprobate, if all the Churches on earth were together; there are many that ſhall be damned, yet I cannot ſay this man or that ſhall be damned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Concluſion, this judgement of charity muſt proceed on divers grounds, according to the divers conditions of the men we have to deale withall of neceſſity; for inſtance, in the Old Law, no heathen might be made partaker of the priviledges, <hi>Eſay</hi> 56.4. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord to the Eunuches that keep my Sabbaoth, and take hold of my Covenant, &amp;c.</hi> before wee receive him, wee muſt heare him expreſſe himſelfe, as they did not receive him, nor would not untill he expreſt himſelf; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2 12. <hi>They muſt renounce their Idolatry, and imbrace the Law:</hi> the childe of this man is made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the ſeal. I muſt judge him in covenant, how ſhall I have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable charity, here is no profeſſion? there are divers wayes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; ſo that we muſt proceed upon ſeverall grounds: Hence you may obſerve, men of years muſt be received by profeſſion, and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and practice; and therefore they muſt be divers from Children: how muſt it be done on Children? thus, in reference to the covenant of their fathers, from the reference the Childe hath to the covenant of the father, it is made partaker of the covenant with the father, and by the father God hath promiſed, that ſhould be a means, not that the father conveyes grace to the childe (that is a dream) but he uſes the father as a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111041:12"/>means, and he will communicate himſelf to the childe, as he ſees fit: here is my ground, thou art a means to do good to the childe; hence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain obſerve, that if according to the judgement of reaſonable charity they did judge in <hi>Abrahams</hi> dayes, upon the ſelf-ſame ground men may and ought to judge children to have right to the covenant; if they might, we may; our grounds are the ſame, the covenant and ſeal are the ſame, then and now: this for the generall.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Now to the ſpeciall, the ſubjects capable, and they are men of years, and children: Firſt, What makes men of years capable: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, What does make Children capable of this ſeal of inciſſion; that is my main ſcope. The Lord Chriſt hath different ſeals, he looks to the entertainment of his ſervants, he ſuites his own end, and then he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for them, that is, <hi>the ſupper of the Lord:</hi> Baptiſme is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into his family, there is much more to be looked at, to make a perſon capable of the ſupper of the Lord; a man muſt be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelf, he muſt not onely have grace, but growth of grace: he muſt have ſo much perfection in grace, as to ſearch his own heart, and he muſt be able to <hi>diſcern the Lords body,</hi> or elſe, <hi>he is guilty of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of Chriſt:</hi> ſo as there is more required in this, for there muſt be a growth: But Baptiſme is our entrance, and the loweſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of grace will ſerve here in the judgement of charity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I will ſhew how it muſt be diſpenſed to men of years; what muſt be in them to make them capable, and I ſhall be ſhort here; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the difficulty lies not here. What makes them capable, and how it is to be diſcerned, we muſt conſider it in three things, according to the word I ſpeak of, men of years; becauſe if any black-Mores, or of other nations ſhould come and offer themſelves, they muſt be thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thoſe are worthy, that be ſenſible of then ſin and miſery that attend upon them, and be willing and ready to bewaile their ſin, and muſt be freely willing to know them, and know the manner of the committing of them, and confeſſe them after that manner, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent hearer, that is judiciouſly charitable, may think they have true repentance, that he may have good hope his heart is in ſuch a frame of ſorrow, as all may paſſe ſentence upon reaſonable charity; and then we may practice according to a rule, and not be miſſed; thus did <hi>John, Matth.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Thoſe that came to him were baptized of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, confeſſing their ſins:</hi> and in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, <hi>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, what they ſhould doe; bring forth fruits worthy, &amp;c.</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, you have profeſſed repentance, let your practices ſhew it, your actions
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111041:13"/>muſt cary weight for weight, your converſation ſhould hold correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with your profeſſion; you make a profeſſion here, make it reall by your converſation, let it be as you profeſſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>They were pricked in their hearts, &amp;c.</hi> ſo let your carriage be, that we may have hope you are the ſame within, that you profeſſe outwardly.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They muſt not onely be ſenſible of their ſin, but they muſt be ſenſible of their inſufficiency to help themſelves, and be willing to yeeld to Chriſt to help them, <hi>Luke</hi> 30.9, 10. where the ſtory of <hi>Johns</hi> preaching is recorded; wherein the ſpirit of God ſhews his great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to uſe ſeverall expreſſions from that in <hi>Matthew,</hi> that we may read all the Evangeliſts, that we may be acquainted with them, there <hi>he calls them a generation of Vipers, and forewarns them of wrath to come,</hi> when this word came, <hi>then they began to be troubled,</hi> and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing driven to a ſtand, ſee how they ſpeak, <hi>the people they come and ask what ſhall we doe? and the ſouldiers they ask, what ſhall wee doe?</hi> as if they ſhould ſay; we ſee our ſins, and here is guilt; we are willing to heat what we ſhall doe? they did not know how to deliver themſelves: and ſo <hi>Peter</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>Repent and be baptized, for the remiſſion of your ſins;</hi> that is, ſee your need of a Saviour, and look to him for help through baptiſme; that is, your inciſion into Chriſt, and having par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the obedience of Chriſt, baptiſm ſeals up this in men of years: why ſhould we come to Chriſt elſe? both theſe laſt are required, when Chriſt gave a commiſſion to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Go teach all nations, &amp;c.</hi> teach, is make them Diſciples or Proſelytes, and then Baptiſe them: the Apoſtles were ſent among the heathen, and they were men of years, make them Diſciples for me, and then baptize them, this was their commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is Gods method, to look at people as they are in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Church, it is a Church ordinance, that is the reaſon now in theſe dayes, that none but Officers of the Church can diſpence them, the ſeale makes good the communion: Hence in the Old Teſtament it was to the Jews, to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed; if the Gentile be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of it, they muſt firſt be made Proſelites: ſo it was to the Jews onely, and thoſe that joyned with the Jews; the frame of the ſcriptures Iye that way: <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was the proper name of a Jew, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion</hi> was the proper name of a Gentile, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.30. <hi>One God juſtifies Jew and Gentile;</hi> that which is ſaid of circumciſion may be ſaid of the other ordinances, they are to them that are in a Church eſtate; Hence it is obſerved, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.43.44. <hi>No ſtranger may eat thereof, but thoſe born in the houſe, and bought with money</hi> might
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111041:13"/>when they were circumciſed, ſo as it is in a Church way, as we ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate more afterward. If a man come out of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> if he were fit to receive the ſeales, wee cannot conſtrain him to receiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, the Church hath no power to conſtrain him to be baptized: But if he will ſubmit to the covenant of the Church, then the Church hath power; but if he refuſe to receive the Sacrament, we have no power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain him. Now the evidence and equity of the reaſon is plain: If a Church have no power but in a Church-way, then a perſon hath no rule to challenge it but in a Church-way: If he ſay, I will not be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, but will deprive himſelfe, we have nopower to impoſe it upon him; but if he ſubmit, we may, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.29, 30. The Publicans were baptized, but the Scribes and Phariſees would not, and he did not force them, nor he could not force them: but make Diſciples, and then baptize them, bring them into the covenant and then baptize them. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. <hi>They were joyned to the Church, and then they continued with the Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> You ſee what God calls for of men of yeares: It is a word of advice to thoſe that be now men of yeares; Underſtand what you ſhould doe that you may have the benefit of the Ordinances according to Gods appointment; doe not ſatisfie your ſelves in the judgement of the world, but ſearch your hearts, if you be fitted for a Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, how ever the world think of you, labour tobe ſo really, or elſe the ſeales will be uneffectuall to you, circumciſion is effectuall if you keep the Law, or elſe it will be nothing: you profeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e your ſelves Chriſtians, your Baptiſme is good, if you keep the Law, and walk ſutable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, otherwiſe you may deceive your ſelves. <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.3. <hi>If hee thinke himſelfe ſomething, &amp;c.</hi> therefore try your own hearts; if you bee more in ſhew then in ſubſtance, you have no cauſe to joy in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God that you doe enjoy: and therefore examine your ſelves, it is not what other men think or judge of you; for you may loſe all the benefit of ordinances, and loſe your ſelves and all, and loſe your profeſſion, and all that you have done in the Goſpel, if you doe not ſearch your ſelves. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 29. <hi>He is a Jew that is one within, whoſe praiſe is not of Man, but of God;</hi> that will give him aſſurance if hee be found in the ſtatutes of God: <hi>whoſe praiſe is not of man but of God,</hi> ſuch a man may have comfort. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.21. <hi>If our hearts condemns us not, then have we b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, &amp;c.</hi> otherwiſe if men think you be good, and you know you are not; if men think you are true, and you know you are falſe: God knowes all things, and will proceed more rigidly againſt you, he knowes more then your ſelves doe.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:111041:14"/>
            <p>Now to the next Head. <hi>Infants are capable:</hi> And here is the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thing of the buſineſſe, and therfore you muſt give me leave to expatiate; I will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more large where the moſt difficulty lies, and I will open my ſelfe in ſeverall propoſitions how to diſcern they are capable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That there is a portion and proviſion of Grace appointed by God, and beſtowed of God on ſome children, according to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his own will. Here are two things to be avoided.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Curioſity: for ſecret things belong to God.</item>
               <item>2 Careleſneſſe: for where God hath a mouth to ſpeak, we muſt have an eare to heate.</item>
            </list>
            <p>We muſt be carefull therefore to know this truth: But what the number of Infants be, and after what manner he doth beſtow this Grace, I will ſay nothing; but what the Word hath learned me, I will learn you, That ſome children are elected, and God will ſanctifie them, and glorifie them; but for the number, and manner, I leave that. Mr <hi>Spilsbery</hi> oppoſes two of theſe, <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Glorification,</hi> when they are againſt the expreſſions of the Word; ſo they are not onely er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but groſſe errors. In the third page, line 14. his words are, <hi>They muſt be capable of Grace, or elſe they are not elected.</hi> Now he ſaith, children in their nonage are not ſubjects of <hi>Election,</hi> or of <hi>Glory.</hi> I oppoſe both; There is a portion of Grace for children, and Glory: If he ſpeak to the purpoſe, and ſay, there is no faith in Election; or capability of Glory; I doe not think children becauſe they are children, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected &amp; glorified, there is no ſhew of the queſtion in that ancient men are not elected becauſe they are old, nor glorified becauſe they are old; he will ſave them from ſinne, not as they are old, or rich, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, that is not ſenſible: &amp; therefore his meaning is, that Children fall not within compaſſe of election, nor if they dye, to have glory; and that is a groſſe error. There is a number of children that it is the purpoſe of God according to election to ſave them. <hi>Rom</hi> 9.11, 12. <hi>The children being not yet born, it was ſaid, The elder ſhall ſerve the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Malach.</hi> 1.2, 3. <hi>Was not Eſau Jacobs brother? yet I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Jacob, and hated Eſau.</hi> And, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Whom he will he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</hi> And this is upon children not as children, but while they are ſuch; all the men in the world are either veſſels of mercy, or veſſels of wrath, according to the good will of God.</p>
            <p>Now if all be under election or reprobation, to ſay all children are rejected, were groſſe, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 25.22, 23. <hi>The children ſtruggle in her womb, the Lord ſaid, Two Nations are in thy womb, &amp;c.</hi> And they were types of the children of light, and the children of darkneſſe, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111041:14"/>ſo muſt our children be children of light, or children of darkneſſe. Now to ſay all are rejected, he hath not the face of a man that will ſay ſo; for the Word hath taught us the contrary.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if there be a number of children to whom the Kingdome of Heaven belongs unto, then bleſſedneſſe belongs to children: But that it is ſo, appears, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. <hi>For of ſuch is the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Now Anabaptiſts darken that place, and ſay, Theſe are not chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but men of years, ſuch as are humble, &amp; of a childlike diſpoſition. But the Gloſſe does corrupt the Text, and croſſes the ſcope of the place: for Chriſt ſpake it to make it appeare they may bee bleſſed here, thus: If to ſuch belong the Kingdome of Heaven, they may bee glorified; if they may be glorified, then they may be bleſſed here. The ſenſe the Anabaptiſts give, makes it ſenſleſſe: if it ſtand thus, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven belongs to the humble, it is one thing to be humble. and another thing to be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>What is this to children of yeares? If children belong to heaven, they may be bleſſed here, and therefore our Saviour calls them, and bids them come to him, that he might bleſſe them: and the nature of the thing teacheth it; for there are but two places after this life, Hell or Heaven, except men will follow the dotage of the Papiſts, to make a Purgatory, which fire was kindled in the Popes Kitchin. Now to ſay all children that are dead are in hell, they dare not ſay ſo: now that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery</hi> ſaith, <hi>He will ſay nothing to it:</hi> he muſt ſay ſo; for he can ſay nothing to any purpoſe, therefore he ſpeakes that to dazle mens eyes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there are ſome children God will work grace in now, <hi>Luke</hi> 1 15. it is ſaid of <hi>John, That hee was filled with the holy Ghoſt from his mothers womb.</hi> Chriſt did ſanctifie one, to ſhew there are more that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſhall be ſanctified here, and therefore it appeares there are a number of children that God doth beſtow grace upon here, and ſhall be glorified hereafter.</p>
            <p>And although the manner of Gods working upon children be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mans account, yet it is ordinary with God to work it in them, that day he workes faith in them, certainly they are as capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the work of the Spirit, as men are; but the manner of working is ſecret. But it is Gods common courſe; and certainly he doth work faith in them. Infants are as capable as men conſidering the work of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Propoſition: Although the manner of working be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in reſpect of the meanes, and the perſons upon whom it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111041:15"/>is wrought, yet in regard of God it is ordinary and eaſie; and he doth certainly work faith in the hearts of infants that die in their infancy, that are elected; and alſo in regard of the Spirit that is the worker of it in them.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is extraordinary in regard of the meanes; if we have an eye to, the meanes, that puts not forth that power as it doth when there is a concurrence of all things that are ſutable to work with the means; and therefore when this is wanting now to do it, is extraordinary; But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants doe not, nor cannot thus concurre: for they cannot exerciſe their underſtanding, they cannot put it forth as men of yeares can doe, they cannot put forth to the ſignification, they cannot take it in ſo far as to affect their hearts with the nature of it: therfore all ſuch power upon their actual apprehenſions, ſignification, taking, &amp; working, of abilities of their own, it is onely to men of yeares, it is beyond the rank and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of infants, and the means cannot worke in this regard beyond their order and rank, to doe as to men of yeares they may. And the ſame may be ſaid of circumciſion; for there is the like difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men of yeares and infants in that, and yet this did not hinder Gods end in that ordinance, nor did it prejudice the good God inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to beſtow upon infants, though the abilities of infants could not receive it from the Ordinance, or the Ordinance receive help from them: for this is extraordinary, and beyond the parts of a child, that is the meaning of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Yet in regard of God it is his ordinary courſe, and certainly he doth work faith in the hearts of all elected infants that dye in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy. Doe not ſtumble that I uſe the phraſes of <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> in regard of the parties and meanes, it is ordinary with God, for we may ſee it ſo in other workes of God, as in the work of vocation there is an infuſion of a ſpirituall principle into the ſoule, which is beyond all the abilities of the nature of any man to bring it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own ſoule: but if we look at the work of God, then the way that God hath made known, is ordinary, and a continued courſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe a principle of grace into the ſoule. So it is Gods ordinary way to put faith into an infant that is elected, and dies an infant. As for inſtance, there are many revelations of God, every revelation is a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spirit, but it is according to the Word. Now although it is extraordinary in regard of the work of the Spirit revealing; yet it is ordinary with God. Now this comes to the heart of the cauſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this give me leave to do three things.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:111041:15"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 To open the meaning, and ſtate the queſtion, how God doth put faith into infants.</item>
               <item>2 That it ſhould not ſeem hard, nor men ſhould not think it hard to ſay, God works in this manner.</item>
               <item>3 We will give you the reaſons of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 In the meaning of it, the ſecreſie of God does drive men to much trouble: it is like an unbeaten way to the Seamen, they muſt ſound e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part of it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Some think it is kept in his own ſecret will.</item>
               <item>2 Some think the Spirit does work it.</item>
               <item>3 Some think God puts in a ſeed of faith.</item>
               <item>4 Some think there is a habit of faith put into the Soule.</item>
               <item>5 Some think God does powre faith into the heart of infants that die in infancie that be elected, that they ſhall be converted, and put into Chriſt: this is the main truth of the queſtion. God does powre it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoule, and ſo the ſoule is converted, and planted into Chriſt as the head of the covenant. This is the ſtate of the controverſie, and this I ſhall labour to ſtrengthen.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, it ſhould not be ſtrange, nor need not to bee counted hard to any judicious Chriſtian, to aſſent to this. The reaſon is, becauſe there is a work alike, in a parity to that which is daily expreſſed in the courſe of Gods providence, and is acknowledged by all judicious, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt. And if it be ſo, why may he not doe the like in this? That there is a like work, and that it is acknowledged, appeares thus: It is a confeſſed truth that the Lord does infuſe a ſoule into the body, and the ſoule is pure and holy as it comes from him, otherwiſe God muſt be the authour of ſinne; yet through the ſinne and guilt of <hi>Adam,</hi> the ſoule is turned from God, and is poſſeſt with originall ſinne, and ſo ſin and guilt is imputed, and the curſe juſtly inflicted. And the ſoule being thus wholly turned from God, it is wholly poſſeſt with originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. It is a deluſion to ſay the ſoule is propagated. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.3. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam beg at a ſonne in his own image,</hi> being wholly turned from God, and turned to ſin. And <hi>John</hi> 3.6. <hi>That which is born of the flaſh is fleſh;</hi> all comes from the ſin of <hi>Adam.</hi> Now mark, if this be ſo, that the ſin &amp; guilt of <hi>Adam</hi> is thus conveyed, and the guilt &amp; curſe, this is done dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though we ſee not the manner how it is done: then why may not Chriſt convey grace, turne the heart of a child from ſin to himſelf? the party is the ſame as before, and look to the cauſe, and it is greater in the latter then in the former: if we looke at Chriſt, there is an advantage in reaſon to believe the latter rather then the former; and why ſhould
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111041:16"/>it be thought a thing incredible, ſeeing the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> can turn away the ſoule from God, but that Chriſt by the power of his merits, may convert Infants to himſelfe; and why then ſhould it bee incredible? Now one of theſe are done from day to day, and none doubt of it, I meane the firſt; and the ſecond we have more advantage to believe, becauſe the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is above the firſt, and why then ſhould not the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> be as readily aſſented unto as the firſt; but every man is forced to yeeld the firſt (that is judicious) let us not doubt the ſecond.</p>
            <p>One thing is to be noted in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery's</hi> Booke, in the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page, 19 lines from the end, where he ſaith, <hi>The word condemnes none but for actuall ſinne;</hi> if he mean, as he muſt needs doe, no man is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned but for the ſinne of the party it ſelfe, it is a groſſe error, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>For as by one man ſinne entredinto the world, and death by ſinne, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, <hi>If by the finne of one man judgement came upon all,</hi> then for the ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> God may juſtly condemne all, though they never commit actuall ſin, is the judgement of all that are judicious. Death over ſpread all by <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, and therefore wee ſee in infants that dye, <hi>Adams</hi> ſin was actuall; and let him ſhift what he can, the caſe is cleare, and the word condemnes men for originall ſinne: <hi>The wages of ſinne is death;</hi> ſo originall ſinne it is the rebelling againſt the law of out mind, and therefore it muſt be ſinne, and to ſay the contrary, is a groſſe fulſome error: Mark when ſuch errors come from the pens of men, it ſhewes there is more behind; and he muſt ſay, either originall ſin is no ſin, or that infants have no originall ſinne: And if he ſay ſo then the ſin of the heathen cannot hinder, but that all their children that dye, muſt be ſaved. If you look in the forenamed place in his book, you may finde it: I ſpeak it that men that have the books may find it. And let no man think that theſe things be ſtrange, ſeeing the like is done, that you may ſee with eaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Now I will give you in the Reaſons; but firſt let me lay ſome grounds before I diſpute it.
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Ground,</hi> All infants are guilty of ſinne, and liable to the guilt, and curſe, and condemnation for ſin; they are all guilty, becauſe they were all in <hi>Adams</hi> loyns, as in a common root; and therefore they muſt ſhare with him. <hi>Doe and live, Doe not and die</hi> ſpiritually: And ſo he falling, all his poſterity is poſſeſſed with originall ſinne, as <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Hee beg at a ſonne in his own likeneſſe.</hi> What was the Image of the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi> Ignorance, and unbeliefe, and ſtubbornneſſe, &amp;c. <hi>As wee have born the Image of the earthly, ſo we muſt beare the Image of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly;</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111041:16"/>but we have born the image of the earthly, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. <hi>That which is born of the fleſh is fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> And again, none can bring a clean thing out of an uncl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>; therefore Children dying in ſin, the Curſe is theirs.</item>
                  <item>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Ground.</hi> Children being guilty of ſin and the curſe, they muſt be delivered, but they cannot deliver themſelves; and therefore they muſt be delivered by another, and none can deliver them but Chriſt; for there is no other name whereby wee can be ſaved: <hi>Acts</hi> 4. and therefore it is he that muſt ſave Infants.</item>
                  <item>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Ground.</hi> If Infants muſt be ſaved by Chriſt, and have a ſhare in grace and glory, then they muſt be united unto Chriſt; for where there is no union, there is no communion; therefore if they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, there muſt be union: <hi>He that hath the ſonna hath life, and he that hath not the ſonne hath not life;</hi> and John 1.12. <hi>To as many as receive him, to them he gave prerogative to be the ſonnes of God, even to them that believe on his name.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. There is no union with Chriſt without agreement of both parties, for if there be oppoſition of one partie, it is diſſention and not union; and nature cannot unite it ſelf to Chriſt, and corruption will not, and therefore grace muſt, nature cannot, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14 <hi>The naturall man underſtandeth not the things of God, neither can he, &amp;c.</hi> ſo as nature cannot, it muſt be a ſpirituall name, and <hi>John</hi> 14.17. <hi>Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to ſend the ſpirit, which the world cannot receive, nor corruption will not:</hi> Rom. 8.7. <hi>The carnall minde is enmity againſt God, it is not ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be,</hi> the fleſh will oppoſe: but only Chriſt and grace cannot but conſent to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. therefore it muſt be by grace and Chriſt muſt give the grace, by which we come to cloſe with him, if any grace, then faith; my faith before any, becauſe it is the uniting grace: you young ones, take this in, Children muſt be ſaved by Chriſt; for theſe <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> will be dealing with you, they ſtudy not ſelf-denyall nor humility; and therefore they will be dealing with Children: but know, faith is the grace of union; if Children will have glory, they muſt have a ſhare in Chriſt by grace; therefore they muſt have the grace of union, that is, by faith they muſt be united unto Chriſt; or take it thus, if they be united unto Chriſt, they have grace, and therefore faith, if they are converted unto Chriſt: If Children have communion they muſt have union; but if they be elected, they have communion, becauſe they ſhall be glorified.</p>
            <p>If Children dye in their infancy, that be elected, they are converted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111041:17"/>really, and they have faith wrought in them in truth, it is a truth out of the ſeripture; if they did not believe there was no converſion in the Old Teſtament, converſion and faith is the ſame; but they are really converted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if they be not really converted, then they are averted from God eternally unto ſin; they cannot ſay ſo, for if they doe, they muſt ſay, they are damned; for it is contrary to their being in heaven, for if they enjoy God, they muſt be converted; think of this you that are wiſe: to ſay a man may depart from God, and live with God, it is a profeſſed contradiction, for it is a hell to ſtand againſt God, if it were in heaven, and an humble heart is happy in hell; and therefore it is to ſay, a perſon is ſaved, and yet he is damned.</p>
            <p>All the ſinfull ſons of men, that ſtand defiled with originall ſinne, if God ſave them without faith, then he ſaves them in the ſtate of unbelief, they are unfaithfull; if God will ſave them, he ſaves and maintains them in a ſtate of unbeliefe, contrary to <hi>John</hi> 3.18. <hi>Hee that believeth not is condemned already;</hi> and elſe where it is ſaid, <hi>He that believes not ſhal be damned;</hi> and if God ſave them in a ſtate of unbeliefe, then he muſt maintain them in a ſtate of unbeliefe, and in that eſtate he is an unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable; ſubject in all capable ſubjects take away the perfection, and imperfection will follow; take away ſight from the eyes, and blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will follow; and take faith from the ſoule, and unbelief will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; ſo that if faith be gone, unbelief will be there: but they ſay, thoſe places are meant of men of years; that is but a ſhift; they may ſay it is but meerly affirmed and we deny it, and our deny all is as good as their affirmation: but we ſay, as the word ſaies, <hi>He that believeth not ſhall be damned:</hi> and it is contrary to the nature of the thing, for if God ſave them, and maintain them in their unbelife, hee muſt ſave their ſoules and their ſins, and ſo they muſt carry their unbelief into heaven (and if that be taken away faith will be there) and if unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe be there, there will be a departing from God, as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Take heed leaſt there be in any of you a heart of unbeliefe, &amp;c.</hi> ſo that there muſt be a departing from God in heaven, this is a contradiction, and therefore it is a meer conceit.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thoſe that are accepted with God, thoſe muſt have faith; but ſo are elect Children that die in their infancy; <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.4. <hi>By faith</hi> Abel <hi>offered unto God a more excellent ſacrifice then</hi> Kain, &amp;c. Why is God offended, but for ſin, and it cannot be removed but by faith; for we muſt have Chriſt to remove our ſin, and if we will have Chriſt, we muſt have faith; and as for juſtification and ſanctification, ſo of glorification, all come by Chriſt; and therefore they muſt have faith,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111041:17"/>or elſe they muſt come unclean into heaven, but that is impoſſible, for no unclean thing ſhall enter into heaven, they muſt be converted unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now to the third thing: the third branch is, that in regard of the operation of the ſpirit, Infants are as capable as men, I am forced to ſpeak thus, becauſe I muſt have to deale with Mr. <hi>Spilebery,</hi> and that I might meet with him, I have on purpoſe expreſſed my ſelf on this manner: When it is objected to him, that Infants are capable, he anſwers in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> page, and the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> line, thus, <hi>If by being ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable be meant oppoſition againſt the Spirit, that they cannot oppoſe the ſpirit in working on them, then ſtones are capable; for God can raiſe of ſtones Children to</hi> Abraham: <hi>but if this be the meaning, they are as able to comply with the Spirit, I deny it: and to affirm that, this is the way God uſes to bring children to him, I oppoſe it; and it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues ignorance to ſay ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, it is the truth of God, and it is Gods way to work ſo, and that Children are as capable as men of years; if we eye the operation of the Spirit, and the diſpenſation thereof, they are as capable as men, much more therefore then ſtones; and that I will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and prove in foure things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The nature of man as it was made fit for grace before the fall, ſo it is capable of grace after the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> when I ſay capable, I ſay two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſubſtance of the ſoule and body need not be changed from their being, when they receive grace, the nature of the ſoule and body being not changed, but unfitted for any ſpirituall work: As take a Clock that all the wheels are out of frame, you need not make new Wheels but onely rectifie them, if they be foule make them clean, if they be wrong right them; ſo by the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> all, ſoule and body is out of frame, and out of joynt, the minde unfit to know God, and the will unfit to cloſe with God; before the fall all were in frame, but when it jarred againſt the Law, then Originall ſinne came upon all his ſeed, and that makes them jarre againſt the law: now when a ſinner comes to be renewed, there needes not new faculties, but thoſe he hath, to be ſet in frame; this is the meaning of the Spirit of God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Plow up your fallow ground, &amp;c.</hi> ſo the minde is arrable ground although it be over grown with luſts, that as there is no fruit of holines to God, or righteouſnes to men; but the minde of man is over run with diſtempers, and therefore (as they ſay) we muſt give it another tilling, by plowing up the weeds, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19. <hi>As you have given your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111041:18"/>members weapons to unrighteouſnes; ſo now give your members as ſervants unto righteouſneſſe, unto holineſſe:</hi> the meaning is, as we have given our members, in the ſame proportion as we have given them to ſin; ſo we ſhould give them to be at the command of the ſpirit, the ſame underſtanding, will, and affections; whereas, if God raiſe them out of ſtones, as he can doe, he muſt firſt give it to be a man, and make it to have a body and a ſoule, and then convert it; but he need not doe ſo, when he comes to men or children: As if a man would have a crop of Corn upon a rock, he muſt firſt make it ground, and then plow them; but if hee have ground, although it have thorns and rubbiſh, when he hath removed that, he may plow it, and expect a crop, becauſe ground is capable to bear Corn. Now the proof of the point is plain; that the nature of man is capable, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears; that which is capable of a privation is capable of the habit of the contrary grace. of neceſſity; the in beeing of a thing requires a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blens: the eye cannot be ſaid to be blind except it be capable of ſeeing; it is not ſaid, a mans hand is blinde, becauſe it is not capable of ſeeing; ſo the body may be ſaid to be dead, becauſe it is capable of life; ſo it is in the underſtanding, it is full of blindeneſſe, becauſe it is capable of ſeeing; and ſo the will is capable of holineſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Once you were darknes, now you are light in the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. <hi>As we have born the Image of the earthly, ſo we muſt beare the image of the heavenly;</hi> the body is ſick, and it may have help.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Our nature is not nextly fit for grace, yet it is capable, that is, the roome may be made fit, though it be not fit for the preſent: as a Veſſell that is full of ill liquor, it is capable to hold good liquor, but it is not fit before the filthy liquor be powred out: ſo our nature is capable of grace, we need not change our being, but wee muſt bee made fit.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Particular.</hi> The ſpirit of God does in all men, whether young or old, firſt looſe the ſoule of a ſinner from ſin and ſelf, by his Almighty power; before he puts a principle of grace into the ſoule, and before he leads the ſoule to God in Chriſt, this muſt be done; take a childe, or a man, God does work this, it is the nature of Gods diſpenſation, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>To open their eyes, that they may turn from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to God, &amp;c.</hi> Firſt, they are taken from under him, and then they are turned to God, and <hi>John</hi> 15.19. <hi>Becauſe I have choſen you out of the world, therfore the world hates you, &amp;c.</hi> you were under the power of ſin, and I have called you out, &amp; then I will cal you to my ſelfe <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Who hath delivered us from the power
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111041:18"/>of darkneſſe, and tranſlated us into the kingdom of his dear Son, &amp;c.</hi> We muſt be cut off from the wilde Olive before we can be planted into the true Olive: It was never known an Imp could grow on two ſtocks at once; you cannot ſerve two Maſters, you cannot be in Hell Heaven together, there cannot be two Gods in one heart, it is not poſſible: therefore ſee how <hi>John</hi> prepares the way for Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.5, 6, 7. <hi>The mountains muſt be laid low, and the crooked things muſt be made ſtrait, and then they ſhall ſee the ſalvation of God:</hi> ſo it is withall the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> nature and reaſon will conſtrain the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In this double work of the ſpirit, the ſpirit depoſes ſin and ſelf, and then powers in a principle of grace: in both theſe, all men that receive the worke of the ſpirit are meere patients: when it depoſes ſin and ſelf, young and old, and are meer patients, all men, children, and infants; thus it is in all on whom the great work of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion is, they are meerly patients; we have already made it good: I will give you two or three reaſons of it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Averſion cannot bee a cauſe of ſalvation, a frame to turn from God cannot help a man to turn to God, no more then light can cauſe darkneſſe, ſin and ſelf carry the ſoule from God; and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not carry the ſoule to God. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>For the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit luſteth againſt the fleſh;</hi> and thoſe are contrary one to another. Now that which deſtroyes the work of the ſpirit, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring it in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. <hi>I know that in me, that is, in my fleſh dwelleth no good thing:</hi> now that which hath no ſpirituall good, can doe no ſpirituall good, and ſo it cannot helpe to God.</item>
               <item>2. That which cannot be ſubject to the Law of God, cannot be a cauſe of the work of the ſpirit, but ſin and ſelf cannot be ſubject, and therefore they cannot be the cauſe of the working of the ſpirit; nay, the nature of man cannot be, nay they cannot ſuffer the work upon them, they are not able to bear it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. <hi>It is not ſubject to the law of God, neither indeed can be.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. That which is wholy beyond the power of corrupt nature, that corrupt nature cannot bee the cauſe of; but to put off ſin and ſelf, is wholy beyond the power of corrupt nature; for nothing can work beyond the power of its own principle; and of our ſelves, we are not able to think a good thought; So it muſt be given us, ſo we have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this, that therefore, we are all meer patients in the work of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, both men and children.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="4">4. Here lies the life of the anſwer in theſe ſeverall works, where the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111041:19"/>hearts are ſufferers, the ſoules of Infants are as much fit as the ſoules of any man, and not ſo much unfit as the ſoules of many men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive grace: and they have as great a capability as men have, and in ſome meaſure a greater capabilitic then ſome men have: here is two things to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they are as fit as any, but not ſo unfit as many; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all are meet ſufferers in the work of the ſpirit to have ſin and ſelf ſubdued; the ſoules of children are as fit, and have as great a capabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the world.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You muſt remember, heretofore we have made it good, that all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> are tainted with Originall ſin equally, no man have leſſe of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, nor leſſe of Originall ſin one then another, but all men and children are equall here, and men of years have contracted many actuall ſins; nay, whatever they doe before they are converted, is ſin, all their thoughts, words, and deeds, ſo as they grow more proud and more witty to commit ſin, and to doe wickedly: becauſe of actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all tranſgreſſion ſome grow more ſturdy in their ſinfull courſes, which is drawn and contracted by actuall ſin, and infants are free from thoſe; now thoſe that have acted them, are more fit to commit them, nay many are habituated in commiting of ſin, ſo as they have gotten a habit of drunkennes, and a habit of uncleanes, &amp;c. ſo as it is plain, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are as fit as any, and not ſo unfit as many are; for if children have as little oppoſition as any, and leſſe then ſome, then it muſt needes be true. For where leſſe oppoſition againſt a thing is, there is leſſe trouble to receive it, for they are contrary, for where leſſe oppoſition is, there is a greater diſpoſition to receive it; but that children doe as little oppoſe grace as any man of years: all oppoſition comes from the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> and Originall ſin came from that; and here wee ſee all are equall in men of years and children, and this is the firſt kinde of oppoſition.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Sort of oppoſition ariſe from ſinfull habits, and this comes by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall ſin, and by this we come to bee more ſelf-confident, and all theſe infants are free of; a man that hath lived many years in ſin, is come to be habituated in ſin, as a man that dotes upon the world gets a habit of covetouſnes, and a man gets a habit of frowardnes; theſe infants are freed from, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.28. <hi>Wilt thou kill me, &amp;c?</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 18.6. <hi>And when they reſiſted and blaſphemed, &amp;c.</hi> Children are dead in ſin; but ſome men are twice dead, as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks at the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. verſe, <hi>Twice dead, and plucked up by the roots,</hi> and as Chriſt ſayd of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, <hi>they made men twofold more the childe of Hell:</hi> take the moſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111041:19"/>men living, and there is Sin and Selfe to be ſubdued; and in regard of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſin, and originall ſin they are all alike. But by actuall ſin, men are full of carnall confidence, and therfore the Spirit muſt have much to do here becauſe men do harden their own hearts, and ſo make themſelves twenty times more the child of hell; ſo they are <hi>twice dead, and pulled up by the root;</hi> ſo that they are leſſe fit then ſome naturall men in the world, and many men in the world, that are but men of the world, are more fit then they; ſo that children are more capable then any man. The place in <hi>Jude</hi> is ſpoken againſt falſe Prophets, they were <hi>twice dead,</hi> they were dead by originall ſin &amp; actuall ſin; there is a ſort that hath received a ſeeming light, and get a little of the Word, and that he is provoked, that a man thinks he is a living man. There is another ſort that perſecute the Word, now theſe are dead again, ſo they are <hi>twice dead,</hi> he is provoked by the work of the Law, and now he is more proud, and is as athing <hi>pulled up by the roots,</hi> ſo as nothing can recover him, no poſſibility to come neere him, ſo as it is ſo farre from being harder for the Spirit to work upon infants, that there is an eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this kind.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Propoſition:</hi> Beleeving Parents when they enter into a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble covenant to walk in Gods wayes, they enter not for themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but for all that come of them; and God does ingage himſelfe by their meanes to worke grace in their hearts as he ſees fit; hee counts them to have federall holineſſe: God accepts of both, and he will doe good to them as he ſees fit. In this Propoſition there are foure things to be conſidered.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Believing Parents enter into a viſible covenant for themſelves and their poſterity.</item>
               <item>2 God expects it at the hands of them both.</item>
               <item>3 God ingages himſelfe to uſe them as inſtruments to doe good to them as he ſees fit; God wil give grace to his children, he will uſe them to his own mind, God will uſe them as inſtruments; but he will doe them good as he ſees fit: not that parents can give grace, or worke grace in their children, and therefore ſpeak not ſo; for that is, as if when God works upon the heart by the preaching of the word, you ſhould ſay the Miniſter gives grace.</item>
               <item>4 God accounts children as having federall holineſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 When believing Parents enter into a viſible covenant, they doe enter into it for themſelves and children: But they muſt enter into a viſible covenant, the reaſon of it is, becauſe communication of them that doe ſo enter into covenant, doe in reaſon belong to them that be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111041:20"/>in a community of other, according to rationall charity; becauſe God gives the priviledges of his holy things to a community of men, and they muſt judge according to a rule of charity, and paſſe ſentence as things appeare according to that rule: For if it be left to every privat man to judge, that every man may judge himſelf fit, and be his owne Judge, to partake of the ordinances, then theſe two evils will follow.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 An abuſing and prophaning Gods holy things: for he would carve all to himſelfe although he had no right nor reaſon ſo to doe. So that if they be left to them ſelves they would prophane them.</item>
               <item>2 There will be a confuſion on the holy things of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that God hath given them lawes, and hath committed theſe to a community of men, and hath left it to them, according to the rule of rationall charity, to judge whom they will admit, and to thoſe they do admit, to become ſubject to thoſe Lawes and Rules, and live according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſo as it is committed to them for that purpoſe, to whom and when they pleaſe. Thus it was in the time of the Law, and thus it is in the times of the Goſpel, and ſo it ſhall be to the comming of Chriſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Thus it was in the time of the Law, they muſt be in covenant, the people of the Jewes were taken in from the world, and <hi>hee gave them lawes, he hath not dealt ſo with any Nation, Pſalm</hi> 147.20. The treaſury of his Lawes were committed to them. And <hi>Romanes</hi> 3.1. all the ſpirituall priviledges were committed to the Jewes. <hi>What is the priviledge of the Jewes? Much every way, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.11. <hi>For as the girdle cleaves to the loynes of a man, ſo have I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied to me the whole Houſe of Iſrael, &amp;c. But they would not hear, [that they might] be people to God,</hi> and then have that honour. This is the reaſon in <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.38. he ſpeak thus, <hi>Now becauſe of all this, we make a ſure covenant and write it, and our Princes, and our Levitse, and our Prieſts ſeale unto it.</hi> Hence it is, that all the choyce priviledges are the Legacies of the Jewes. And <hi>Exodus</hi> 12.43. <hi>No ſtranger ſhall cat thereof.</hi> And therefore they muſt be in the compaſſe of a viſible Church. Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is the proper name and livery of Gods people. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>You were Gentiles, and called uncircumciſion of them that were called Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, &amp;c.</hi> and that were the Jewes, and they were the people of God, to whom it was left, to judge of them that were fit to be made par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akers of theſe priviledges.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is thus alſo in the time of the Goſpel, they muſt be ingaged in the covenant; and the Seales, and Officers, and Ordinances of the Church are their propriety. As for the Officers, <hi>Chriſt when he aſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he gave gifts unto men, and ordained ſome to be Apoſtles, and ſome
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111041:20"/>Prophers, &amp;c.</hi> Hee ſpake of ſome part for the whole, therefore in an ordinary way it muſt be a viſible Church, the inviſible do not meet to chuſe; but the officers are by the choyce of ſuch a people in ſuch a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, and God does ſet them in a particular Church, and the Officers are to diſpenſe the things of God to that Church: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Miniſter without a people, is as a husband without a wife. And therefore all the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s muſt be diſpenſed by the Officers of the Church, and by none elſe, as appointed by God ſo to do. And therefore the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of the Church muſt be diſpenſed by faithfull men, choſen by the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3. <hi>Chuſe you men of honeſt report, and full of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> If they muſt be ſo that muſt order the treaſure of the Church, much more the ſeales, which are the ſpeciall treaſures of the Church; they muſt be men that have gifts choſen; &amp; the Sacraments are the ſeales of the Covenant, one with another we are all one bread, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10.17. <hi>For we that are many, are but one bread.</hi> And if there be no Officers but in the Church, and they that be Officers are to adminiſter onely to the Church, they muſt needs be a company ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in a Church. How a man muſt be fitted to come into a Church, belongs not to me now.</p>
            <p n="3">3 This muſt continue till the comming of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. <hi>And though ſome of the branches be broken off, and thou being a wild Olive tree, wert grafted in for them, and made partaker of the root and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Olive tree.</hi> Where h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeakes of unchurching of the Jews, and Churching of the Gentiles, <hi>If the branches be cut off, and thou art grafted in, and made partakers of the fatneſſe of this Olive tree:</hi> So as the Gentiles are made partakers of the fatneſſe of the Olive; the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live tree is the Church, and the fatneſſe of the Olive tree is the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that appertain thereunto; ſo as alwayes they muſt be ingrafted into the Church, before they can have the priviledges belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and this ſhall be to the end of the world. When the Jews are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, they ſhal come into a Church of God: this is the firſt, they ſhall enter into a Church, and then the fatneſſe followes to the branches in the Olive.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they covenant for their children as well as for themſelves. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10. <hi>You ſtand this day every one of you before the Lord your God, your Children, your wives, &amp;c.</hi> which ſhewes they may receive the covenant. When he ſpeaks of the covenant in the breadth of it, then he takes in their little ones, and therefore parents covenant as well for their litle ones, they undertake for all that ſhall be born of them, they are in their parents loynes, all of them are under their power, and they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111041:21"/>have authority to impoſe the law of God upon them. So in <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17. 10, 11. <hi>Let every man child be circumciſed, and this ſhall be a token between me and you, of my covenant, every male ſhall be circumciſed.</hi> This is the cauſe why <hi>Joſhua</hi> when he was to depart the world, ſaid to the people, <hi>Chuſe you whom you will ſerve, but I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Every believer hath power to bring his children into this covenant, it was a ſpeciall prerogative to <hi>Abraham</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery</hi> ſaith, <hi>If this be to every believing Parent as to Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, then every beleever muſt be the father of the faithfull, as Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I deny the conſequence: for it will not follow, if we looke at <hi>Abraham</hi> as a pattern of believers, hence the priviledges and covenant are entailed upon <hi>Abraham</hi> to all the nations of the world, viſibly to be diſpenſed to all the nations of the world, and they ſhall know and imitate him, and God will ſave them; <hi>He is the Father of the faithfull</hi> by imitation, the covenant is made after <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. he is called, and the root is ſtated upon him. Although there was a covenant with <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Shem,</hi> yet it was ſtated upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> and not upon them, ſo as the conſequence fails: But if we look to his perſonall faith, he hath power to his children onely. But <hi>No Spilsbery</hi> in the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page, 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> lines, if it be meant to all his children, he conceives he had many children by <hi>Keturah, Geneſ.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he conceives was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the covenant; for they were not partakers of the ſeales. This will follow: for <hi>Keturah</hi> was not worſe then <hi>Hagar,</hi> for ſhe was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubine as well as <hi>Keturah,</hi> yet <hi>Abraham</hi> did circumciſe <hi>Iſhmael</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God, and it is his glory. If <hi>Iſhmael</hi> have right to the ſeale, why not the children of <hi>Keturah?</hi> And we cannot thinke otherwiſe in charity; if no man have right to the ſeale but thoſe that are in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible covenant, why then may we not believe the ſonnes of <hi>Keturah</hi> were as well as <hi>Iſhmael:</hi> If you ſay <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was not, becauſe he was baniſhed, otherwiſe <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt goe againſt his light and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his practice, for he muſt know and doe contrary to his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; therefore we may ſay, they ſhared in the covenant and ſeales as well as <hi>Iſhmael.</hi> But if you ſay, <hi>He was baniſhed afterward,</hi> I anſwer, that was when his evill appeared; but before he was not, but was made partaker of the ſeales, and ſo in the viſible covenant. And ſo it was with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> he was viſibly in the covenant, and ſhared in the ſeales, and <hi>Philip</hi> did right, according to the Rules of Charity; but if it appeare otherwiſe after, they may be caſt out. Many men have been baptized, and afterward, their wickedneſſe hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:111041:21"/>
            <p n="2">2 God accepteth of both parents &amp; children, <hi>Deu.</hi> 265. <hi>And thou ſhalt ſay before the Lord thy God, A Syrian was my father, who being ready to periſh, went' down into Egypt.</hi> He ſpeakes of all parents &amp; children; and when they were to bring their firſt fruits, he ſaith, <hi>Thou haſt avouched the Lord to be thy God, &amp; he hath avouched thee to be his people.</hi> So <hi>Deu.</hi> 29.10, 11, 13. <hi>You ſtand before the Lord your God, your Heads of your Tribes, your Elders, your Officers, even all the men of Iſrael, your children, your wives, &amp;c. that thou ſhouleſt paſſe into the covenant of the Lord thy God, and into his oath which the Lord thy God makes with thee this day, for to eſtabliſh thee this day a people to himſelf, &amp;c.</hi> Whom God doth eſtabliſh his covenant unto, they have right to it, that is, to them, their wives, and their little ones. Let no man bogell and ſay, God enters covenant with wicked ones: For all their daily waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and offerings did ſhew forth this, that they were ſinners, in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we may ſee it: You may ask whether the Apoſtles did not rightly gather the Churches of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and the reſt of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches of <hi>Aſia;</hi> and ask if that all that were ſo gathered, were not bapt zed according to God; and yet it is ſaid of <hi>Sardis,</hi> there were but a few names; and of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> it was poore, and blind, and naked, and faults in other of the Churches; ſhall any man ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were not in covenant? God deals and diſpenſes his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by men, and he proceeds according to the rules of Religion and rationall Charity, by the miniſtery of men, and goes by the judgements of men, according to thoſe rules.</p>
            <p n="3">3 God does ingage himſelfe to communicate ſpirituall good to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by meanes of their parents, as he ſees fit, reſerving ſecret things to himſelfe, when and in what manner he will doe it: he ingages him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to communicate ſpirituall good to children, and he will uſe the parents as meanes of that good, and that he will doe two wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The parent covenanting with God, the Covenant is improved as a meanes that God will work ſpirituall good in the child: As when a Miniſter or a Friend doth give counſel that a perſon gets good by, God uſes them as meanes of that good: ſo hee doth parents; for by their meanes the children are brought into covenant, and ſo God commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates good to them, which before God had ſtirred up, and by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents they come into covenant, and ſo God communicates good to the children. Hence we may come to ſee the right underſtanding of that which <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>And thou Solomon my ſonne, know the God of thy Fathers,</hi> remember I have ingaged my ſelfe in covenant; and know thou that God that hath ingaged himſelf to thy father, hath ingaged
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111041:22"/>himſelf by the father to do good unto thee, and that is the beſt ſence of thoſe words, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33 12. ſpoken of <hi>Manaſſes, When he was in tribulation, he prayed to the Lord his God, and humbled himſelf greatly before the God of his fathers.</hi> I take the meaning to be this, when he was in affliction he beſought God; but how came hee to be his God, to have a title in him, he being ſo vile as he had been, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made a league with the Devill, and deſtroyed all the worſhip of God; he was mindefull of the covenant God had made with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as if he ſhould have ſaid; I am and have been a vile ſinfull wretch, and am not worthy to beg the leaſt mercy from thee; but remember the covenant with my fathers, thou haſt engaged thy ſelf to doe good to them: and ſo <hi>David, I am thy ſervant and the ſon of thy hand-maide;</hi> he had a very good mother, and he pleaded the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of his mother: ſhe had given him many councels, and wept many tears for him; and therefore he pleades the engagement of the covenant of his mother, and by his mother to himſelf; for the patents engage themſelves for themſelves and children, and God engages him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to them and to their children, that he will be a God to them, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſecret things to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Here beware you miſtake not, Parents doe not communicate grace to their children, for that is an errour to ſay ſo; for they are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath as well as others, and they are void of grace; for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration does not convey grace; but by vertue of the covenant, God hath engaged himſelf to doe good unto them, when they are propagated by vertue of the covenant, God does covenant to doe good to all their children, reſerving ſecret things to himſelf; whereas it may be ſaid if children have grace, how can ſin be propagated to them, no, but when children are propagated, by vertue of a covenant, God does uſe the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents as he ſees fit, as a means of good to their children; and this is of ſpeciall conſequence, to think that God will uſe the parents as a means to doe good to the children; it is an extraordinary benefit to believing parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God engages himſelf to uſe the Covenant as a means to doe good to them, as he ſees fit; for all Gods ordinances are the propriety of the Church, God leaves them to them, God covenants to leave his word to them, and thoſe that come of them; this is the meaning of all thoſe places: <hi>I will take away the heart of ſtone, and give a heart of fleſh.</hi> When Parents engage themſelves to him, then he engages himſelf to them and theirs: <hi>And I will circumciſe their hearts, and the hearts of their ſeed, and I will power clean water upon them;</hi> When believing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111041:22"/>parents wait upon God for their children, he will give a bleſſing as he ſees fit, leaving ſecret things to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God accounts them as having federall holineſſe, ſuch as may fit them for a people in that relation, here is the ſtick of all; and therefore I will tell you what federall holines is, it is a relative holines, it is not any inherent grace, or true ſaving grace, but it is relative, and it is not inherent; it ſtands in reference of the covenanter with God, and alſo the engagement of God to entertain ſuch as are rightly diſpoſed and fitted for a covenant-holineſle; it is the ſetting a thing a part for ſpeciall uſe to God; as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is called the holy City, there was not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent grace in the ſtones of it; but <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſet a part for holy uſes, ſo the Land was ſaid to be holy, that is, relative holineſſe; therefore mark here, the ſoul that engaged it ſelf, he ſet himſelf for God to attend upon him, and all his poſterity to do ſo; God allows this and appoints this, God ſet himſelf a part, that he will be for this people, &amp; the God of this people; thus we ſhal find in the Old Teſt. <hi>Thou art a holy people,</hi> not inherently holy, but conſecrated to God, and he will look to them; that is the meaning of the place, and no other meaning, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.15. when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw <hi>Peter</hi> that he went not right, but did in a ſort diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaw the <hi>Jews</hi> had a mean eſteem of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> he withdrew himſelf: and <hi>Paul</hi> he tels them they were both in covenant, &amp; he by halting might diſcourage the Gentiles, therefore reproved him and ſaid, <hi>If thou being a Jew, doſt live after the manner of the Gentiles, and not like the Jews, why conſtraineſt thou the Gentiles to dee like the Jews?</hi> We who are Jews by nature, and not ſinners, of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; that is, not onely ſinners; for the Jews were holy in point of the Covenant, and the Jews were they which God had engaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto: but the Gentiles were not holy, for God had not engaged himſelf to them, ſo as they had not this relative holineſſe, but the Jews had it; ſo they were not ſinners after the Gentiles; but the Jews had this federall holines. Now for the further clearing of the thing, wee will conſider of that place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. <hi>For the unbeleeving husband is ſanctified to the believing wife, and the unbelieving wife is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the believing husband;</hi> elſe your children were unholy, but now they are holy, that is, federally holy. For the meaning of the place, that we may ſinde out the minde of God, we muſt conſider three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. We will ſhew you what this federall holineſſe is.</item>
               <item>2. The meaning of the words, and the ſcope of the Apoſtle.</item>
               <item>3. Wee will ſhew you the gloſſe of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> on the text,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111041:23"/>and remove all their falſe conceiving that they have to cloud the truth; elſe were your children unholy, but now they are holy.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, Federall holineſſe is a ſpirituall priviledge, but not a ſaving grace, nor a ſpirituall work of ſanctification; the holines here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of is federall, or relative holineſſe, but no ſaving work upon the ſoule; this we will cleare from all cavils.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Saving grace is proper to thoſe that ſhall be ſaved, if the work of ſanctification be there, then there will be glorification following; if we be made holy here by ſanctification, we have an intereſt in glory; Hence <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. Paul <hi>was ſent to turn men from darknes to light, and from Satan to God;</hi> and elſwhere we are ſaid <hi>to have an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with thoſe that are ſanctified;</hi> they are the heirs of that glorious inheritance prepared for thoſe that ſhall have it, and they ſhall attain the end of their hopes, the ſalvation of their ſoules; ſaving grace is the propriety of thoſe that ſhall be ſaved: but there be many perſons that enjoy federall holineſſe, that ſhall not have glory, <hi>Deutr.</hi> 7 6. <hi>For thou art a holy people unto the Lord thy God, the Lord thy God hath choſen thee to be a precious people unto himſelf, above all people that are upon the Earth;</hi> and this is ſpoken of the body of the Jews, they had this federall holineſſe, the ſpirituall priviledges; ſo as none other people had, and yet ſhall any think they were all ſaved; nay, the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. <hi>They did all cate the ſame ſpirituall meat, and did all drink the ſame ſpirituall drink, &amp;c.</hi> And yet with many of them God was not pleaſed, <hi>for they were overthrown in the wilderneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> they did not enter, <hi>through unbeliefe thouſands of them periſhed;</hi> and yet they had all the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> did not exceed them in the kinde of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saving grace is never unfallably communicated to all the poſterity of believing parents: <hi>Adam</hi> had a <hi>Cain</hi> as well as a <hi>Shem,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> had an <hi>Eſau</hi> as well as a <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> had an <hi>Iſhmael</hi> as well as an <hi>Iſaac;</hi> and therefore we ſee it is not ſo alway to believing pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, that all their children ſhould be ſaved; and therefore 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>Now they are holy,</hi> that is, federally holy; and Rom. 9, 3, 4. <hi>I could wiſh that my ſelf were ſeparated, &amp;c. for my kinſmen, for my brethren, according to the fleſh; to whom pertaineth the adoption, &amp;c.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was deeply affected for all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> their, adoption which was the higheſt of their armes, it belonging to <hi>Abraham;</hi> and they were all <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> becauſe <hi>Jacob</hi> did wreſtle with God, and prevailed; ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111041:23"/>they are called children <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. <hi>I have nouriſhed and brought up chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> all were adopted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Saving grace can never be loſt; where the worke of ſanctification is, that cannot be loſt, but federall grace may be loſt; <hi>Hoſea</hi> 1.6. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was not his Wife,</hi> therefore God gave her a bill of divorce; they were his people by federall holines, but they loſt that, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Which in times paſt were not a people, but now are the people of God, &amp;c.</hi> the time will come, the Jews ſhall be known to be the people of God; they ſhall be called, <hi>you are my people:</hi> they were the people of God by federall grace, but they loſt it and themſelves and all: but the ſpirituall and ſaving grace cannot be loſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.28. <hi>No man can pull them out of my hand;</hi> if a man once be called to Chriſt, no man can pluck him out of his hands, untill he come to everlaſting happineſſe. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Wee are perſwaded better things of you, and ſuch as accompany ſalvation:</hi> Where the work of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is, there is better things then the beſt hypocrite can attain unto, <hi>And bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God;</hi> and they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſin, becauſe they are born of God: this will diſcover Mr. <hi>Spils<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery</hi> in the 21 page, the three laſt lines, and the 22 page, and the ſix firſt lines, He explicates that that holines that intitles a man to God is twofold; either the holineſſe of Chriſt, that is imputed to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, for whoſe ſake God does account them holy; or elſe, it is a holy frame of heart in regeneration; there is no other way ſaith he. It is a wide miſtake, for there is a threefold holineſſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Imputative in Chriſt to his ſervants.</item>
               <item>2. Inherent in his ſervants.</item>
               <item>3. There is a relative holineſſe, which is that, I have diſputed off; therefore his expoſition is ſhort, and his reaſon is ſhort and worſe, the 22. page and the 4. line. What ever does truly inright a man to God, inrights him to holineſſe; all muſt be ſaved, or fall away. I wonder ſuch things ſhould fall from a mans pen, but that God hath ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hand in it: For had not <hi>Iſrael</hi> right to the Ordinances, and had not <hi>Judas</hi> right to the Paſſeover, and <hi>Symon Magus</hi> to Baptiſm, and had not all the Nation of the <hi>Jews;</hi> the Apoſtle tels us, they were all Baptiſed in the Cloud, and in the Sea; did they not partake of ſuch priviledgesfor the kinde, as the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> had not better; the Apoſtle bids them take heed, for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had the ſame privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges for kinde as they had, and were made partakers of them, and yet they had no right to heaven, but many of them were ſhut out, I ſay therefore; have not all the <hi>Jews</hi> right to the priviledges: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111041:24"/>Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> they were baptized; and as they had it in all Churches, ſo they had right to Baptiſme, and all the holy things that were in any Church, and the Church was bound to give them to them. Now whether all theſe had not right, common ſenſe will tell us, and yet among theſe, there might be many that had not true ſaving grace. We may ask a queſtion concerning that in <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.6. when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and all <hi>Judea</hi> ſent to <hi>John</hi> to be baptized, there came the Scribes, and Phariſecs, and Publicans, and Souldiers: and <hi>Luke</hi> 3. it is ſaid, <hi>they were baptized, conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſing their ſinnes.</hi> Whether M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Spilsbery</hi> think all theſe had right to glory, if he be put to it, I am perſwaded his heart would faile him to ſay they had, and yet they were baptized of him that was the fore-runner of Chriſt, and the Diſciple of Chriſt, and was ſent of Chriſt. In a word, there is a federall holineſſe men may have, that ſhall never have glory: But thoſe that have an inward right, thoſe have right to glory. Nay, a man cannot have an inward right, but he hath right to glory. And here you may learn to ſee, thoſe reaſons carry not common ſenſe with them. Carry this along with you, I will learn you to make uſe of this (that federall holineſſe is not ſaving grace) offenſive and defenſive.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 If this be ſaving grace, a man may fall away from this, but ſaving and covenanting grace cannot be loſt, <hi>He that beleeves ſhall be ſaved.</hi> It doth not ſuppoſe that he that hath this federall grace, hath right al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the blood of Chriſt infallibly. Hence it followes, a man is not bound to beleeve, that every man that hath it ſhall be ſaved. This will anſwer a fourfold cavill of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery,</hi> in page 27. line 17. Hence followes a foure-fold abſurdity, to ſay Infants have right to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 If Infants have an intereſt to grace, then men may fall from grace.</item>
               <item>2 Then the covenant of grace may be to vile perſons, and a man may have the outward covenant, and not be ingrafred into Chriſt.</item>
               <item>3 This will bring in univerſall redemption, no federall grace does make a man redeemed, it daſhes this.</item>
               <item>4 It makes us believe an untruth, for <hi>Iſhmael</hi> he did periſh: but he may have federall grace, and this is the holineſſe meant here.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now to the ſecond thing, what is the explication of the words, there are three things to be conſidered in the place.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks.</item>
               <item>2 Of what he ſpeaks.</item>
               <item>3 What is the fitteſt ſenſe of the Argument. And when we have this,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111041:24"/>
we ſhall ſee the plain meaning.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Of whom the Apoſtle ſpeakes: If you look into the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>verſe,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>To the reſt ſpeak I, and not the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> What are theſe <hi>Reſt,</hi> you will find in the tenth verſe; you may obſerve two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To them that are married, <hi>Let not the wife be put away, except it be for adultery.</hi> And thoſe the Lord ſpeakes to, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. as if the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had ſaid, that caſe hath already been opened and ſpoken unto by the Lord Chriſt in that place. If a man take a diſtaſt againſt his wife, he may not give her a bill of divorce, nor put her away for that, although formerly they might doe it, but it is unlawfull now. Chriſt had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken plainly to that, therefore I will not ſpeak to it. But <hi>to the reſt,</hi> that is, thoſe that were married Infidels, he takes that for granted, that they were not converted before they were married, but they were both Infidels, and the one is converted, and the other left; to theſe I ſpeak, in the 13, 14, 15. verſes; concerning theſe, Chriſt hath not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, he hath not expreſſed himſelf in this caſe; but I ſpeake to that, I have the Spirit of God, theſe are the parties, both unbelievers, and one of them is converted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of what hee ſpeakes: the ſtate of the queſtion, the one is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, the other is not, the unbelieving party hinders the work of the believing party: the queſtion is, whether they ſhould continue that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce between them, there being ſo much oppoſition; whether they may doe it without prejudice to the conſcience of the believing party in that ordinance of God, or may they have the pure uſe of marriage? His anſwer is, It is a matter of duty, if ſhe will yet remain, it is a duty enjoyned of God. Mark the Apoſtles queſtion, not whether they may marry an unbeliever, that is not here ſpoken of; but it is taken for granted they were both unbelievers, and now one is converted, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he or ſhe may continue, the anſwer is, Yes, he may &amp; muſt. Thus you ſee, of what he ſpeaks, not of making marriages, but of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: This he proves, &amp; he reaſons fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the effect; If the unbelieving party be ſanctified by the believing party in that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> belongs to the uſe of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage then they may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue: but ſo they are, and that is no prejudice to that ordinance of marriage: If a believer may have a ſanctified uſe of an unbeliever, then they may abide: but ſo they may, &amp; the unbele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſanctified to that uſe by the believer, the meaning is, that the unbeliefe of the party cannot ſo out-bid the faith of the believer, as to pollute the conſcience or faith of the party: but that faith the believer hath, through Chriſt he ſhall have a ſanctified uſe of to his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and the ſpirituall uſe of marriage; for that was to beget a holy
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111041:25"/>ſeed to God, and it is made holy in the believer, not in himſelfe: But the unbelieving husband, he hath not a ſanctified uſe of marriage, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his own conſcience, nor in his faith; but in the believing wife, in vertue of that power cloſing with Chriſt, they have a ſanctified uſe of marriage, and in marriage, and may attain the right end of marriage. The Apoſtle proves it by the effect; where holineſſe is in the effect, there it is in the cauſe, the wife hath the child that comes of her, fede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally holy, therefore they have right to the priviledges of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant; if the one party be faithfull, their children are federally ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo they may have a ſanctified uſe of Gods ordinance: but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if both be unbelievers, they have no right, but are as Pagans, and have no right to the priviledges of Gods covenant.</p>
            <p>Now we will come to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery's</hi> interpretation in foure things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The holineſſe here is meant the holineſſe of the fleſh, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe is meant the uncleanneſſe of the fleſh, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3. they had married ſtrange wives, and by Gods appointment they were to put them away, they acknowledge, <hi>we have tranſgreſſed,</hi> and therefore they make a covenant to put them away, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 6.18. <hi>He that commits fornication, ſinneth againſt his own body, &amp;c.</hi> And 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 2, 3. <hi>For this is the will of God, even your ſanctification, that every one of you know how to poſſeſſe his veſſell in ſanctification and honour.</hi> In the 22. <hi>pape</hi> and the 23. line.</item>
               <item>2 The holineſſe of the Parents, and of the children, are of the ſame kinde, and muſt be attended in the ſame way, and not in a divers manner, in 23. <hi>page,</hi> and 26. <hi>line.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 The holineſſe of the fleſh is this, when they match according to Gods allowance; the uncleanneſſe is, when they meet together in an unclean manner, and croſſe to God: and lawfulneſſe in their marriage is holineſſe, when parties come together in a lawfull manner, thoſe have holineſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Again, when children are born in a lawfull way of marriage, they are clean when they are lawfully begotten: but if they be unlawfully begotten, then they are unclean, ſo Baſtards are unclean: when they meet in a way of God, then they are holy, but if in adultery, then they are unholy. The meaning of the Text is (ſaith he) elſe they were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards; but now they are right born.</p>
            <p>The fourth <hi>Ground</hi> is (ſaith he) you judge your children holy, and therefore you may dwell one with another, your marriage is good: this is the laſt.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:111041:25"/>
            <p>The ground he makes to be this; the Chriſtians wrote to the Apoſtles becauſe of that in the 10. of <hi>Ezra,</hi> that was the occaſion of the ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and upon this ground they wrote it: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1, among many other, this was one oceaſion, and this is the ſubſtance of his interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; againſt this I will give you ſeverall reaſons, and ſo quit the place: I will doe it in three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The ſtate of the queſtion does no way ſuit the intendment of the Apoſtle in regard of the Parties, for they make the queſtion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelves, and ſo the parties carry no reaſon with them in <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> for they in <hi>Ezra</hi> were matched to them of a contrary Religion, in the entrance of their marriage, Jews and Heathen, they ſuite not therefore with the Apoſtles aime; hee wrote to them in <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rinth,</hi> and they were all Pagans as appears, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Yee know that you were Gentiles carryed away unto theſe dumb Idols as you were led,</hi> ſo that all of them were Heathens, therefore the parties differ; and the ſtate of the queſtion is not whether they may marry one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that was out of queſtion; for marriage is honourable among all men, the bed undefiled, God did not forbid them marriage: but now, one of them being converted after they were married; now they que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether if either be converted, whether they ſhould abide with a pure conſcience one with another, that is not converted; now here is a ſanctified perſon, and that party may have a ſanctified uſe of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to a holy end; and therefore may abide with a pure conſcience: this caſt the cauſe fully.</item>
               <item>2. This croſſes the grain of the text, it will not admit of it. I ſhew it thus; that a civill way of marriage is not meant here, for that holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is meant here of which the believer is the cauſe to derive to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, of them the words of the text is meant, and it will admit no other; mark, the unbelieving party is ſanctified to and in the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving party, it comes by the believing part; for to the pure all things are pure, he or ſhe hath a ſanctified uſe in their conſcience, and the ordinance: the Apoſtle doth not ſay, the believer is ſanctified by the unbeliever; that is croſſe to the texts, but the unbeliever is ſanctified by the believer, and ſo it is communicated to poſterity: Now they are clean; how? by the believer; to the children they are made holy; but mark, if you take it of the fleſh, that is, of all ſuch as are lawfully married: marriage is as lawfull to Infidels as to believers, but that is not ſo meant. Again, the children of Infidels that are not baſe born, come from both parents, and both communicate to the Childe; but mark the holineſſe here meant, is, from the believer alone; but this lawfulneſſe of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111041:26"/>marriage belongs to Infidels; and therefore that cannot be meant here; but this is to believers, but that of marriage is not ſo, and therefore it is federall holineſſe which is proper to beleevers.</item>
               <item>3. This interpretation takes off the Argument, and makes this Reaſon no Reaſon; for it ſtands thus, If your children be not Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, you may ſtay together. Mark, it takes of the edge of it; for the Apoſtles reaſon doth not take away the doubt of the queſtion: For if he ſay thus, if you marry lawfuly, your children are not Baſtards, your doubt doth ſtill remaine; for that might be as doubtfull as the former: for this doth not prove their intereſt in their marriage, nor the lawfulneſſe of it, and therefore it cannot prove it. If a queſtion be, whether ſuch a man be lawfully married or not, if I ſhould come &amp; tell him, if you be lawfully married, your children are no baſtards: this doth not prove it: for it iſſues from hence, if ye queſtion the one, the other may be more: that he alledges to eaſe this, he ſayes he ſpeakes to your apprehenſion, you judge your children are no Baſtards this croſſes the words of the Text: for he doth not ſay, elſe you may judge them unholy; but he ſaith, they are holy, whether they thinke ſo or not, ſo as it perverts the Text. Again, it croſles the reaſonable appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a man that knowes what he ſpeakes; if I know the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are no baſtards, I ſhould not queſtion whether the man and wife be lawfully married, for it hath reference to one lawfully married: if he ſay, he is not lawfully married, then they are not lawfully born: it croſſes Reaſon to be unlawfully born, when lawfully married; ſo they take off the gloſſe of the place.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſecond place of Scripture they build upon, is <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. <hi>If the firſt fruits be holy, ſo is the whole lump; and if the root be holy, ſo are the branches.</hi> It is ſpoken of the Jewes; for the opening of the Text, I will doe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Open the meaning of the Text.</item>
               <item>2 Propound the reaſons.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 What is meant here by holineſſe.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer is, Federall holineſſe, not the holineſſe of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but confederation; that holineſſe which is part of ſanctification, is that which is ſpoken of, <hi>Epeheſ.</hi> 4.24. <hi>And put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe:</hi> But ſo it is not here uſed, but for <hi>arelative holineſſe,</hi> whereby they were knit' to God, and he to them; they avouch him to be their God, and he avouches them to be his people. One place he complaines, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.2. <hi>They have mixed the holy ſeed with the people of the Lands, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:111041:26"/>The holy ſeed is the Jews, they mingled with the common people, that is, ſuch as were not free Burgeſſes in the Church, that is, they were mingled among the heathen; all the people of the land were not ſanctiſted, but they were holy in this way: that it is federall holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, appeares; ſanctification is never conveyed by the Father to the Child, this is from the Spirit of God, , he workes as he ſees fit, therefore two in one bed, one taken and another left; ſo two in one belly, one taken, and another left: but this is by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>If the root be holy, ſo are the branches; if the firſt fruits be holy, ſo is the whole lump:</hi> the root and firſt fruits; and from him is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance, <hi>Abraham</hi> did covenant for his, as well as for himſelf, wee may ſcoin the 17 verſe, ſanctification cannot be loſt, but the branches are broken off that came of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and proved a vagabond people, they may be cut off, but ſanctification cannot be loſt; they loſt their confederate holines, but they that are ſanctified ſhall be glorified.</p>
            <p>Hence we may ſee the growing of theſe branches is not the growing of ſaving faith, but federall holines; it is not the growing to Chriſt by faith, for then they ſhould never be broken off from faith: to ſay ſo, is a falſhood; for if a man be called he ſhall be glorified, we are made one ſpirit. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32. <hi>This is a great myſtery, but I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and his Church,</hi> if Chriſt ſhould loſe one, he ſhould be unperfect. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.23. <hi>The fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all things.</hi> Chriſt is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, but if he want one member, he ſhould not be compleat. This is cleare, ſaving grace cannot be loſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That holines agrees with the body of the Gentiles, they are brought into a viſible covenant, as in the 17 verſe, they are brought into a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, that is the root and the fatnes is the priviledges: the body of the Gentiles had not ſanctification.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what is meant by <hi>firſt Fruits,</hi> and <hi>Lump,</hi> one is from the Ceremoniall Law among the Jewes, <hi>Lovit.</hi> 23.14.17. <hi>You ſhall eat neither bread nor parched Corn, nor green eares, untill the ſelfe ſame day you have brought an offering to the Lord your God. This ſhall be a law for ever in all your dwellings.</hi> And in the 17. verſe, <hi>you ſhall bring out of your dwellings for a ſhake offering, two loaves of two tenth deals of fine flower, &amp;c.</hi> When they had received in their Corne, it was unlawfull to ſpend it, till they had firſt offered the two loaves for a ſhake offering, and then all the whole lump was ſanctified for their uſe, according to the allowance of God. So by way of reſemblane <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> is the firſt fruits, he being in covenant with God, all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are in the covenant, God accepts of both him and his poſterity,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111041:27"/>the Father being in covenant with God, they become a holy people: <hi>You, your wives and little ones;</hi> ſo their federall holines is to all that come of <hi>Abraham</hi> as his ſeed; and this is the meaning.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>If the Root be holy, ſo are the Branches;</hi> What is meant by <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Branches?</hi> We ſhall find out the root: by the true Olive here is the Church of the Jewes, the Root was <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe the firſt covenant was made with him, all came from him; it was made to him, and from him it came to his poſterity, they are the naturall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the poſterity born of him; ſo he is as the head of the covenant to them. <hi>Abraham</hi> being holy to God, he brings forth a holy ſeed and Nation, having federall holineſſe: <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſterity by birth, are all a holy ſeed, but the Gentiles are ingrafted by profeſſion and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, the priviledges and the fatneſſe comes to them by being ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the place is ſpirituall, I will deſcribe the wilde Olive and the Branches, and then you may know the true Olive, it will help you to underſtand it the better.</p>
            <p>The Gentiles, the body of them are wild, not by originall ſinne, for ſo the Jewes were as bad as they, and had as much of that as they: Whence is their wildneſſe then, becauſe God left them in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall corruption without the help of thoſe meanes that might help them, and therefore they grew wild as a tree in the wilderneſſe growes wild, ſo they were left without any intereſt in any means of help, and ſo they grew wild; for God had not ingaged himſelfe to them, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>In the times of ignorance God regarded not, but now he admoniſheth all men every where to repent:</hi> that is, now all the nations of the earth ran riot, it is the ſame with that in <hi>Acts</hi> 6.1. <hi>the Widowes were neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> that is, God left them as Trees in the Wilderneſſe, God did not care for the Gentiles, in giving them meanes for their good, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now they grow wild. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.16. <hi>who in times paſt ſuffered all the Gentiles to walk in their own wayes:</hi> Iſrael had lawes to walk by, but it was not ſo with other Nations, and therefore they were wild, and ſtrangers from the common-wealth of Iſrael. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. they had not an intereſt in the covenant of the Jewes, but were wild ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and not under the dreſſing of God for their good; and ſo were all thoſe that came of them, Pagans of Pagans, ſuch Children of ſuch Parents, under the curſe of God, in ſinne; and not looked after, having no meanes, the Fathers ignorant, and ſo were the Children. And this is the meaning of that <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.24. <hi>For if thou were cut out of the Olive Tree, which was wild by nature, and were graſred contrary to nature into the right Olive Tree, &amp;c.</hi> What nature is meant? corrupt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111041:27"/>nature? No, for the Jewes were corrupt as well as they: the Jewes were as deep in originall ſinne as they; not onely contrary to corrupt nature, but they were wild by nature, that is, they were under ſuch a diſpenſation, that God was not ingaged to them, and ſo the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of them were under the like condition, they were in ſuch a courſe, as they had not the meanes to mend them, nay they had no ingagement of God, but they were under the curſe of God, without meanes; but now the true Olive, that grew not wild; not that they had not as many ſinnes by nature; and as they, ſo their children, the ſame ſinne in their nature: but they had an intereſt in the meanes to help them, and God had ingaged himſelfe to them in Church-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, <hi>I will cauſe them to walk in my wayes,</hi> that is, the Church ſhould not grow wild, becauſe they had meanes, and God had inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelfe to them. Hence they were free Burgeſſes, and hence comes it, that the poſterity of the Jewes are called the <hi>Naturall Branches;</hi> ſo as the child of a Jew, though ſinfull, and have no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe by birth, yet he was within the compaſſe of the Church, and ſo God was ingaged to doe him good, as he ſees fit by nature and gonera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe he came of <hi>Abraham,</hi> he falls under God, and God takes him in his naturall condition, and ſo he comes under the means to be brought home to God.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the Gentiles are wild, becauſe they were not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods tilling, nor was he ingaged to doe them good, and ſo he ran wild.</p>
            <p>Now to the true Olive in way of oppoſition they were the Jewes; not by way of ſinne, but becauſe they were under the hand of God, and ſo they had an intereſt in the meanes of grace. Now the Jewes, though they were wicked, yet they were not wild, but they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods hand ordering them: and hence they were preſerved under his hand. This is the meaning of the Prophets, you may referre them to this, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>The Lord had a Vineyard, and he planted it, and fenced it, and made a wine-preſſe in it.</hi> And in the ſeventh verſe, <hi>And what could I have done more for my Vineyard?</hi> Here you may ſee what care and skill God did uſe towards them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſecures his Vineyard, and therefore he hedges it, and makes a wall about it, and uſes all the wayes of preſervation he can.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By way of prevention and therefore he removes thoſe things that might anoy it by gathering out the ſtones and bryers out of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He laies in proviſion, he plants it with choice plants, and built a Wine-preſſe in it, and what could he have done more in outward
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111041:28"/>means. Now he did not thus to the Gentiles, they grew wilde, he did not take that pains with them; ſo <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 2.21. <hi>Yea, I planted thee a noble Vine, whoſe plants were all naturall, &amp;c.</hi> That is, as a Vine planted on purpoſe by the gardiner, it was not a wilde one, in regard of God, and his promiſes, as he had made them a Church, ſo all ſhould before their good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.24. <hi>They were ingrafted into the true O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,</hi> and originally planted by the dreſſer; that as the wilde Olive grows in the wilderneſſe, ſo the good Olives are planted by the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſer: therefore you may ſee what he ſpeaks further of the Vine, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 5 7. <hi>Surely the Vineyard of the Lord of hoſts is the men of Iſrael and the men of Iudah are his pleaſant plants;</hi> or as the word ſignifies, the people of Gods imbracements; that is to apply a mans ſelf plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly to another with loving imbracements; that is the word; the Lord out of his good pleaſure and tender pitty did take the people of the Jews into his imbracements, he took them into the Arms of his imbracements of the covenants, and into the arms of his compaſſion, ſo he doth to every Congregation to this day; in this regard they are planted into the true Olive; <hi>Deut</hi> 7.7. <hi>The Lord did not chooſe you, becauſe you were more in number, but becauſe he loved you,</hi> and <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> 24.23, 24.29. <hi>I will raiſe up for them a plant of renown, &amp;c.</hi> See what affection he carried to them, then what they are called, <hi>thus ſhall they know that I am with them:</hi> he will make them glorious: the ſum is, when God is pleaſed out of his love to take a people to himſelf, and ingage himſelf to them for their good, that people is a true Olive, and ſo of a perſon, or children of ſuch parents under them are ſaid to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall branches: ſo we may ſee their excellency above others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How holineſſe is derived from the root to the branches, the words themſelves carry it privily, if the one then other; for the root hath a cauſe and means to carry holineſſe to the branches: now the grace of ſanctification is not conveyed; what ſap is in the root, the ſame is in the branches: the things whence the compariſon is taken, is from the firſt fruits in the time of the Law, <hi>Levit,</hi> 23.17. It was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for them to take the fruits of the ground untill they had firſt brought the two loaves to offer them a Wave-Offering unto the Lord; but when they had done that then the whole lump was ſanctified, he had a ſanctified uſe of it, and it did ſignifie peace and purity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; that was the means by Gods Inſtitution: the root in nature is the cauſe of the ſap that is conveyed to the branches, the ſcope is one; ſo that in that is ſignified, <hi>Abraham</hi> was the root and firſt fruits; if he were good and walked in fear and love, and ſo became holy to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111041:28"/>Lord, ſo were his poſterity by a covenant made with <hi>Abraham:</hi> here let me vary with you, <hi>Abraham</hi> is taken into covenant with God, and ſo to be conſecrated to God, and therefore federally holy, his children are in covenant as well as he; ſo they in the ſame ſet apart, they partake of the ſame; thus the holineſſe does not iſſue from hence, as they are born the ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> nor that they were born Jews no further then a bate Jew or the Propagation of a Jew, if God had not taken them into covenant, and engaged himſelf unto them no more then the Gentiles: he engaged himſelf to them, and they to him, or elſe they had not been holy: Hence it is becauſe they renounce the promiſes of God, they loſt their federall holines. Now mark, hence is the ground of this holines, it is federall; God took him into covenant and his children, and that of free-favour; therefore he may chooſe and leave. Hence they become holy the lump of them, becauſe of their father being in the covenant, and he choſe him, becauſe he loved him, their parents did covenant; <hi>Abraham</hi> entred into covenant, and that he did becauſe he choſe them, and he choſe them becauſe he loved them, and he loved them becauſe he would love them, and therefore he did. choſe them; and becauſe he choſe them therefore he did enter into covenant with them, their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were holy becauſe he choſe them, and entred into a covenant with them and with their children by their fathers covenants: now you ſee how it is communicated, being bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of parents that are in covenant with God, and God with them, this is the pedigree of the text; now you may ſee what is ſaid to the contrary by Mr. <hi>Spil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, He ſayes by firſt fruits and lumps, the elect are to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in believing it ſet forth ſuch as are in Chriſt, according to which you may ſee 17. page, 9 lines from the end, in Chriſt they are proved ſubjects of the kingdom of Heaven; what is meant by root, Chriſt, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Chriſt conveys living grace to his living members of his body and the branches are thoſe that are planted in Chriſt by faith and the ſpirit; for faith he, myſticall Chriſt is the Church, for the Church are not a mixt company in the 20, 23, 24. lines, I will anſwer in two things to clear the place:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. It is unfound, and does not ſuite the Apoſtles meaning.</item>
               <item>2. If we grant it, it will not help. his cauſe to hinder from the baptiſing of Infants.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It is unfound were Gods elect of a viſible covenant; if that onely were the firſt fruits, then <hi>Abraham</hi> could not; <hi>Adam, Abell, Noah;</hi> and <hi>Shem</hi> were the elect of God, and theſe were before <hi>Abraham;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this will not hold out that he faith, but as the covenant of grace
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111041:29"/>was ſet upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo he is the firſt fruits.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It hath been proved out of the text as holineſſe to the lump, ſo God intends it as a means; not that elect people are able to convey ſaving grace to the lump of all the Jewes in any caſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the elect were onely the members, he contradicts his own courſe; for thoſe that have a right to baptiſm are inveſted into all the priviledges; but Gods elect people are not the onely ſubjects of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: for when <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> did baptiſe all thoſe that came to him, in the judgement of <hi>Iohn</hi> they were approved ſubjects of Gods grace: Yet I ſuppoſe no man will ſay (though they were men of ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res that were baptiſed) that they were all the elect of God, and that they were approved ſubjects, and yet they did not onely apply the ſeale to themſelves for their good, but they did abuſe the ſeals, and yet they were approved of <hi>Iohn</hi> to be made partakers of it; although ſome of them were Apoſtates and Reprobates; in a word, thoſe that are in the covenant of Gods grace that are elected, are really partakers of the work of the ſpirit inwardly, but for the outward we ſee they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, which is that of which we now ſpeak, not the elect onely, but others in the federall holineſſe, and <hi>Abraham</hi> was the firſt fruits by way of covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the root here is not Chriſt miſtically conveying grace to his branches, and ſending nouriſhment from the head as it is the viſible covenant; againſt this, I ſay,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Root here meant, is that from whom the Branches ingrafted may be broken off, that is, the Jewes; they were broken off from the Church, and are at this day; but no Branch that is ingraſted into Chriſt by faith, can be broken off: Firſt, we may ſee it in the Text: Secondly, we may ſee it in Reaſon, he that is in Chriſt cannot be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off. For, <hi>whom he called, he juſtified; and whom he juſtified, he will glorifie. And thoſe that come to Chriſt, he will not caſt them away; for it is the will of the Father to give them eternall life, and no man can take them out of his hand; ſo as the caſe is cleare.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The Root is meant the body ingrafted, as in the 15. verſe. <hi>If the caſting away of the Iews ſhall be reſtored the body of the Gentiles</hi> 24. 25. <hi>verſes, all the body ſhall be ſaved,</hi> but the body of the Gentiles are not ingrafted into Chriſt myſtically to be belivers, ſo the root is not here, and this ſhews the unfoundnes.</item>
                  <item>3. The reaſon Mr. <hi>Spilsbery</hi> uſes, is againſt his cauſe in his 17. page and the laſt and the beginning of the 18. they carry not the weight of a feather, that Chriſt is the Olive and the Jews are caſt out, and the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111041:29"/>Gentiles are grafted in, I deſire no better reaſon againſt him, for the Jews are not caſt out of Chriſt myſticall out of this root, becauſe it is the Church of Chriſt where many hypocrites are, becauſe they may be caſt out.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In that the Apoſtle charges the Gentiles for boaſting, the root bears thee, and yet thou have no ſaving grace, but a naked profeſſion and expreſſion in the 17. verſe: it is a falſe miſtake out of that place, boaſting is not ſaving grace, for it is a pang of pride; God hath no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple but have their weaknes of grace: <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren they ſold him, and would ſee what would become of his dreams, and the <hi>Corinthians</hi> they did boaſt, one was of <hi>Paul</hi> another of <hi>Apollo,</hi> but did all theſe want ſaving grace? No, but it is as a caveat given them to pull it down; it is not to ſay, they all want ſaving grace, it is falſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that the Apoſtle charges the Gentiles for boaſting, it is againſt the argument.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thus, if the Gentiles be ingrafted in want of grace, therefore Chriſt muſt be the head, the conſequence deſtroyes the concluſion; the root is meant, as he faith, the ingrafted, and the want of grace the body; butſo is no member that is in Chriſt myſtically; therfore the root is not meant Chriſt, for the want of grace cannot be in Chriſt myſtically, ſo he deſtroyes his cauſe; now we ſhew you the meaning of the text, the ſcope is; they ſhould not liſt up themſelves, for the Jews were cut off: he reaſons thus. It is groundleſſe to boaſt againſt the Jew, becauſe they receive all from the Jew; therefore they ſhould ſit down, for if they have any right, they have it from him, for <hi>Abraham</hi> is the root, how? by covenant with him; <hi>Abraham</hi> bare by a viſible cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; therefore the Gentiles may thank <hi>Abraham</hi> for it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have no cauſe to boaſt, for it was ſaid to him, <hi>in thee ſhall all the Nations of the earth be bleſſed:</hi> ſo the truth is cleared, the children are holy, but not by a ſpirituall holineſſe, but a federall holineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If we grant him his interpretation it will be no help to his cauſe; if the firſt fruits and lump be the elect, the children are elect alſo; if they be veſſels of glory, upon the ſame ground, children are elected as well as they, and let Chriſt be the head of thoſe that be ingrafted, then children and infants are the branches of this head, and ſo to be judged in charity, and if they ſhall be ſaved, they are members, Epheſ. 5.26. Children ſhall be ſaved by Chriſt, they he, his body; he hath gotten nothing here, but we have gained that children have federall holineſſe againſt all oppoſition.</p>
            <p>The 4th Propoſition is, Although the ground be not the ſame, yet
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111041:30"/>there is as ſure a ground to evidence to judicious charity, that children are in covenant as well as parents, if they be believers, the ground is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t good to the one as it is to the other, to a Rule of judicious charity it is alike to both.</p>
            <p>There is not the ſame ground altogether, becauſe the parents are of yeares of diſcretion, and ſo they are able to expreſſe the ſpeciall or common good, and therefore they can give a reaſon of the hope that is in them, and ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge themſelves to walk in the wayes of God, with a conſciencious performance of it, becauſe they are in the compaſſe of the covenant, they are ſo farre able to put forth this. The Soribes and Phariſees they made profeſſion of their faith, and they did expreſſe a readineſſe and willingneſſe ſo to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo they came to <hi>John</hi> to bee baptized; as if they ſhould have ſaid, Command, and we will doe it, and follow it conſcientiouſly. And <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. <hi>Then Simon himſelfe believed alſo, and was baptized, &amp;c.</hi> There was a large diſcovery to ſay, <hi>I believe.</hi> An <hi>Acts</hi> 2.31. <hi>Repent and be baptized, &amp;c.</hi> This is the outward profeſſion of men of yeares, that is required of them, but it is not required of Infants, for thoſe are grounds of rationall charity, thoſe are not among infants, for that were to require impoſſibilities and contradictions; the firſt part is evident, but they are as ſure grounds to children as to parents, we will make it good in 3 things, all follow from the former propoſition.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Becauſe of the covenant on their parts, believing parents enter firſt into the covenant perſonally for themſelves and their children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.11. <hi>You, your wives, and your little ones.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 In regard of Gods acceptance, be accepts of both, and doth avouch them both to be his, and he adopts them both in the ſame bond, at the ſame time they are accepted of God. There is a twofold adoption, the one is internall and ſpirituall, and God diſpenſes this in a various manner in his own wil, as to accept the father ſomtime, and the ſonne ſometime, and ſometime the one and ſometime the other, as he pleaſes; ſo wicked <hi>Ahaz</hi> had good <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kiah,</hi> and good <hi>Joſiah</hi> had a wicked ſonne; ſo it was in the Kings of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and ſo we ſee the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of God, wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> had fooliſh <hi>Rehoboa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> theſe are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: but there is an externall adoption, and that to Fathers and Children; ſo we ſee holineſſe is not by generation, but by covenant with the Father, and therefore to ſay that holineſſe is by generation, it is a dreame. <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. <hi>You onely have I known of all the Nations of the earth, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves leſt you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>get the covenant of the Lord your God which he made with you, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:111041:30"/>And <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. <hi>who are Iſraelites, to whom pertaine the adoption and the glory, and the covenant, &amp;c.</hi> they were all adopted externally, and alſo in covenant; but in the internall there is variety of diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of that, as God pleaſes.</item>
               <item>3 There is like federall holineſſe belongs to the father and the ſon, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 7. All theſe we have made good heretofore, and cleared the coaſt by making them good againſt all oppoſition. Is the father in covenant? ſo is the ſonne. Is the father holy? ſo is the ſonne: it is as ſure to the one as to the other; that is the reaſon God ſpeaking in thoſe places of the Gentiles as to the Jews, he ſpeakes indifferently of both; <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.43. <hi>The Goſpel ſhall be taken from you, and ſhall be given to a Nation that will bring forth the fruits thereof.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. <hi>You put away the word of God, and therefore we turn to the Gentiles.</hi> So as they have the ſame mark, and obſerve when they were ſeparate from the Jew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, then they are ſaid to be <hi>Aliens from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Iſrael, Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. So as the Gentiles were not free Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes; But now the caſe is altered, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. <hi>You are no more ſtrangers and forraignors, but Citizens with the Saints, &amp;c.</hi> Now the Goſpel is come to the Gentiles, now they are no more forraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but free Denizens. There be three phraſes there, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.6. he ſpeaks of the Gentiles, that they were fellow-heires of the ſame body and of the ſame promiſes, they were heires of the ſame Corporation, and they had the benefit of the promiſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. <hi>They were partakers of the Root and fatneſſe of the Olive, &amp;c.</hi> When the Jewes were broken of, the Gentiles were grafted in, and made partakers of the ſame fatneſſe, it was ſent abroad to them as well as to the Jewes.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Hence I will reaſon ſeverally before I paſſe, 1. That they that have as ſure ground, by rationall charity ought to have them: but they are as ſure to children as to parents, therefore they ſhould have them, and we in rationall charity ſhould diſpence them to both.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I reaſon thus; Thoſe that are ingra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted into the ſame covenant with the Jewes, and are partakers of the ſame fatneſſe as large as the Jewes did, they are eſſentially begotten into the ſame Olive: But ſo are the Gentiles; for what the Jewes had, the Gentiles have, if in the ſame Olive God will give the ſame extent to them as to the Jewes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That which appertaines to the covenant as the covenant, that muſt belong to all thoſe that the covenant appertaines unto; as that which belongs to a Corporation as a Corporation, it belongs to all that are of that Corporation, and all have a ſhare in the ſame: But it
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111041:31"/>belongs to the covenant as the covenant, to in title Infants to the ſeale, becauſe they belong to the covenant; therefore they muſt needs have the ſeale. In <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. God will eſtabliſh his covenant with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his ſeed: and in the ninth verſe, <hi>they ſhall keep his covenant,</hi> and therefore he muſt keep the ſeale of the covenant, and this is the ſeale of the covenant, <hi>Every man child among you ſhall be circumciſed,</hi> becauſe I will be thy God, thou ſhalt keep the ſeale of my covenant: he does not mention expreſly what ever ſeal of my covenant thou ſhalt keep, but this is the ſeale, <hi>Thou ſhalt circumciſe every man child;</hi> ſo he appoints one, that he may keep that; and if I appoint another, keep that, what ever ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I appoint. Now I come to the fourth thing to be handled.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether the Church may not lawfully ſometimes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the ſeale of the covenant to ſuch as ſinfully receive the ſame?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church may warrantably diſpenſe the ſeales of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to ſuch as many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es doe receive them ſinfully and unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and doe ſinfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g. There is a double unworthines, one is open, that appeares com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n outwardly, when the wickedneſſe of mens hearts appeare in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> lives, ſuch ſhould be caſt out from the Church, and the Church hath not allowance to retain them, nor to diſpenſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances to them, they are ſcandalous, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5.5. <hi>It is heard certainly there is fornication, and ſuch fornication as is not named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles, &amp;c.</hi> and they had not proceeded againſt them; and therfore the Spirit of God reproves them ſharply, and does charge the Church with ſinne, for not doing it. In <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.18. The Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> is reproved becauſe they ſuffered the woman <hi>Jezebel</hi> to prevaile, ſhee carried the day againſt the Officers, to beare with her ſinfully.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There is an unworthineſſe that appeares not to the eye of men, cloſe hearted hypocrites, which deceive themſelves and others; thoſe that carry it ſo cunningly that no eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n ſee them they are ſo cunning; their ſin is inward, ſo ſecretly conveyed ſo cunningly from the eye of the Brethren, or the Officers of the Church, in this caſe they cannot know it, and therefore they cannot conſure it, nor proceed againſt them; but they are unblameable in the Churches eye. In this caſe the Church hath warrant from God to diſpence them to ſuch; though they doe ſinfully in receiving, yet the Church doth warrantably in giving it unto them, as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>For this cauſe many are ſicke among you, and weak</hi> &amp;c. They may be ſecret, and come &amp; cat and drink their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111041:31"/>own damnation, and the Church in no fault becauſe ſhe proceeds not againſt them, becauſe ſhe knowes them not. But now the difficulty growes, and for this cauſe I ſpeake it: They ſay, this is to abuſe Gods Ordinance, and ſet the ſeale to a blanke in Baptiſme. Here may be comfort in both; but thus they argue; They are not in Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they abuſe the ordinance, and ſet the ſeale to a blank, for Baptiſme is a ſeale, and therefore they abuſe God and them. The argument they may think ſtrong, but it is weak and falſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 It is exceeding weak; for it doth not hurt the cauſe of baptizing of children, it is of no value to hurt the baptizing of children: For if it muſt not be adminiſtred to Infants, becauſe it is the putting of a ſeale to a blank, then it muſt not be adminiſtred to men of yeares; for there are hundreds of thoſe that are men of yeares, that are cloſe and groſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, that never had any communion with Chriſt, and yet they are in the Church, and the Church cannot hold them back. For inſtance, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1.4. in the firſt it is ſaid, <hi>They had a name to live, and are dead;</hi> and in the fourth verſe, <hi>There were but a few names which had not defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their garments,</hi> and yet they were all baptized; for they came in and were all baptized, and yet they were moſt of them nought. Now they ſet a ſeale to a blank the Apoſtles themſelves, there were but a few did walk with Chriſt, they were dead in ſin the moſt of them; the moſt were ſo when the Apoſtles planted the Church; outwardly they appeared to have ſome good in them, but many were naught that the Apoſtles themſelves did baptize: and it muſt be ſo of neceſſity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the Church there are many hypocrites, although they be Saints in the appearance of men, ſo as the Church cannot diſcern them; and in this caſe it is warrantable to give them the Sacrament, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> gives allowance ſo to doe: and therefore if that be to abuſe the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then we muſt ſay <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave us allowance ſo to doe, provided they be cloſe hearted, and keep themſelves ſo: and the like may be ſaid of the Supper of the Lord, there bee thouſands of hypocrites in the church on earth, that the church doth not know; thoſe that appeare holy, prove to be rotten. When we baptize men of yeares, we muſt goe by the judgement of charity, and ſo there is hope in children; it is by charity, and yet it is no abuſe of the Sacrament, it may be ſo, and ſo the argument comes to nothing. So for ſetting of the ſeal to a blank. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was baptized, and yet he was <hi>in the gall of bitterneſſe,</hi> and therefore upon this ground there muſt be no Sacrament given at all to any, and ſo it is weak.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We ſay it is falſe, that it is the abuſe of a Sacrament if we give it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111041:32"/>to them, if they be ſecret, that the Church cannot perceive them, they have warrant to give it them; and therefore they doe not abuſe it: we will make this clear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is falſe, for the Church is bound to give it to ſuch, for the Church muſt judge of the perſons fitnes, or elſe ſhe goes blindefold: the Church in her officers, and the reſt muſt judge, and then ſhe is in her way; they ſhould pray the Lord to purge out the old leaven, that ſhe may be a pure lump, and thoſe that be unworthy, the congregation muſt remove them, but they muſt firſt judge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The judgement of the Church muſt paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> according to thoſe things that come into view, according to experience and practice; as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>by their fruits you ſhall know them;</hi> it is the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of God to try the heart of man, but man is to ſee the working, as it appears outwardly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.16. <hi>By their fruits you ſhall know them;</hi> the ſap is ſeen in the fruit of the tree, of things ſeen we judge, but ſecret things belong to God. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 29.29.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe that are ſecret, that are received by the judgement of the Church, directed by a rule of diſcerning, the Church hath free and full warant from God, if ſhe go as far as ſhe can, ſhe hath full warrant from God to diſpence the ordinances to them; ſuppoſe hypocrites be there, and ſuch as be counterfeit, yet if ſhe go as far as a rule will allow her, ſhe is not bound to know the heart, but by the expreſſions in life and converſation, if there be nothing againſt them, ſhe hath full war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: men may abuſe the ordinance; but ſhe doth not abuſe it, for it is her duty, Chriſt ſaith, he had choſen twelve, and one is a Devill, he knew it as God, that he was a Devill, and ſhould betray him; he was acted by Satan, and he know it as God; yet <hi>John</hi> 13, 14.18. he cates the Paſſover with <hi>Judas,</hi> and it is thought he did cat the Supper; but if he did not, he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls what the Church may doe; nay, what ſhe muſt doe in that behalf, according to a rule; if he had appeared before, Chriſt would have dealt with him accordingly, but becauſe it did not appear therefore he was received.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſeals ſo adminiſtred unto ſuch perſons, if they look at Gods inſtitution, or the ſcope of the adminiſtration of the Church, it is the end of the ſacrament or ſeale, and according to the proper work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat proceeds from the nature of it, for the nature of it is onely to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiver; it doth and will ſeal up the covenant of grace to them that worthily receive it; if we look at it in it ſelf, it is to ſeale up and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to the worthy receiver; it doth and will ſeal up the covenant of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111041:32"/>grace, and it doth it, and not failes to them that are fit: Gods means uſed in Gods manner never faile of Gods end.</p>
            <p n="5">5. No unworthy receiver may ſo farr croſſe the end of a ſacrament, as that which is a ſeal of confirmation, being rightly uſed; through his ſin, may be a means to agravate his condemnation by reaſon of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of it; he may ſo harden himſelf, as he may increaſe his ſin, and ſo his curſe; mark this, the ſacrament in the end and work of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, as a ſacrament, it onely does ſeale, and it intends to ſeal and confirme the Covenant to them that believe; but this does not hinder, but an unworthy receiver may croſſe the end, and make it po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon to himſelf, <hi>He may eat and drinke his own damnation:</hi> but this does not alter the courſe of the ſeal in it ſelf conſidered, if we look at it in the end God and the Church aym at in it, for that is to ſeale to the worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver; but by reaſon of their own ſin, they alter it, and ſo ſet a ſeale to a blank: thus it carryes a double ſence with it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſay it is the end in God or the Church, or the work of the ſacrament, in its own nature, to ſeal up the covenant to unbelievers, is a groſſe errour; the Church of Chriſt never thinks ſo, but as God and the Church, and the ſacrament it ſelf ayms, it doth not ſeal to an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever; but if this be their meaning, to adminiſter the ſeale to ſuch as are unworthy receivers, and if we abuſe the ſacrament by putting the ſeal to a blank, this God warrants; and this the Church does, if that be the meaning, it is ordinary to themſelves to doe it: the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſte</hi> doe ſo themſelves, and the Church doe warrantably in ſo doing. Carry this with you, the Sacrament, look what it doth of it ſelf, it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſeals up the covenant of grace to believers: hypocrites receive it to their peril, but that the ſacrament intends, is the ſame: for inſtance; Take a Prentice that is bound for ſo many years, it may be, he in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters abſence, gets his Indenture and brings it forth, and goes and ſets up his trade within two years, at laſt it comes to light, and although he have the ſeal of the Corporation that will doe him no good, becauſe he dealt not faithfully nor ſincerely, in the getting of his Indenture he deprived himſelf of the benefit; ſo it is here, the ſcope of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the end of it is to ſeal up the covenant: the Church cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne; a man may come in a counterfeit manner, they put to the ſeale, and give the ſacrament to him as to a believer; yet he deprives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the nature of it, and the ſeal not altered; they never ſet the ſeal to ablank.</p>
            <p>Now having intrenched our ſelves by making the doctrine plain, we now prepare to meet the Adverſary. We will now therefore ſhew
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:111041:33"/>Mr. <hi>Spilsberyes</hi> reaſons, they be nine in number; and becauſe we will not miſtake we will read them, as they are in the book. Firſt, There is neither command nor example in the New Teſtament for the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Infants: the ſumme of his argument is this, if there be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand nor example in the New Teſtament, then it is unlawfull.</p>
            <p>Both the parts are falſe: for if there be warrant in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, there is ground enough to ſetle any mans conſcience to doe it, for it is too narrow to tie men onely to the New Teſtament, neither have we ground ſo to doe; if we have a warrant in the Old Teſtament. we may be incouraged to doe any thing; for the whole rule of God is to be attended, and the Old and New are both equall, and therefore both together; and either of them alone is enough to bear us up in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing we have to performe to God: there are many things in the Old Teſtament that are not ſo in the New, God having regard to the people and time of the Jews that they lived in; for they were in their nonage and ready to be taken aſide, God deals with them as with chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren new come to ſchoole; he would have them ſpell out his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, he doth point them with the feſcue, he builds up the partition wall, they were in their weaknes, and for this God does it that they might not be led aſide; therefore in the generall it is falſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.3 4 When they were to paſſe out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſee how exact God was to ſhew them his mind; <hi>Let every man take unto him a Lamb, according to the houſe of his fathers; if the houſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld be to little for the Lamb, he ſhall take his next neighbour, &amp;c.</hi> See how God leads them, for the lamb, and the number and the perſons that muſt cate, which was next his neighbour, this God did, becauſe the people were raw; thus God ſpels out every tyllable to them, and tels them point by point; but in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when he ſpeaks of the Supper of the Lord, when the people were able to underſtand how to come, he is not ſo exact, neither is there any example; neither is there precept or example in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ever a woman ſhould receive the Supper of the Lord; yet I hope, none will be ſo void of ſence, as to ſay, therefore it is unlawfull for women to receive the Supper of the Lord; it would be weakneſſe of brain, and to be forſaken of common ſence to ſay ſo: ſo although God did ſo in the time of the Law as to ſpeak to the number of the perſons, and who they ſhould be, yet it is not ſo in the times of the Goſpel: but the way is plain in the New Teſtament; and therefore it is miſerable weakneſſe, and ſo in <hi>Leviticus</hi> 18. There the Lord ſpeaks of unlawfull marriages, for number and nature of them in a large man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; but it is not mentioned in the New Teſtament, but when men
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:111041:33"/>come to diſpute of them, they goe to the old Teſtament. Is any ſuch a wiſeaker as to ſay, thoſe degrees of marriages are not forbidden now in the new Teſtament, when they be condemned in the old, although the new Teſtament ſayes nothing of them, when as it is ſaid, the land ſpued out thoſe nations that were before them becauſe of that; and God tels them ſo, that they might not be taken aſide therewith; and God doth not ſpeak of them at all in the new Teſtament: and therefore to ſay it is unlawfull, becauſe it is not commanded, or have ſome example for it in the new Teſtament, it is notoriouſly falſe; for it is though if we have a warrant out of the old.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond part alſo is falſe: <hi>But</hi> (faith he) <hi>there is no command nor example in the new Teſtament.</hi> For the underſtanding of it, take a caſe, and we will prove that it is falſe. Now to open the thing, we muſt underſtand, in the word we ſhall find a thing may be ſaid to be found two wayes: Either in the letter, or included in the ſenſe: it is included when what ever by the ſtrength of the Rule, or rationall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference can be brought out of the Scripture by neceſſary circumſtance, that is Scripture, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2, 24. <hi>And they ſhall be one fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh:</hi> and when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeakes of it, he ſaith, <hi>They two ſhall be one fleſh.</hi> But it is not ſo in <hi>Geneſis. Matth.</hi> 19 5. <hi>And they two ſhall be one fleſh.</hi> And ſo <hi>Mal.</hi> 2 15. <hi>And did he not make one?</hi> And <hi>why did he make but one, ſeeing he had abundance of the Spirit.</hi> He could have made three or foure women for one man, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at he would learn to keep one to one, therefore he did it. When Chriſt had to deal with the Sadduces, he tels them, <hi>They erre, not knowing the Scriptures, Matth.</hi> 22 31. He proves the reſurrection by this, <hi>God is the God of Abraham, of Iſaac, and of Jacob, he is not the God of the dead, but of the living.</hi> Now if you look on the words of the promiſe, <hi>To be their God,</hi> there is no word of the reſurrection ſpoken of, but only it is neceſſarily included in the covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> when they were dead they lived with him; and becauſe whole <hi>Abraham</hi> had the promiſe, therefore <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> body muſt live again. Therefore this is Scripture although the letter be not there at muſt be ſo there from the ſtrength of diſpute. The body muſt riſe, and every one that believes ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Sarah,</hi> and <hi>Thomas,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> believing ſhall be ſaved, though it be not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſo in the letter, their names are not named; yet it followes, that <hi>Sarah,</hi> or <hi>Thomas,</hi> or <hi>John</hi> believing, ſhall be ſaved. But ſome of them deny this, and he doth ſeem to deny it alſo, but that he dare not in plain words do it, becauſe that would be ſo groſſe, men would ſtop their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes at it. But he hath ſome ſuch expreſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for he ſaith, <hi>The old Teſtament
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111041:34"/>hath it commanded; and ſo the ten commandoments forbid all ſin, and command all duties, although they be not named: the ſecond comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement forbids all falſe worſhip that is ſpoken of in the Scriptures.</hi> Now to apply our ſelves to the baptizing of Infants, there be texts that it is to be inferred from, although it be not expreſſed in ſo many words. For we may as well reaſon, that no woman ſhould receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe there is no expreſſe word for it; but in the Rules of the Goſpel it is inferred. I will make it appeare, if there be as ſure grounds for the title of children to the Sacrament, as to the parents, then they may be made partakers of it as well as the parents: but ſo there is, and therefore they may. Are the parents in covenant? So are the children. 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 7.14. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. of which we have formerly ſpoken, and ſhewed the title is the ſame to the ſeales, and ſo we ſee both the parts of his Argument are falſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 2. <hi>It is a high contempt put upon Chriſt, to force an unnaturall wife upon him, one that is impure, he being a pure and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall husband; for where there is one in the Spirit, there is twenty in the fleſh.</hi> This is the frame of the Argument, To force a Spouſe upon Chriſt that is naturall, he being ſpirituall, is a contempt: But to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize infants is to force a Spouſe upon Chriſt that is naturall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a contempt to him; becauſe that in the Church children are founded upon naturall birth. The firſt part is granted, the ſecond part is falſe. To force a naturall ſpouſe upon Chriſt, is unlawfull, that is granted: But the ſecond part is falſe, and the Argument is worſe, that the baptizing of Infants make a godleſſe Church. For firſt, that children are graceleſſe, none can prove: if they be graceleſſe, if they die in their infancy, they muſt periſh, for they are out of Chriſt; but they dare not affirm that themſelves, &amp; it hath been proved, that God hath provided a portion of glory for infants, and it is certain, that all that are elect infants, that die in their infancy, God doth work faith in their hearts, and therefore it is groſly falſe, and the weakneſſe of it appeares thus, Our children in the time of the Goſpel, are the ſame with them among the Jewes, and God did joyn them to Chriſt as he does now, there is the ſame reaſon now as then.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The baptizing of Infants doth not make them members of the Church, for they are members before they be baptized, and baptiſme doth but ſeale up the covenant unto them; for baptiſme ſuppoſes they if in the body firſt; and the proof of it is more groſſe then the other: he he will diſpute it, he muſt prove it, becauſe ſuch a Church is founded upon naturall birth, all children of believers are by nature the children
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111041:34"/>of wrath, that they come to have an intereſt in the covenant, it is not by birth, but by their parents covenanting with God, he does it as he ſees fit; it doth not come by birth or propagation, but by vertue of the covenant with the parents, and God does it as hee ſees fit, ſo it is a groſſe miſtake. Now gather it up, children are federally holy, becauſe they come of holy parents; they are holy becauſe of the covenant which they receive, God brought them in becauſe he loved them, and he loved them becauſe he loved them; and becauſe he loved them, he choſe them; and becauſe he choſe them, he brought them into cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and therefore meerly of grace: So that men are or will be blind, if they doe not ſee this.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>It is a practice that doth overthrow the body of Chriſt, or the Temple of God, and ſo a Nation may be corrupted, and may make the godly a ſcorn and contempt.</hi> The Argument lies thus, That which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the Body or Church of Chriſt, that is unlawfull: But the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of infants does deſtroy the Body or Church of Chriſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is unlawfull, for it will make a nationall and carnall Church. He ſayes ſo, we may ſay it is not ſo; and our ſaying is as good as his. But I ſay, the firſt part is true: but that baptizing of infants makes a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Church, that I deny; for it will not follow: but the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of a nationall Church did belong onely to the Jewes, and there fore it had nationall ordinances, they were to meet three times a yeare before the Lord; and they had nationall Officers, the High Prieſt, and all the males were bound to appeare three times a yeare, ſo all was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall: but now it is not ſo, but they are particular to particular churches, and particular ordinances, and particular officers, the Paſtor and Teacher is or ought to be in their own congregation; and though children are baptized, they are made members of a particular congregation. And beſides, a Nationall church in it ſelfe does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the body of Chriſt: For that which God hath appointed for his church, that doth not deſtroy the church; for then God may be ſaid to deſtroy the church: but that were blaſphemy to ſay ſo. But now all are in a particular church. And the ſecond part is as falſe, that it brings in graceleſſe members into the church; for the baptizing of infants is no cauſe of it, for that does not make them, but ſeales up the meanes of grace to them, as God ſayes, they are <hi>under his wing. What could I have done more for them? Deut.</hi> 6.18. God brings them into manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, he hath them in his hands as plants of his embracing in the means of grace: if they bring infants into the congregation, they bring them under the meanes, and God ingages himſelfe unto them. The reaſon
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:111041:35"/>the Gentiles grew wild, they wanted meanes, Pagans of Pagans, God takes no care of them. And beſides, will any ſay circumciſion of infants was the cauſe to make graceleſſe members, our baptiſme is the ſame.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Becauſe it is a ground of ignorance and error, to hold people in blindneſſe, and make people thinke Baptiſme is neceſſary to ſalvation.</hi> The Argument is this, That which is the cauſe of ignorance and error, and to hold the people in blindneſſe, that is unlawfull: But the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of infants is the cauſe of all this, and therefore it is unlawfull. A thing may be ſaid to be a cauſe of a thing two wayes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 When out of its own nature, or out of the action from it, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or as corrupt counſell to lead them to evill, are the cauſe of ſinne; thus to doe out of intendment to give bad counſell, is the cauſe of ſinne.</item>
               <item>2 Though of themſelves they be good, and the intendment be good, yet meeting with a corrupt heart, it makes him doe contrary: this is beyond the ſcope of the thing, it cauſes evill without a cauſe; the Goſpel is the cauſe of contention thus, as <hi>Luke</hi> 12.51. <hi>I came not to ſend peace, but rather debate, &amp;c.</hi> It is a cauſe of converſion to one, but meeting with a corrupt heart, it cauſes contention; but that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſcope of the Goſpel. And ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15. <hi>For I allow not of what I do, for what I would do, I do not, but what I would not do, that I doe, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore as I have ſaid formerly, a wicked ſervant will be worſe in the beſt family; for it inrages corruption, becauſe it meets with a corrupt heart, ſo the baptizing of infants may be a cauſe of ſtumbling to ſome, becauſe they do not ſee, and ſo it may be a cauſe of evill to ſuch.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe it is a cauſe of error, and keeps men in blindnee: Theſe are meer words, if men by ignorance or careleſnes cannot, or will not ſee; if the Paſtor be careleſſe, and there be thouſands doe not know it, the fault is their blindneſſe: For looke at the nature of this Ordinance, where it is taught they ſhall not be kept in blindneſſe, that appeares thus, The laying forth of the extent of this ordinance, is not to keep men from the underſtanding of it, or to keep them in blindneſſe, but to inform them by this, being taught, it layes forth the nature of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, it containes all that men of years have taught them, and no more. what they teach men of yeares that are to be baptized, they ſay all that, and more then that, they teach according to God, I may appeale whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the opening of the nature of this Ordinance, have not let in light to this ordinance.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:111041:35"/>
            <p n="2">2 That it keeps them in error, and makes them ſimply perſwaded of the neceſſity of baptiſme to ſalvation, it is their own fault if it be ſo, and not in the ordinance that leads them to it. Circumciſion in the old Law was to be on the eighth day, can any body ſay there lay a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſalvation upon circumciſion? God did enjoyn them to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe them, then the parents ſhall ſee it, and the nature of the thing, and therefore we ſhould keep from ſuch conceits. It is a ſeale, and does ſuppoſe the party is in covenant, they not having or having, does not make it that it cannot be deceived Laſtly, I know no judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Divine that teaches of Baptiſme, but will teach Baptiſme is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation; if any wilfully miſtake, his blood be upon his own head.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>It lifts up the ſtate of Antichriſt, by granting him this ſo chief a Corner-ſtone, and makes the Church of Rome a true Church: for where true Baptiſme is, there is a true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of the Argument, That practice that upholds the ſtate of Antichriſt, is ſinfull: But the baptiſing of infants upholds the ſtate of Antichriſt, and makes the church of <hi>Rome</hi> a true church; therefore the baptizing of infants is ſinfull.</p>
            <p>I anſwer in the generall, this reaches not the cauſe in hand: For our queſtion is not, whether baptiſme in the church of <hi>Rome</hi> be true or not, but whether it belawfull in a church that is gathered and well ordered according to Chriſt, and therefore that he ſpeakes here, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches not the cauſe. If hee condemn baptizing of Infants upon that ground, he muſt condemne men of yeares alſo: For doe but turn the Tables, that practice does uphold Antichriſt by the baptizing of men of yeares in <hi>Rome;</hi> for where true baptiſme is, there is a true church, that does confirme Antichriſt as well as this; for it is equall the one as well as the other, if the baptizing of men of yeares, then infants, one is as well to be looked at as the other, and one makes a true Church as well as the other. So as if that be an Argument, there muſt be no bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing at all, neither of the one nor the other, and ſo there come in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny abſurdities.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The argument prevailes not at all, neither for the baptiſing of men of years, nor children, for to prove <hi>Rome</hi> to be a true Church; for <hi>Rome</hi> being a true Church does not depend on this cauſe, but this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is, becauſe baptiſme in <hi>Rome</hi> is true, whether it be of men of years or Infants for where true baptiſme is, there is a true Church take it as they uſe it; but whether it be according to God that they ſhould be baptiſed or not; then it does not make that a true Church: there
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:111041:36"/>is no man can inferre it from that, if it be lawfull to baptize Infants in <hi>Rome,</hi> is it therefore a true Church? Baptiſme may be true in a true Church; but it may be ſo abuſed, that it may not be lawfull after that manner; the fault is not, that they are baptized, but it is done by an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, or a man not approved: Thus imagine a Prieſt in <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> ſhould baptize one <hi>I the name of the Father,</hi> and not the Son or Holy Ghoſt, that baptiſme is unlawfull. And now ſuppoſe that it were lawful for any to baptize, then it is lawfull for a Midwife to baptize; but it is not lawfull for her to baptize, although ſhe baptize right for the matter, <hi>In the name of the Father and Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> becauſe ſhe hath no true call to it, ſhe is not in Office ſo to do: but the queſtion is, whether it be lawfull to be done in a lawfull manner.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Many have held one of theſe opinions, and have denyed the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; children &amp; men of years may be baptized, ſo it be not in an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Church, but if it be, it is unlawfull ſay ſome, ſo ſays <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and ſome others were of this opinion, that baptiſme was lawfull for men of years, if it were not done by a Heretick; if this be granted that <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> faith, that it is unlawfull for an Heretick to baptiſe, although he doe it in a right manner, then this may bee ſomething to prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not a true Church; and although there be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in <hi>Rome,</hi> yet that doth not prove <hi>Rome</hi> a true Church; I doe ſay that opinion is true, that ſo many hold.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I ſay, the propoſition is falſe, if baptiſm be adminiſtred in a right manner by a faithfull Miniſter, yet that makes not a true Church: if an Elder in new <hi>England,</hi> that is rightly called to Office, ſhould go among the <hi>Indians</hi> and baptiſe <hi>In the name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt;</hi> if the ſubject ſhould not be baptiſed, there were a ſin, although the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance were rightly adminiſtred; but this would not follow that the <hi>Indians</hi> were a true Church: although the miniſter were rightly called, yet that does not make them a true Congregation; for a true Church is when many believers doe enter into a Covenant to walk together, in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, that is a true Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Argument, It builds faith upon humane teſtimony in matters fundamentall, ſo that they have nothing but the bare word of a man for it: the frame of the argument is this. That practice that builds faith in matters fundamentall, upon humane teſtimony, is unlawfull, but the baptiſing of Infants does ſo, and therefore it is unlawfull: for he muſt bring in humane teſtimony, and ſo the word of men muſt be in the place of the word of God. Becauſe they ſeem to place much here, and the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is ſomewhat unwonted; therefore give me leave to inlarge.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:111041:36"/>Here I will doe two things,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I will ſhew you the vanity of the argument.</item>
               <item>2. I will rip into the bowels of the argument, that you may ſee the feebleneſſe of ſuch, and how they will melt as dew before the Sun.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The vanity of the reaſon, and the weakneſſe of it appears thus, That practice that builds faith upon humane teſtimony in matters fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall, no other wayes then God doth allow, and the word war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, is not unlawfull; but the baptizing of Infants does not build them no otherwiſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Gods word dos allow in the like caſe; as in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, for that was a ſcale of the ſame covenant to them that this is to us; it is clear, that was a ſcale of the righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eouſneſſe of faith to them, and ſo is this to us, and is as fundamentall as baptiſme to us, a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall of faith: thoſe that were circumciſed in the law in their infancy as Infants, muſt prove it by their parents, it is plain; and therefore if any man will charge God with want of wiſdome, or want of care, how ſhall a childe ſatisle another but by bare teſtimony humane; every man would condemn this as helliſh blaſphemy, this is enough to daſh the argument: now we will ſearch into the ſecrets of the argument, and we will doe two things,
<list>
                  <item>1. By way of explicition of ſome paſſages in the reaſon.</item>
                  <item>2. We will make application in the firſt; you here of matters fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall, in that we muſt know three things.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Matters fundamentall touching faith, that there is one God in three perſons, Eather, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; and Chriſt the ſon of the Virgine <hi>Mary</hi> is the Saviour of the world, and that God by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit does bring his children to know himſelf, and bring them to his Son; and that his Saints are juſtified by Faith, theſe are fundamentall. Secondly, there are matters flow from theſe; if God by his ſpirit make a ſinner believe, then there is not free-will; and that we are juſtified by the active and paſſive obed once of Chriſt; and if we have title to the covenant, then we have title to the ſeals.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some matters annexed are circumſtantiall, as receiving the ſeals in this manner; there is a matter of faith, and matter of fact, faith in matters to be believed or works of mercy; matters to be believed or or done, are contained to the Scriptures; but for matter of fact, that is to ſuch a man by name, is not contained in the Scriptures, Faith comes by hearing, and is contained in the ſcriptures; but that ſuch a a man did heare at <hi>Hurford,</hi> the ſcriptures doe give no teſtimony, that this man by name, at this time and place is not contained in the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:111041:37"/>
            <p n="3">3. That a mans faith may be built upon the word, and it reſt upon the word, or that is contained in the word; the concluſion muſt be in the word, but the other part in a mans ſelfe; to build our faith on the word is enough, if one propoſition be in the word, and the other hee may finde by experience: carry theſe along with you, and you will ſee the we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>knes of the Argument: we will ſhew you the Application in three things,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Children when they doe ſurvive may receive the benefit of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme by faith, built upon the word of God, and not upon humane reaſon; they may receive the benefit of their faith built upon the word, thus inſtanced; whoſoever doe or have received baptiſme by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God to them, God on his part hath ſealed up the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to them; but children have ſo received, and therefore they have the covenant ſealed on Gods part to them; and therefore they may have the comfort of it, that they have received it on Gods part: every man that by Gods order hath the ſeale, God ſeales to him; then chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by the order of the Goſpel, have received the ſeale of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſo both are true: but how doth it appear that a childe hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, that is not to be required in the ſcriptures, but in practice; not in the Goſpel nor is required in the cauſe: for it is enough that the propoſition or concluſion be in the ſcriptures, that this is true, I will give you ſeverall inſtances. Thus it is a truth, That all children muſt honour their father and mother; and therefore every childe muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his Parents: but how ſhall the childe know that this man is his Father, or this woman his Mother; the common teſtimony is enough to the childe, for to give them obedience of faith, although it be not ſet down in the ſcriptures; that this or that man or woman is his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: and ſo in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> The Unkle muſt not marry his Neece, for that was a ſin; for all ſuch marriages is unlawfull: but how ſhall this woman know this was her Unkle? The conſtant report of men is enough in this cauſe: <hi>And remember you keep holy the Sabbath day,</hi> this was the ſeventh day from the Creation to the Jews, and the eighth day to us; but how ſhould they know which was the ſeventh day, <hi>Abraham</hi> living ſo long after the beginning of the world, and it was not written in the word which was the ſeventh day: ſo that it muſt be by witneſſe, and ſo this is enough; for the concluſion is of faith. So for the benefit of baptizing of Infants, the teſtimony of them that lived when I was baptized, is enough to ſettle me.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Men of years have not a better bottome to beare up their faith
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:111041:37"/>then children have, they may have a ſtronger, but it is the ſame for the kinde; whoever have received the ſacrament according to Chriſt hath a ſcale of the covenant; but I have ſo received it, and therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to me, may a man of years ſay now in the time of the Goſpel; now you may ſay, let him prove it? he may ſay, I have heard the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter pray over me, and ſaw him take the water and ſprinkle mee: he ſayes ſo; but it is but humane teſtimony: ſo for a childe, others heard ſo, all is but humane teſtimony; ſo for your own experience, it is more, but the ſame in kinde: humane teſtimony is the ſame ground, ſo both of them are the ſame for kinde.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The reaſon ſhews two things contrary to truth:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That knowledge of Baptiſme is a fundamentall of Faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the teſtimony of others ſtands in the place of the word of God, that I have heard or preacht in new <hi>England</hi> is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the word of God, all the particular actions that a man does, he needs not bring in proofe out of the word of God, and therefore it does not ſtand in the place of the word of God, and ſo we ſee it is falſe; I could have ſpoken more ſhort of theſe things, but that they are not u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall to the people.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Argument,</hi> The baptiſing of Infants makes the Ordinance of Chriſt a lying ſigne; for it is not to be expected in an Infant, that which this Ordinance doth call for: the argument ſtands thus, That practice that makes the ordinance of Chriſt a lying ſigne, is unlawfull; but the baptiſing of Infants makes the ordinance of Chriſt a lying ſigne, and therefore it is unlawfull. The firſt part of the argument we grant, but the ſecond part here is the old frame, a bare affirmation, but no proof that it is not to be expected, but it ſhould be proved, but here is deep ſilence: It ſhould have bin proved that God works faith in Infants are elected, that dye before they be baptiſed; and if Mr. <hi>Spilsbery</hi> will but hold to his principles, he ſhall be the man that ſhall ſay ſo, <hi>All children ſtand defiled of originall ſin, and if they be polluted, either that muſt be removed or they cannot come into heaven;</hi> if they come to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the power and preſence of ſin muſt be taken away, or elſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſeſſe nor enjoy God; and therefore either they muſt let it go, or elſe it muſt be removed; but they cannot let it goe, and therefore it muſt be removed, and where the privation is, there will be the habit; and therefore if ſin be gone, there is perfect ſanctification: and he muſt conclude ſinning to be gone, in all that be ſaved, he dare not deny it. And if they be guilty, they ſtand in need of a Redeemer; and if they be redeemed they muſt be redeemed by Chriſt, or ſome other way;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:111041:38"/>but there is no other way, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>There is no other name whereby we may be ſaved;</hi> and therefore if they be redeemed, they muſt ſhare with Chriſt in his ſatisfaction, and therefore they muſt have union with him; and if they have union, they muſt have faith, and ſo he may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to confeſſe and yeeld they have ſo.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>The ſubject of Baptiſme muſt be paſſive, but infants are not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, as the ordinance requires, and ſo not fit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The frame of the Argument is, If infants be not ſit ſubjects for bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, they are not to be baptized: But they are not fit ſubjects for baptiſme, and therefore they ſhould not be baptized; they muſt be fit to receive it, or elſe it oppoſes baptiſme. 2. It muſt be ſo paſſive, that it muſt produce a voluntary ſubmiſſion to the ordinance, he proves it hath ſuch a ſuperior work they may ſubmit to the ordinance by force, and yet not be fit ſubjects; but they muſt be freely paſſive that be fit ſubjects. Here is the old guiſe, an Argument taken and framed, but nothing proved; for the Argument is more falſe then the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They ſay they oppoſe baptiſme. If they mean an outward oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, they may eaſily be confuted; for infants doe not ſo oppoſe it. If they mean an inward oppoſition, when the Spirit workes, it takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way reſiſtance; and children doe as little oppoſe, and leſſe, then men; and when the Spirit comes, he findes leſſe oppoſition in them, then in men; and they are as capable by nature as men, and they are meetly paſſive in that, as well as children: for the Spirit works in us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us; he takes away ſin, and puts in a principle of life: ſo he can ſeal us without us. If they ſay there muſt be ſuch a taking away of oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as frees them from ſinne, and hath ſaving grace: That is falſe; for <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was baptized, and yet he had it not: and therefore take it in what regard you will, there is no more reaſon why children ſhould not, then why men ſhould not.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It muſt be a free and voluntary ſubjection: if they muſt expreſſe it outwardly, it is not required in all thoſe that receive the ſeale, no more then circumciſion was here; if they mean freely and willingly to take the ſeale, that is not enough: for there are many will ſubmit, that are not fit for the ordinance, as they doe to the Supper of the Lord. If they ſay they muſt have the power of ſaving grace, that is falſe; for <hi>Johns</hi> hearers had it not: but if they mean federall holineſſe, then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant is holy thus.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>It oppoſes the words of the Text, by ſaying children are conceived in grace,</hi> Pſalm 51.5. <hi>What a thing is it to hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men ſay they are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:111041:38"/>and ſubjects of grace, when God ſayes they are children of wrath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The frame of the Argument is, That practiſe that oppoſes the word of God, is ſinfull: But the baptizing of infants doth oppoſe the word of God, and therefore it is ſinfull. That he ſayes, proves nothing; hee had as good ſay, what unholy men ſay, that infants are clean from the womb, we have often met with ſuch things, and it were enough to gainſay it onely, for it is falſe.</p>
            <p>That I ſay to his proofe is:
<list>
                  <item>1. No man ſayes infants are holy; but there is no more holineſſe required in us, then in the time of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that does not oppoſe the word: <hi>For Adam beg at a ſonne in his owne likeneſſe.</hi> And <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6. <hi>The frame of mans heart is evill, and onely evill continually. Pſalm</hi> 51.5. <hi>I was born in iniquity, and in ſin hath my mother conceived me:</hi> Then by the word of God infants had holineſſe required, and therefore it was not croſſe to the word; we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no other holineſſe then they did.</item>
                  <item>2 If he or any Anabaptiſt can bring any writings that doe maintaine they are not born in ſinne, by any that oppoſe their deluſions, then they ſay ſomewhat; but they have not, nor cannot: nay, the moſt of them, their old generation, deny originall ſinne to be in infants, though the younger bluſh at it to own it; but the old deny it, and ſay, they ſinne by imitation, and that their ſin is theirs, and their fall is theirs, it may ſilence impudence it ſelfe.</item>
                  <item>3 All the holineſſe we attribute to them, is not by nature, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe all born of ſinfull parents, and are polluted with originall ſinne by nature: all the holineſſe we aſcribe unto them, is not by nature, not by propagation, but that which is their parents, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. <hi>But thou art a holy people unto thy God, the Lord thy God hath choſen thee to be a pretious people unto, himſelfe, above all people that are upon the earth.</hi> And hence they are called <hi>the naturall branches, Rom.</hi> 11.24. <hi>For if thou waſt out of the Olive tree, which was wild by nature, and waſt grafted contrary to Nature into the right Olive tree, how much more ſhall they that are by nature be grafted in their own Olive tree?</hi> So as we look at no other holineſſe but what the Word ſayes, and hath ſaid from the beginning in <hi>Moſes</hi> time; ſo as what he ſayes is falſe in this kind againſt us.</item>
                  <item>4 When he addes, <hi>It is no error to ſay they are ſubjects of grace,</hi> if he hold to his principles he muſt ſay ſo; for he ſayes they are ſaved, and to ſay ſo, is to ſay they are freed from the power and preſence of ſin: for if they have either of both, they cannot be ſaved; but he ſayes ſo when he ſayes they are ſubjects of grace. For if they be ſubjects of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:111041:39"/>grace, they are ſubjects of glory; and if ſubjects of glory, they muſt be ſubjects of grace: <hi>For no unclean thing ſhall enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven.</hi> He dare not deny that, for if he doe, be muſt deny that which the word doth affirm.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And now we have done with all his Arguments; and wee ſee the Batteries raiſed againſt this Doctrine, and by what hath been ſaid, I doubt not but underſtanding men in the congregation, may be able to give an anſwer.</p>
            <p>Now we come to the reaſons of the point, which are foure,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That practice that is commanded in the Word, is lawfull: But ſo is baptizing of the Infants of thoſe that are in covenant; and therefore it is lawfull. It is contained in the Word either inplain words, or may be neceſſarily inferred from the words: I here expreſſe it may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily inferred, to let you ſee that it is ſuch a dreame to ſay there is nothing Scripture but that which is expreſſed in ſo many words: For it may be neceſſarily included, although not plainly expreſſed. And that this is ſo, we may ſee it in the New Teſtament and in the Old: That it is included, ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19. <hi>All power is given to me in Heaven and Earth; Goe therefore and teach all Nations, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. Goe and teach, is, Goe and make Diſciples,</hi> ſo is the word in all Nations. Now they had Authority to plant churches, and to baptize them: I reaſon thus, if Children be included in thoſe that are to be made Diſciples, then they are to be made partakers of the Seales of the Covenant: But Children are made partakers of the Covenant of the parents; and therefore it warrants the Seale to bee given to the Child; if the warrant be alike to the one as to the other, then the child may be partaker of it as well as the parents; if the parents be in covenant, the children be in covenant, and made Diſciples: All the difficulty lies in the ſecond part, That children are in covenant, if chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be in the covenant and included; we will open the place in three things,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 What is meant by <hi>All Nations.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 What is meant by <hi>Teaching.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 What it is to <hi>make Diſciples.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1 When Chriſt ſends them to all Nations, hee doth difference the Nation of the Jewes from all other Nations; for his Church was there then, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.10. <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with every Nation, neither have they knowledge of his Judgements.</hi> And he ſaith, <hi>You onely have I known of all the Nations of the world.</hi> It was that unconceiveable
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:111041:39"/>goodneſſe of God to them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.32, 33. <hi>Inquire of the dayes that are paſt, which were before thee, ſince the dayes that God created Man upon the earth, and ash from the one end of heaven unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if there came to paſſe ſuch a great thing as this, or whether any ſuch thing hath been heard, Did ever people heare the voyce of GOD ſpeaking out of the fire, as thou haſt heard?</hi> So as there was never ſuch a thing; for God took them out of all Nations: His Ordinances muſt be in this Nation, all muſt come for any Ordinances to them. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. <hi>But if a ſtranger dwell with thee, and will obſerve the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over of the Lord, let him circumciſe all the Males that belong unto him, and thou let him come and obſerve it; and then hee ſhall bee as one that is borne in the land: For no uncircumciſed perſon ſhall eat thereof.</hi> So as none may partake untill they be in covenant. And <hi>Iſai.</hi> 56.4.5. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord unto the Eunuches that keep my Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and chuſe the thing that pleaſeth me, and take hold of my cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, even to them will I give in my Houſe, and within my walls, a name better then of ſonnes and daughters: I will give them an everlaſting Name that ſhall not be put out.</hi> So as we ſee, all muſt take hold of the covenant, thoſe that were Jewes borne, were in the covenant, and muſt be circumciſed, and ſo all other that will become Jewes, muſt take hold of the covenant, and ſo be circumciſed.</p>
            <p>Now Chriſt hath all power given to him in heaven and earth, now he enlarges his Kingdome, and therefore he ſends to all before. <hi>In Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah was God known, and his Name was great in Iſrael. He hath not dealt ſo with any Nation. Acts</hi> 10 35. <hi>But in every Nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteouſneſſe, is accepted of him.</hi> Hee doth not ſhut up himſelf to them, but now he fends them to all.</p>
            <p n="2">2 What is meant by <hi>Teaching:</hi> He teaches no other thing for ſubſtance then what <hi>Moſes</hi> had taught, and the types held forth, and the Prophets foretold Chriſt comming in the fleſh, which was fulfilled in his comming: for Chriſt was held forth in the Goſpel, Law and ſhall be to the end of the world; the manner of diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is altered, but the ſubſtance is the ſame. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22. <hi>Wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing to ſmall and great, ſaying no other thing then thoſe that Moſes and the Prophets did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y hould come to paſſe,</hi> to wit, <hi>that Chriſt ſhould come.</hi> So as it was foretold there, and revealed here. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. <hi>It is a ſmall thing that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſhouldſt be my ſervant, to raiſe up the Tribes of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and to reſtore the deſolations of Iſrael. I will alſo give thee a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayſt be my ſalvation to the end of the world,</hi> It is the ſame Chriſt and Covenant that they muſt teach.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:111041:40"/>
            <p n="3">3. What is meant by making of Diſciples? to train up people to follow Chriſt in the way and worſhip of Chriſt: Diſciple, is called Chriſtian; <hi>Go make Diſciples:</hi> not to aſſent outwardly to the truth, but alſo give probation to the truth: for there be many, that may be in Chriſt and ſeem to be informed, that the way of the Goſpel is holy, but they dare not come in to hold it forth, for when they come to hear Chriſt ſay, <hi>The foxes have holes, and the birds of the ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have neſts, but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head:</hi> no more of them, <hi>Joh</hi> 6.60. <hi>Many therefore of his Diſciples when they heard this, ſaid; this is hard ſaying, who can hear it?</hi> And when he came after to pinch them upon the narrow in the 66. verſe, it is ſaid, <hi>Many of his Diſciples went away, and walked no more with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. They muſt be qualified that muſt receive the ſeals, he muſt be ingrafted in a covenant for him and his; we ſhould ſuffer them to come in if he be a Diſciple ſo ingaged in Covenant or for them; and therefore this is as the preſſe money to the ſouldier: and here is the main, it is the ſame covenant with the Jews, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.43. <hi>Therefore, I ſay unto you, the kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you, and ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a nation that will bring forth the fruits thereof:</hi> That is the covenant of the Goſpel; ſo as the kingdome of God is the ſame to Jew and Gentile, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.11. <hi>But I ſay unto you, that many ſhall come from the Eaſt and from the Weſt, and ſhall ſit downe with</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>in the kingdome of heaven:</hi> that is, they ſhall have the ordinances into all the world; ſo as it is the ſame covenant that was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> at the firſt: the Jews ſhall be caſt out; and as the kingdom is the ſame; ſo the Gentiles are incorporated upon the ſame terms as the Jews were, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould be inheriters alſo of the ſame body, and partakers of his promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel:</hi> ſo we ſee God did reveal the Gentiles ſhould be fellow heirs of the ſame body, as the Jews had; as the Jews had royall priviledges, ſo the Gentiles ſhould ſhare in the ſame corporation into Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Now therefore you are no more forreigners, but Citizens with the Saints and houſhold of God:</hi> ſo as you are fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Citizens of the ſame houſe and corporation, and have the ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges; and they ſhall have all theſe in a viſible covenant: ſee all in the context; as the Gentiles ſtood in oppoſition, the partician wall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in uncircumciſion, and the Gentiles known to be Gentiles: as he was made before he was in a viſible Church; now when one is in a viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible covenant, that makes them differ; for it cannot be meant of a ſpirituall work, for all the work of circumciſion was never thus; for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:111041:40"/>then it muſt have been upon all that were circumciſed, but we know it was not ſo, for all of them had not Chriſt; but it is meant, a viſible Covenant which the body of the Jews were made partakers of, and ſo of the Gentiles; if it were ſpirituall then the Jews were un-Chriſted, but the cauſe is cleare: As the Jews were in a viſible covenant, ſo it ſhould be now in like manner unto all people. Mark, they covenant for themſelves and children as the Jews did; and he is a Diſciple that is thus quallified, now Baptiſme is the preſſe-money; ſo as we ſee what the meaning of Chriſt is. Now he intends they ſhould <hi>goe to all nations and teach them,</hi> that is, enlighten their judgements, and as they had right to the covenant, ſo had their children right to the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of their parents: Why? becauſe they were made Diſciples, they were taught: becauſe Chriſt hath received all power, and all power being given to him; now we are able. Thoſe parents who are made Diſciples, they are incorporated for themſelves and children as the Jews were into the covenant: Now the Jews were incorporated for themſelves and children, and ſo bee thoſe that are made Diſciples. Now the firſt of theſe is not denyed, they that were made Diſciples ſhould be incorporated, but all that are made diſciples and are incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, are as the Jews were: and therefore as the children of the Jews were included, and ſo had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight to the ſeals, ſo have wee, by <hi>Goe and teach;</hi> thoſe that be taught as before, muſt be baptized: Firſt, it muſt be publiſhed, that ſo they may approve of it, and then engage themſelves, and then all that belong to them as parents: ſo as if it be demanded for whom they doe enter Covenant? it is true, Parents doe it actually, but not for themſelves onely, but for all thoſe that ſhall come of them as parents. As take a parent, he makes a bargain, and draws a covenant, and makes it ſure to himſelf; the childe hath not made this covenant, ſhall he therefore have no benefit by it; is any ſuch a wiſeaker, to think when the father was alive, and concluded it, that he did it for himſelf, but not for his children; the ſame is here: The father expreſſes the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but the children are included, and in common ſence the children may claim a right. If any plead &amp; ſay, it is not your right, you were not born then he may ſay, it was for me the covenant was made, and it will hold in any court: this is the dream of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> againſt common ſence; but heare this yee that turn proſelytes, and take hold of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and take up the ſame worſhip: yee take it for children and all; and they have good right to the poſſeſſing of it: ſo it is here; if we teach the ſame Chriſt, and receive him as before, and engage out ſelves in the covenant for our ſelves and ours, then they may be baptized, for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:111041:41"/>he is in covenant, and ſo are his children.</p>
            <p>Wee gave in teſtimony to the Doctrine laſt day from the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19. <hi>Goe make Diſciples:</hi> Now we will give in Teſtimony from the Old and New Teſtament together, for they give a joynt teſtimony together; if you pleaſe, we will proportion them one with another.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the Inſtitution, all is one.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In the Application of it, we ſhall ſee the ſame ſpirit in both, and are both of the ſame authority, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. <hi>This is my Covenant which yee ſhall keep between me and you, and thy ſeed after thee: Let every man childe among you be circumciſed.</hi> Compare this with <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. <hi>Then</hi> Peter <hi>ſaid unto them; Amend your lives, and be baptized every one of you, In the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of ſins; and you ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt. For the promiſe is made to you, and to you children, and to all that are a farre off, and to as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> So as we ſee, both hold out the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Command of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Application of it; ſo <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks here, ſo as we ſee it is not onely commanded in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11. but inferred from that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant made to <hi>Abraham:</hi> Therefore thou ſhale keep my covenant, as 12. verſe, <hi>All the males of eight dayes old ſhall be circumciſed:</hi> It is by inferrence from the covenant appl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d in reaſon; it is true, it is proper to God to appoint ſacramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and ſeals, who can give the grace ſignified: it is he that may doe it, but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it is appointed, thoſe that are intereſled in the covenant by vertue of the covenant, they have an intereſt and a right to the uſe of the ſeal, or el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale hath not the end for which it is appointed: O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not the uſe of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that have right to it; then no man muſt uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>y muſt have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the ſeale; for the ſeal ſhews the cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>t, and ſhewed in the reaſon thus: That which is infe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed from the words, and contained in them, that is included, but ſo is the ſeale; and therefore it muſt be included in the text.</p>
            <p>The firſt part none queſtion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part reſts in the Text, and it is included in the Text: therefore you ſhall finde it thus;</p>
            <p>Thoſe that are inſtated in the Covenant have a right to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le into the entrance; and therefore to wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r they belong, it is to them and their ſeed; it is forced from the covenant, as if God had ſaid the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame, you have an intereſt in the Covenant, and you ſhall have the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:111041:41"/>benefit of it; I have given it to take away the ſin that is conveyed and brought to the ſoule, and the ſoule is made partaker of it untill Chriſt repeale it; they that ſhall receive the ſeale of the covenant: what circumciſion ſhews to them, the ſame does baptiſme hold forth to us; this is ſo, as nothing is more plain ſo as you have it, becauſe you are in covenant: Now you may ask why God doth appoint a ſeal of the covenant, is it for God? No: for he is faithfull, and in him there is no ſhaddow of change; but it is for our end that we may know whom to reſt our faith upon, for we are ready to ſtagger; and therefore to ſhore up our faith, the Lord gives it to ſtrengthen our faith withall. Agam, you may ſay, to whom or for whoſe good doth God appoint the ſeals of the covenant, for thoſe that are within the covenant, or thoſe that are without? Not for them that are without, but for thoſe that be within, and to all of them; for there is the ſame reaſon for all, that are in covenant, the reaſon is the ſame, and the right is the ſame to all, to the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as to himſelf; the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is, <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed:</hi> ſo as this is plain, Becauſe they have received the greater which is the covenant, therefore they may be partaker of the leſſer, which is the ſeale of the entrance: the other ſacrament, he paſſes that according to their eating, for it is a ſacrament of growth, and there muſt be examination of our ſelves; we ſee Gods command, for this he appoints, and infers it by the covenant; and as it is made for them, ſo it is applyed; <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. <hi>Then</hi> Peter <hi>ſaid unto them, amend your lives and be baptized every one of you, In the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for the remiſſion of ſins, and you ſhall receives the gift of the Holy Ghoſt. For the promiſe is made to you and your children; and to all that are afarre off, oven as many as the Lord our God ſhall call:</hi> For the uſe of it he alledges the promiſe, and applics it. When they were pricked at the heart, then he bids them <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be Baptized;</hi> and then he tells them the promiſe is <hi>made to them and to their children, and to as many as the Lord our God ſhall call:</hi> even that promiſe, <hi>I will be thy God and the Gad of thy ſeed:</hi> if God will be a God to you and your children, then doe you by the power of faith, receive the ſeale of the covenant to you and to your children: the time that was before Chriſt they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aled up Chriſt to come; but he is now come, doe you therefore by faith make it ſore: and the exhortation is made to parents that receive it to them and theirs, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.34. <hi>And let not the Son of the ſtranger, which is joyned to the Lord ſpeake and ſay, the Lord hath ſurely ſeparated me from his people; Neither let the Eunuch ſay, behold I am a dry tree: For
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:111041:42"/>thus ſaith the Lord to the Eunuches that keep my Sabbaths, and chuſe the thing that pleaſeth me, and take hold of my covenant.</hi> God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts them from this thoſe that choſe his covenant, thoſe that are made partakers of the priviledges of the church, that is, by joyning them ſelves to the church of the Jewes, they ſhall partake of the Ordinances of Chriſt that the Jewes partake of, and that is the ſame that is acted now. This is the ſtrength of the Apoſtles diſpute: If the promiſe be made to you and your children: then you may partake of the ſeale, you and your children.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles Argument runs thus, Becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> and his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were circumciſed, as a ſeale of the covenant; ſo all thoſe that take hold of the covenant, have right to the Seale for them and their children: it carries weight for weight. The Anabaptiſts are troubled with this, and quarrell much at it, and ſay, By children here is not meant infants, but children by imitation, meaning ſuch as follow the ſteps of their godly parents: As <hi>John</hi> 8.39. <hi>They anſwered and ſaid unto him, Abraham is our Father. Jeſus ſaid unto them, If you were Abrahams children, you would doe the works of Abraham.</hi> So as there it is taken in a ſpirituall ſenſe. But this makes nothing to their purpoſe. For this promiſe makes nothing to that, <hi>The promiſe is made to you and to your children;</hi> that promiſe is not the covenant, but it is another promiſe, the raiſing of Chriſt to be a Redeemer, it is Chriſt to the Jewes is meant here: ſo that promiſe will not abide it. This is that they alledge. It is true, children ſometimes are taken for imitation; but if it had been ſo in this place, he ſhould have proved it: But here is a deep ſilence, and no proofe. We further reply, the promiſe cannot be here meant, nor can it be the ſenſe of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That promiſe that is here meant, is that promiſe that gives evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and intereſt to the ſeale of the covenant: For they that have the one, have right to the other. If the promiſe be to you and to your ſeed, therefore be baptized: ſo as it is not from repentance, not bee baptized, becauſe you repent, that croſſes the diſpute: For <hi>Job</hi> did repent, and yet he had not an intereſt in circumciſion: but he muſt be Jew, if he will partake of the Ordinances of the Jewes. So in the Church of Chriſt, repentance is not the ground of the Apoſtles diſpate: but repentance is the concluſion. The covenant is to your uſe; this is Gods way for you to partake of the Seale: it is the way both for you and yours, for the covenant was before the ſeale. The promiſe is there made, and that gives an intereſt into the ſeale of the covenant; it is not the preaching of the Goſpel that gives right to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:111041:42"/>the ſeales of the covenant, but thoſe that are in the covenant, have right to the ſeales thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is confeſſed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery,</hi> that all whom God ſhall call, that have anſwered the call of the Goſpel, and make profeſſion of their faith, they have a title to the ſeales. Thoſe that are here underſtood, they pertain to ſuch as are viſibly called: But the promiſe of the word is made to them that doe not anſwer the word: it belongs to them that are called. The promiſe that Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is made known to many that never were called; but thoſe that are in the covenant of the Church, the promiſe is made for the good of them and their feed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If by children we ſhould take men of yeares that follow the faith of their parents, we ſhould croſſe the letter of the Text, and the Apoſtle who makes three degrees; <hi>To you, your children, and thoſe that are far off:</hi> If the Text run thus, The promiſe is made to you and to all that God ſhall call, &amp; that anſwer the call; it croſſes the ſcope of the Text, for it is <hi>you and your children, and as many as are afarre off,</hi> all three, and therefore that interpretation cannot ſtand. If a man have but an humble heart, the words are ſo plain, it will carry away the heart, it goes from parents to children, to thoſe that ſhall be called hereafter, when they come in as you and your children are, then they and their children ſhall have it as you and your children have it, and not before. Now we will cleare this from all gain-ſayers.</p>
            <p>They ſay, Infants of believing Parents may not receive it, becauſe they have not ability to receive that ſpirituall good of the Seale; or if they be able, God would not have them receive it: But neither of them are true, or can begranted, therefore they have a right to it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are capable to receive the ſpirituall good of the ſeale, and that appeares thus, If children in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time were able, then chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are able now: But the children were able then, and ſo they are now. The ſecond part of the reaſon is moſt queſtionable; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery</hi> ſayes, the ſeale of baptiſme is the ſeale of the covenant of grace, but that to <hi>Abraham</hi> was but of outward priviledges. But conſider what hath been ſaid before, if the children now be as able as before, if there be the ſame v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue of the ſeal of the covenant as then, &amp; as much requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then as now; (for it was to receive the good of the righteouſneſſe of faith) then it muſt be the ſame now: but it was Chriſt that the hand of the child did receive, and the covenant of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſealed it, the ſeale is one to them that did not believe, as to them that did believe, as it was to <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> and if they abuſe it, it is their ſin, if they refiſt, I
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:111041:43"/>know not how to avoid it: But they had as much as we, and they were as able to improve it; God did now appoint it: but to ſay God would not have them have it, were to impeach his care, to bring them into covenant, and not be willing they ſhould receive the grace of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and if not, he ſhould be willing to croſſe his fatherly love in Chriſt: but Chriſt he bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th his children, and brings them to heaven, and therefore he will deny them no ordinance that may ſerve to that end.</p>
            <p>If it be unlawfull for children to be baptized now, then the grace of Chriſt is of leſſe force then it was before, or of leſſe extent, but that is ſinfull, and therefore it is an error to ſay ſo, either that it is of leſſe force or of leſſe extent, or to ſay that now it is to men onely: the two parts are plain, that it is not of leſſe force, or of leſſe extent then it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>'Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>We have alſo a moſt ſure word of the Prophets, to the which you doe well that ye take beed, as to a light ſhining in a dark place untill the day dawn and the day-ſtar ariſe in your bearts.</hi> They were before in the ſhadow in compariſon; but now the day-ſtarre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, that is, the Ordinances, according as they are called, better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p>If M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Spilsbery</hi> ſays, the grace of Chriſt is ſtraitned, for all that was before, was fleſhly, it was a fleſhly and carnall covenant; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, It is the ſame now in the time of the Goſpel; the ſeale is the ſame, the covenant is the ſame, the intereſt is the ſame as in circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. If he ſay, <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was circumciſed; I ſay, ſo was <hi>Simon Magus</hi> baptized, and ſome other, and yet were naught: So as to deny it, is to deny the Sun to ſhine, or to deny the incarnation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Uſe is three-fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Of <hi>Inſtruction.</hi> Here we may ſee, and for ever magnifie the bounty &amp; compaſſion of the fatherly love of God, in ſtooping to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of his people; ſo that no weaknes of faith, or want of years, can hinder the compaſſion of God towards them, but he takes meaſure of all our wants: Art thou weak in faith? It may be ſome heavineſſe to thy ſelfe, becauſe thou canſt not conceive of thy eſtate, ſo as others can; but although thou beeſt weake, yet this hinders not the love of God to thee: For he loveth the little ones, and therefore the little ones may be comforted; for God denies no good to children, but even thoſe little ones are deare to him. God and Chriſt are carefull over them, as a good Shepheard who will be carefull over the young and tender of the flock, to feed them by the budding graſſe; the weak ones they ſhall
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:111041:43"/>feed by the tender budding graſſe, &amp; by the running waters. This is the great indulgence of God to his, and his marvellous care over his; and therefore let not the weak in faith, or a child ſay. God is not carefull of me: for God will gather his out-caſts, he hath mercy &amp; compaſſion for you. God is in the Reer-ward, nay he is in the Front and Reere too, he hath an eye to the ſick, weak, poor &amp; dead creatures; for he doth not only go before his, to incourage them, and inable them; but he is with them in the Reere, and he will gather them up alſo; he will hearken to them, &amp; wil gather them as the good Shepheard will take the little ones in his armes, and carry them tenderly; you that are little in your owne eyes, you that are in covenant with Chriſt, he will lead you and your little ones tenderly, and ſo he will all that are little in their owne eyes, and the eyes of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſhews, the deſperate deluſion of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> ſee how injurious they are to the comforts of Gods people: they ſtop us of the living ſprings of comfort, of the favour and faithfulneſſe of God: it choaks the channel of the freſh ſprings that are in God, for God hath little freſh ſprings, as for men, ſo for children: he can heare the one and the other, this to ſhewes the great care God hath of his; baptiſme is a freſh ſpring. It did ſhew the malice of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> to ſtop the Wells; and it was their cruelty ſo to doe: ſo doe the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> they ſtop the Wels to many poore little ones, for there are many that ought to have it; the father and the mother are in covenant, many that cannot goe themſelves to God to call him theirs: but as it is ſaid of <hi>Moſes, He ſought the God of his Fathers;</hi> how came he to bee his God, he looks at him as the God of his fathers; ſo we are not able to goe to God, but in the Covenant of our fathers: But the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> would knock of our hands here, and ſo they would be a means to ſtarve the Saints of God; and are injurious to Chriſt, Father and Spirit: <hi>He that withholdeth the Corne, the people ſhall curſe,</hi> becauſe it is the ſtaffe of our lives, and many a poore man may periſh for want of it; but what will you ſay to them who deprive young ones of the food of their ſouls to whom it is due: there be many children held back by the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> they are cruell men that will hold them back from that which Chriſt hath provided for them; and God will deal with them for it hereafter, God will curſe them, and the wrath of God will be upon them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> Of Exhortation to parents to bee intreated to bring their children into covenant with themſelves; all you that deſire to feare God be you intreated to enter your ſelves and children, bring them under, the wing of God: The mother of <hi>Ruth</hi> did bleſſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:111041:44"/>God who had brought her under the wings of God, to come into covenant, Come you and your children under the wing of God; <hi>Paul</hi> complains, <hi>the dayes are evill,</hi> they are no better now. When wel are the world, if we leave our children here in trouble, this will be a comfort to them, they ſhall be ſafe from Devils; he that is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſhall be ſafe; leave them therefore under the faithfulneſſe of that God, what he hath promiſed, he will beſtow; ſuch as God hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he will mannage, and give all inlargements unto, and they ſhall have proviſion and protection from him; and therefore come into the covenant of the Church, that God may be ingaged unto you, that ſo you and yours may not run wilde.</p>
            <p>The next Exhortation ſhall be to children to lay hold of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; keep it, and lay hold of it, and never let it goe, maintain your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt by that means of the covenant of your Patents; God is the God of your Parents, keep the paſſage open and maintain it, know the God of your Fathers, and that God that pardoned their ſin, and from whom they received their good, that God may pardon your ſins, and you may receive good from him by that covenant: when trouble comes and thou begins to be in ſuſpicion, as the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22. <hi>Behold therefore the bountifulneſſe, and ſeverity of God towards them that have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alne, ſeverity; but towards thee bountifulneſſe, if thou continue in his bountifulneſſe: or elſe thou ſhalt alſo be out off.</hi> In this place he ſpeaks of the cutting off the Jews; they did reject Chriſt and were broken off from the covenant, and ſo they were broken off from God and mercy: now he mindes them of the Gentiles in the ſame Church eſtate, in the ſame body of the Church, you have the ſame priviledges, and all is gone from the Jews; behold therefore the ſeverity of God towards the Jews; the greater good we have, the greater ſin it is to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it, and the greater plagues ſhall be upon them that doe abuſe them. Chriſt was ſent among them, and they did oppoſe him; oh the ſeverity of God againſt them for this, and aſtoniſhing hand of God; view it, ſee the miſerable eſtate of the Jews, his blood is upon them and upon their children: Oh the ſeverity of God upon them, they are damned and few of them but are periſhed! Oh the ſeverity of God! what never have done, 400. years in <hi>Egypt,</hi> 75. years in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon;</hi> take heed, behold the ſeverity of God towards them, but goodneſſe to you; what? to you that were without Chriſt, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the world, and you grafted into the good and fatneſſe of the true Olive tree; if you continue in this goodneſſe, you that are wide that have godly parents, you may have hope your proud hearts ſhalbe humbled: Oh the goodnes of God towards you, if you continue
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:111041:44"/>in this! if you prize the covenant, then happy you that ever you were born; all of Chriſt is yours: but continue, take heed; if thou have a godly Parent, father and mother; if thou remaine in a ſinfull eſtate and condition for all this, it ſhall be caſier for <hi>Pagans</hi> in the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then for you; when thou ſhalt ſee thy Parents going to heaven and thou damned, mercy ſhall be for them, but ſeverity againſt thee that haſt had all thoſe helps and means: And therefore you that have the means, continue in uſing of the means ſo, as that you may bee kept near to God thereby: for if you depart away from God, woe to you that ever yee were born; let none be like prophane <hi>Eſan,</hi> let none be ſuch a prophane childe to ſell all his title to the covenant for his luſt; for he went away and cared not for the covenant: let there be no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, nor no childe that ſhall ſin againſt the Lord, and ſo ſting away the bleſſing from him; for you know, <hi>he ſought it with tears;</hi> his heart was ſo filthy that he ſold his birthright, but afterward he comes, <hi>Bleſſe me O my father, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt thou but one bleſſing?</hi> but the heart of <hi>Iſaac</hi> would not repent, and then hee would have had it, but he could not: Take heed of this, you that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave prophane hearts, that care not for theſe priviledges and bleſſings; the time will come, you will crave a bleſſing; when you ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hell gaping for you, then you will ſay, <hi>Lord bleſſe me;</hi> but then Gods heart will be hardened againſt you: for all your tears you will not repent; it will not then be in the heart of your father to forgive you, for Gods heart will be hardned againſt you; you ſhall beg, <hi>bleſſe me,</hi> but all ſhall be in vain, for you ſhall not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a bleſſing at Gods hand; take heed therefore that you provoke not God to withdraw his hand and his heart from you. The Lord hath ſaid, the men of <hi>Judah</hi> are Gods pleaſant plants, or as the word is, <hi>the plants of Gods imbracings:</hi> think of it when I am in the duſt; you are under Gods imbracings, God does lovingly apply himſelf unto you in counſels, and in the motions of the Spirit; your Parents love you in the imbracings of God: keep your ſelves here and never goe out while you live; for if you do, you will fall into ſin, and temptation, and Devils, and if theſe imbrace you, wo will be unto you, and therefore keep from theſe: but go not from the imbracings of God, and he will comply with you, and apply himſelf unto you: therefore when you come to the word, look to the covenant, doe not ſtep away from it: now you are under a Counſel or a reproof, will you withdraw from the armes of mercy? doe not, for he will comply with you, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace you through all eternity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
